<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Remedy against trouble in a discourse on John XIV, 1 : wherein something is also briefly attempted for clearing the nature of faith, of justification, of the covenant of grace, assurance, the witness, seal and earnest of the spirit, and preparation for conversion, or the necessity of holiness / by H. Lukin.</title>
            <author>Lukin, H. (Henry), 1628-1719.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1694</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 240 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 129 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A49466</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L3481</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R13639</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13137292</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13137292</idno>
            <idno type="VID">97942</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A49466)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 97942)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 426:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Remedy against trouble in a discourse on John XIV, 1 : wherein something is also briefly attempted for clearing the nature of faith, of justification, of the covenant of grace, assurance, the witness, seal and earnest of the spirit, and preparation for conversion, or the necessity of holiness / by H. Lukin.</title>
                  <author>Lukin, H. (Henry), 1628-1719.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[24], 144 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Thomas Cockerill ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1694.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signature A2, pages 67, 69-72, 89 and 141 are tightly bound; p. 102 is cropped in filmed copy. Beginning-end photographed from Cambridge University Library copy and inserted at the end.</note>
                  <note>Errata: p. [22].</note>
                  <note>Advertisements: p. [23]-[24].</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  John XIV, 1 --  Criticism, interpretation, etc.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:97942:1"/>
            <p>A REMEDY AGAINST TROUBLE: IN A DISCOURSE ON JOHN XIV.I.</p>
            <p>Wherein ſomething is alſo briefly attempted for clearing the Nature of Faith; Of Juſtification; Of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of Grace; Aſſurance; the Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Seal and Earneſt of the Spirit. And Preparation for Converſion; or the Neceſſity of Holineſs.</p>
            <p>By H. LUKIN.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Thomas Cockerill</hi> at the <hi>Three Legs</hi> in the <hi>Poultrey</hi> over-againſt the <hi>Stocks-Market.</hi> 1694.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:97942:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:97942:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>THE enſuing Treatiſe is the Subſtance of ſome Sermons, which I tranſcribed at the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of a Friend. I deſigned chiefly a Practical Diſcourſe; and if I have ſometimes fallen upon controverted Points, it is not from any delight that I take therein. I am not of <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner</hi>'s Temper,<note place="margin">2 Sam. 2:14.</note> to make a ſport of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gladiations amongſt Brethren; neither ſhould I with <hi>Alipius,</hi> have been temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to be a Spectator of the Gladiators among the <hi>Romans.</hi> As in paſſing through the Streets in <hi>London,</hi> I would not plod on without minding my way, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve to go on in a direct Line, turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing every one out of the way, without giving the leaſt place to them; but chuſe my way to eſcape the Dirt ſo far as I could, and turn my ſelf ſo as to paſs with the leaſt trouble to my ſelf,
<pb facs="tcp:97942:3"/>
or offence to others; ſo in paſſing through the World, I would not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe my way, walking at random, or at adventures; nor rudely check all that I meet with, or that ſtand in my way;<note place="margin">Prov. 19.16. Levit. 26.21. Pſalm 39.1. Prov. 4.26. James 1.27. 2 Peter 2.20. Rom. 12.18. 1 Cor. 10.32. 1 Theſ. 3.12, 13.</note> 
               <hi>but take heed to my way; ponder the paths of my feet,</hi> that I may (ſo far as I can) <hi>keep my ſelf unſpotted of the world,</hi> and eſcape the pollutions of it, and that I may <hi>(if it be poſſible) live peaceably with all men, giving none offence, neither to the Jews, nor to the Gentiles, nor to the Church of God;</hi> neither exaſperating others, nor giving others occaſion to exaſperate my ſelf. Sharp Humours diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compoſe the Soul, as well as the Body, and hinder the thriving thereof. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Apoſtle prays for the <hi>Theſſalo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians, That the Lord would make them to increaſe and abound in love one towards a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, and towards all men, to the end he might eſtabliſh their hearts, unblameable in holineſs.</hi> A Charitable frame of ſpirit tending much to the promoting there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. Yet we cannot wholly avoid treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of things that are diſputable; and it is an happy work, if any could there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by allay the Heats that are amongſt Chriſtians, and ſet them right in their thoughts about thoſe things that are controvered, both to maintain a good
<pb facs="tcp:97942:3"/>
Underſtanding and Accord among themſelves, and to direct them in their Addreſſes and Applications to God. I have endeavoured to bring Water, not Oyl to the Fire. I know Water will make unquenched Lime burn, but I hope I ſhall not meet with any of that Temper.<note place="margin">Prov. 20.18.</note> We ſhould <hi>with good advice make war.</hi> We ſhould conſider whether we are able to deal with thoſe that we undertake a War againſt. But tho we think that we are ſo, we ſhould conſider whether we have any juſt Cauſe to begin a War. There were great Preparations againſt the Two Tribes and an half on the other ſide of <hi>Jordan,</hi> the reſt of the Tribes fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that they would <hi>bring wrath upon the whole Congregation of Iſrael,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joſhua 22.18, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> but when matters came to be examined, they were pleaſed with the account that the Two Tribes and an half gave of what they had done. So many are ready to undertake a Religious War, or Diſpute, againſt their Brethren, as if they were ſubverting the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion, or undermining the Foundation thereof; but when they come to examine matters, they find there is no cauſe of ſuch heats or emo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of ſpirit; but thoſe things
<pb facs="tcp:97942:4"/>
which they are offended at, are either the private Opinions, or at leaſt the raſh and unadviſed Expreſſions of ſome particular Perſons, which the reſt of thoſe that are ſuppoſed to be of their Party do diſown. This is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ordinary amongſt all ſorts of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons; and I know no ſort of perſons that will vouch every thing which is ſpoken by all that rank themſelves among them; let every one bear their own burthen, and let not others an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer any further for what they ſay, than they have given their conſent thereto. But ſometimes we may mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake Perſons, and impute ſuch things to them as they do not believe. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny do not read mens own Works, but judge of their Opinions by what they read in thoſe that write againſt them, who often chuſe out ſuch paſſages as may give them moſt advantage againſt them, or which they can moſt eaſily anſwer, or will repreſent them as moſt blame-worthy to others, and juſtify their rough treatment of them. It is rare to find in Polemical Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, ſuch Candour and Clearneſs as is obſerved in a late Writer, Mr. <hi>Le Blanc,</hi> who in ſtating many of the Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences betwixt us and the Papiſts,
<pb facs="tcp:97942:4"/>
renders himſelf ſuſpected by ſome on both ſides; ſome Proteſtants think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing he is too favourable to the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts in repreſenting their Opinions; And ſome Papiſts have thought that he hath been partial in the account that he gives of the Doctrine of the Proteſtants; and yet both Papiſts and Proteſtants acquit him from wronging them, in ſetting down their own Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions. Now it is a great diſadvantage to any to have ſome Periods or Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences taken out of their Writings, when we do not ſee on what occaſion they write ſuch things, nor what they write in other places, which may al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay or qualify ſuch harſh Expreſſions. I have ſeen a Letter which was ſo writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, that if it were read at length every Line of it, did import one thing: but if it were ſo folded or turned down, as to hide the end of every Line, it was of a quite different tenor or ſignification. So a partial repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of mens minds, may ſubject them to great miſtakes or miſconſtructions; yea, we may miſtake men many times, tho we read their Writings our ſelves; we may ſay of the moſt Learned Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, as is ſaid of the <hi>Egyptians, They are men, and not God;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſaiah 31.3.</note> they cannot ſee
<pb facs="tcp:97942:5"/>
all things at one ſingle view; and when men are intent on one thing, they will call in the ſervice of ſome <hi>Hypotheſis</hi> which may be for their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent turn, and diſown it at another time, when they ſee that it will not well agree with ſome other Opinion which they would confirm. This is a weakneſs that I have obſerved in ſome of the moſt Learned men that I have read; eſpecially when they write much, and forget at one time what they have written at another; and it may be, have given an Interpretation of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture at one time, when it might ſerve an <hi>Hypotheſis,</hi> which they have an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered themſelves on another occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, when ſome other Point which they have been treating of would not bear their former Interpretation. There muſt be an allowance made in ſuch caſes, for mens over-ſights and infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities. Sometimes men do impute to others the Conſequences of their Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, and ſo repreſent their Opinions as very dangerous; but we ſhould not charge upon perſons what they do not expreſly own. It is true indeed, that from truth follows nothing but truth; but from ſome ſmall Error, danger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Errors may follow; and few can
<pb facs="tcp:97942:5"/>
ſee the utmoſt tendency of all their Opinions, or what Conſequences may be knit to each other. Therefore the Reſpondent, or he that Anſwers in Diſputations, muſt always be wary what he grants, or what Conceſſions he makes, leſt he ſhould be driven to an Abſurdity. As we cannot guard againſt all Accidents, ſo neither can we ſee every thing that may be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced from what we may maintain, nor the Inferences which may be mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplied from it. Sometimes men love to expreſs themſelves in Rhetorical Strains, which muſt not be brought to a rigid Teſt or Examen. It is very na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural to us to uſe <hi>Hyperboles,</hi> or Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes of Speech; yea, God himſelf frequently uſes them; they ſerving to raiſe our minds to ſome adequate con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception of thoſe things which plain words would not heighten them to. So God promiſes that he would mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiply <hi>the ſeed of Abraham,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 15.15. Gen. 22.17. Hoſea 2.17.</note> 
               <hi>as the duſt of the earth,</hi> or <hi>as the ſand on the ſea ſhore.</hi> So he ſays, <hi>He will take the names of Baalim out of their mouth, and they ſhall no more be remembred by their name.</hi> Whereas <hi>Paul</hi> doth afterwards men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion this name;<note place="margin">Rom. 11.4.</note> and it is impoſſible that it ſhould wholly depart out of
<pb facs="tcp:97942:6"/>
their mind. But he would there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by ſignify their great deteſtation of Idolatry. So where our Saviour bids his Diſciples that they ſhould <hi>ſalute no man by the way:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 10.4.</note> it is not likely that he would forbid all expreſſions of Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vility and Courteſy: but he ſeems only to warn them againſt long and tedious Compliments, and Confer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, which might retard them in their work which he ſent them about; the Prophet giving the like charge to his Servant when he ſent him in haſte:<note place="margin">2 Kings 4.29.</note> ſo in controverſial Writings there is ſomething of like nature, which we call <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by men (that they may make it ſeem that their Adverſaries depart far from the truth) run as far as they can on the other ſide, or ſay more than in a ſtrict ſenſe can be admitted. Hence it is that ſome of our firſt Reformers (the more to exaggerate the opinion of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts of the neceſſity of good works) have uſed ſuch harſh expreſſions, which are ſo liable to juſt Exception; as, that it is the firſt and the laſt, the worſt and moſt damnable Hereſy that ever was on Earth, To teach that good Works are neceſſary to Salvation;
<pb facs="tcp:97942:6"/>
and that good Works are ſo far from conducing to Salvation, that they are rather pernicious. When men will take ſuch liberty to themſelves in expreſſing their minds, they ſubject themſelves to great prejudices; but perhaps, if they were to explain them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in theſe things, they might be found to have a tolerable meaning in them. It is too well known, what dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences there have been betwixt the <hi>Lutherans</hi> and <hi>Calviniſts</hi> about the Real Preſence of Chriſt in the Sacrament. Yet about 160 years ago, when di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Learned men of both Parties met to confer about it, upon explaining their minds to each other in a calm and peaceable way, they were ſo fully agreed and ſatisfied, that they em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced each other as Brethren, and ſo parted. So that the differences among Chriſtians are not always from Error of Judgment, but a Strife of Words, through their unhappy expreſſing themſelves, and miſtaking each others minds.</p>
            <p>There is another thing which I have obſerved to be an occaſion of many diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putes amongſt us, and that is the uſe of School-terms, or terms of Art, which indeed are very compendious,
<pb facs="tcp:97942:7"/>
and ſet off mens conceptions in few words, which would otherwiſe require a large circumlocution or compaſs of Speech. Yet they have this inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nience, while men would be brief, they many times prove obſcure; and as <hi>Abbreviations</hi> in writing (which were more uſed, as is moſt likely, before Printing, when they were forced to write all) have occaſioned many er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, and multiplied various readings: ſo <hi>Abbreviations</hi> in ſpeaking, have mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplied Controverſies, and more time hath been ſpent about the meaning of ſome terms of Art, or School-diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, than would have been neceſſary to have expreſſed the ſame thing in many more words. Therefore it is rightly obſerved by the Lord <hi>Verulam,</hi> and other Learned men, that the Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumes of the Schoolmen are greater much than the firſt writings of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, from whence the Maſter of the Sentences made his firſt Collection. For while they purpoſe to abridge, they give cauſe to dilate. For the ſum or abridgment by contraction becomes obſcure, the obſcurity re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quries Expoſition, and the Expoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is deduced into large Commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taries, which grow to be more vaſt
<pb facs="tcp:97942:7"/>
than the Original Writings, from whence the ſum was firſt extracted. And whoſoever ſhall look into Polemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Writings, ſhall find that a great part of them is taken up about ſtrife of words, and many of their queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons about ſecond notions, or fitting School-terms to matters of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Hence it is that Philoſophy is made ſuch a neceſſary Handmaid to Divinity; as of old they would ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times appeal to the <hi>Heathen</hi> Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers in their Theological Diſputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, becauſe their queſtions were about ſuch terms as had been brought out of their Schools into Divinity. And hereby they do (in a manner) keep the ordinary ſort of Chriſtians in ignorance of many things, by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volving them in School-terms: as others do by locking them up in an unknown Tongue; even thoſe Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned men from whoſe Writings (as I have obſerved) the Sentences (which are the Text on which the School<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men Comment) were firſt Collected, would be as much put to it to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand their Writings, as they would be to underſtand the Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage now ſpoken in <hi>Italy,</hi> after it hath ſuffered ſuch changes through
<pb facs="tcp:97942:8"/>
the concourſe of ſo many people to <hi>Rome,</hi> but eſpecially through the Invaſions of ſeveral Nations. There are many things made unintelligible to ordinary perſons, which if diveſted of thoſe terms of Art wherewith they are diſguiſed, and cloathed in our ordinary Language, would be plain to all. Every one knows what it is to eaſe Pain, to expel Wind, to cauſe Sleep, to provoke Sweat; but they know not what is <hi>Anodyne,</hi> or <hi>Narcotick;</hi> what is <hi>Carminative, Hypno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick, Diaphoretick.</hi> Thoſe that well underſtand what is Red, or Blue, or Black, or Green, do not know the meaning of Gules, or Azure, or Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, or Vert. So in Religion, many things that are plain, are made ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure by the terms that they are expreſſed in. But if we ſee plainly that perſons are in an error, let us not exaggerate or aggravate their fault, as they do the Crimes of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lefactors in drawing up their Indict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: as if every thing that they are charged with, were done Felo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niouſly, Traiterouſly, Maliciouſly, of Set-purpoſe, out of a wicked inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; we ſhould be cautious of char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging every one with <hi>rebelling againſt
<pb facs="tcp:97942:8"/>
the light,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Job 24.13. Tit. 3.11.</note> or as <hi>being condemned of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf,</hi> that hath means which we think ſufficient to convince him. We can hardly imagine what influence the courſe of mens ſtudies, the company that they converſe with, their prejudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and intereſt, have upon their judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. Who knows the power of Intereſt? <hi>A gift blinds the wiſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 23.8. Prov. 18.16.</note> 
               <hi>and perverts the words of the righteous.</hi> It is more to blind the eyes, than to pervert the Will, or ſway the Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections. But it firſt commends a man to the favour of another, and then it determines his mind to the ſtudy or conſideration of ſuch things as do (unawares) beguile him into a good opinion of his Cauſe, ſo as he pronounces ſentence in favour of him. So Intereſt ſways mens ſtudies, and chuſes their company, and theſe inſenſibly determine their judgments. Again, it ſhould not ſeem ſtrange to us if we do not ſee all men riſe up to ſome Learned men, which we think have ſo clearly demonſtrated things, that nothing can be further objected againſt them, nor any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doubt made of them. For there are many that are not eaſily deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined in their judgements by the
<pb facs="tcp:97942:9"/>
Writings of Learned men; while they conſider, that ſuch perſons may be (and often are) influenced by their Intereſt and Affections, (which do eaſily beguiie their judgments) to ſay what they can, and can ſay al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt what they pleaſe.<note place="margin">Simon Churmay <hi>at</hi> Paris, <hi>1201.</hi>
               </note> As one that had made a Learned Diſcourſe about the Trinity (for which he was much commended and admired) ſaid, he had much confirmed and advanced the truth of Chriſt; but if he were minded to deal croſly, he knew how with ſtronger Reaſons and Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to confute the ſame. And a very Learned man (known to many that are yet living) told one (who related it to me) that he could write a Book as big as <hi>Suarez</hi> his <hi>Metaphyſicks,</hi> to prove a Deity, and then write another as big to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fute it. Theſe things conſidered, would incline us to more mutual forbear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, and Charity. Many that we look upon as erroneous (if we did rightly underſtand them) might (per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps) be found to be of our mind, and to think the ſame things with our ſelves. Others that do err, yet (as one ſaid) will not be Hereticks; that is, will not perſiſt in their er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror,
<pb facs="tcp:97942:9"/>
if they be convinced of it: which it is not ſo eaſy a matter as many imagine to be; as <hi>Auguſtin</hi> ſaid to the <hi>Manichees, They rage againſt you, that know not with how great la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour the truth is found out, and with how great difficulty errors are avoided.</hi> God hath left many things in his word clear and plain wherein moſt Chriſtians do conſent: but other things for the exerciſe of our dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, and mutual forbearance, in this ſtate of Imperfection wherein we ſee but in part.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:97942:10"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:97942:10"/>
            <head>THE CONTENTS.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <label>CHAP. I.</label>
THE Introduction and Expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of the words.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>CHAP. II.</label>
What 'tis to believe in God and Chriſt; why we are to believe in Chriſt as well as in God. That Faith is the moſt Effectual Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy againſt Troubles, becauſe 'tis the means of obtaining Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>CHAP. III.</label>
What pardon of ſin is; How 'tis obtained by Faith. Reaſons why Juſtification and Salvation are ſuſpended on believing. The bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of pardon of ſin.</item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:97942:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <label>CHAP. IV.</label>
What Aſſurance we have of pardon of ſin by Faith; how far Faith is attended with Aſſurance, and how it may be ſometimes without it. How Aſſuranc is loſt. Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections againſt getting and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining it by marks, anſwer'd. Why ſo rare a thing now. Not eaſy to be had, nor impoſſible. Of the Immediate Teſtimony of the Spirit. The Spirits witneſſing with, or to our ſpirits, what? Of the ſealing and earneſt of the Spirit.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>CHAP. V.</label>
General Obſervations to help men in the trial of their ſpiritual State. Harder for ſome to know it, than for others. Men may at ſome times ſeem better or worſe than they are; reſpect muſt be had to natural temper, and to men's Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances.</item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:97942:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <label>CHAP. VI.</label>
How Chriſtians that are ſincere may be known from others, tho they have their ſinful infirmities.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>CHAP. VII.</label>
Some Characters whereby to know our ſpiritual ſtate.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>CHAP. VIII.</label>
Faith, an Effectual Remedy againſt Troubles; becauſe thereby we have the Comfort and Benefit of the Promiſes. How we have it by Faith.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>CHAP. IX.</label>
Faith, an Effectual Remedy againſt Troubles; becauſe it gives us a view of the future ſtate.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>CHAP. X.</label>
What is required in order to believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. Nothing that may com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend
<pb facs="tcp:97942:12"/>
us to Chriſt for his accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. Nothing to make the Grace of God effectual; yet ſomething is neceſſary, and what is ſo. Whether Preparations are in our our own power? What God doth towards Converſion. Of being rightly and ſufficiently, and long enough humbled.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>CHAP. XI.</label>
Of the neceſſity of Holineſs on ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny accounts.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAg. 2. l. 12. for as r. <hi>us.</hi> p 23. l. 1. blot out the 2 <hi>d.</hi> and p 42. for pleaded r. <hi>placed.</hi> p. 73. l 8. blot out <hi>and.</hi> p. 77. l. 25. for and r. <hi>ſo.</hi> p. 83. l. 28. r. <hi>Doctis.</hi> p. 89. l. 29. r <hi>Politian.</hi> p. 94. l 25. blot out <hi>he.</hi> p. 117. l. 4. for extaſy r. <hi>exceſs.</hi> p. 119. l. 12. r. <hi>nearer.</hi> l. 28. for helps r. <hi>hope</hi> p. 125. l. 16. for were r. <hi>are.</hi> There are ſome other literal faults which the Reader may eaſily ſee to be the miſtake of the Printer.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:97942:12"/>
            <head>Books Printed for, and Sold by <hi>Thomas Cockerill,</hi> at the <hi>Three Legs</hi> in the <hi>Poultrey,</hi> near <hi>Stocks Market.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <item>A Seaſonable Diſcourſe, wherein is exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned what is lawful, during the Confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Revolutions of Government. <hi>Stitch.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Geography Rectified;</hi> or a Deſcription of the World in all its Kingdoms, Provinces, Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, Iſlands, Cities, Towns, Seas, Rivers, Bayes, Capes, Names, Inhabitants, Scituations, Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, Cuſtoms, Commodities, Government. Il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtrated with about 80 Maps. Third Edition. By <hi>Robert Morden.</hi> Quarto.</item>
               <item>Inſtructions about Heart-Work, what is to be done on God's part and on ours, for the cure and keeping of the Heart, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> by that Eminent Goſpel-Miniſter, Mr. <hi>Richard Allcyn.</hi> With a Preface by Dr. <hi>Anneſley.</hi> Second Edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. <hi>Octavo.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Evidence of things not ſeen; Or di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Spiritual and Philoſophical Diſcourſes, concerning the ſtate of Holy Men after Death: By that eminently Learned Divine, <hi>Moſes A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myraldus.</hi> Tranſlated out of the <hi>French</hi> Tongue by a Miniſter of the Church of <hi>England.</hi> Octav.</item>
               <item>A Succinct and Seaſonable Diſcourſe of the Occaſions, Cauſes, Natures, Riſe, Growth and Remedies of <hi>Mental Errors.</hi> To which is added, (1.) An Anſwer to Mr. <hi>Cary</hi> againſt Infant Baptiſm. (2.) An Anſwer to ſome <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomian</hi> Errors. (3.) A Sermon about Union. By <hi>John Flavel.</hi> Octavo.</item>
               <item>A Diſcourſe of Chriſtian Religion in ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry points; Preached at the Merchants Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture. By <hi>Tho. Cole.</hi> Octavo.</item>
               <item>A Diſcourſe concerning Liturgies, by the late Learned Divine Mr. <hi>Dav. Clerkſon.</hi> Octav.</item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:97942:13"/>A Diſcourſe concerning trouble of Mind, and the diſeaſe of Melancholly, in three parts; written for the uſe of ſuch as are or have been exerciſed by the ſame; by <hi>Tim. Rogers.</hi> M. A. who was long afflicted with both. To which is added ſome Letters from ſeveral Divines, relating to the ſame ſubject.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Geography Anatomized:</hi> Or a compleat Geo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graphical Grammar, being a ſhort and exact A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalyſis of the whole Body of Modern Geogra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy, after a new, plain and eaſy method, whereby any perſon may in a ſhort time at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain to the knowledge of that moſt noble and uſeful Science: Illuſtrated with divers Maps. By <hi>Patrick Gordon.</hi> Octavo.</item>
               <item>Love to Chriſt, neceſſary for all to eſcape the Curſe at his coming, by <hi>Tho. Doolittle,</hi> M. A. <hi>Octavo.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>An Expoſition of the Aſſemblies ſhorter Catechiſm, with Practical Inferences from each Queſtion; by <hi>John Flavel,</hi> late Miniſter of the Goſpel at <hi>Dartmouth</hi> in <hi>Devon.</hi> Octav.</item>
               <item>A Diſcourſe of ſecret Prayer, firſt Preached, and now publiſhed at the requeſt of thoſe that heard it. By <hi>Sam. Slater</hi> Miniſter of the Goſpel. <hi>Twelves.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Future State; or a Diſcourſe attemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting ſome diſplay of the Souls Happineſs, in regard to that eternally progreſſive knowledge, or eternal increaſe of knowledge, and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequences of it, which is among the bleſſed in Heaven; by a Country Gentleman, a Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipper of God in the way of the Church of <hi>England.</hi> Twelves.</item>
               <item>The incomprehenſibleneſs of Imputed Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs for Juſtification by Humane Reaſon, till enlightened by the Spirit of God, in two Sermons, preached at the Merchants Lecture in <hi>Broadſtreet.</hi> By <hi>Tho Cole.</hi> Octavo.</item>
               <item>The Almoſt Chriſtian, by <hi>Ezekiel Hopkins,</hi> late Lord Biſhop of <hi>London-Derry.</hi> Twelves.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:97942:13"/>
            <head>A REMEDY AGAINST TROUBLE.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>JOHN XIV. 1.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>Let not your heart be troubled; ye believe in God, believe alſo in me.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I.</head>
               <p>THE deſign of Chriſt in theſe Words, is either to prepare his Diſciples for receiving what he had to ſay to them in this his laſt Sermon be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his Death; For <hi>ſorrow had filled their hearts.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">John 16.6.</note> And till that is allayed
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:97942:14"/>
men are unfit to receive Counſel. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Job</hi>'s Friends ſtaid ſome time till his grief was aſſwaged, when they ſaw it great upon him, before they would ſpeak to him.<note place="margin">Job 2.13.</note> Or as Learned Men firſt lay down their Theſis, which they are to prove, and when they have proved it, reſume it again, as the Wiſe-man doth. So here he charges them,<note place="margin">Eccl. 1.2. Chap. 12.8.</note> that they ſhould not let their Hearts be troubled (thoſe things affect as much that reach the Heart either with Grief or Joy, <hi>John</hi> 16.22.); when therefore he had preſcribed Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies againſt this Trouble, he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes his Diſcourſe to his Diſciples with the ſame in effect, telling them, that he ſpake theſe things to them, that they might have Peace in him, tho they had Tribulation in the World. And as he there warns them that they ſhould have Trouble in the World; ſo in the cloſe of the Chapter, before theſe words that I have recited, he fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warns them of what ſhould happen to them; yet here charges them that they ſhould not let their hearts be troubled. So that we may hence obſerve, That Chriſt would not have his People too much lay to heart the Troubles and Diſcouragements that they meet with
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:97942:14"/>
in the World. Chriſt doth not deal with his Hearers, as the falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets of old uſed to do, <hi>ſeeing for them fooliſh viſions, and cauſes of baniſhment:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Lam. 2.14. Jer. 8.11.</note> 
                  <hi>Healing their hurt ſlightly, ſaying, peace, peace, when there was no peace.</hi> Or as Phyſicians of no value, that give <hi>Ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dines</hi> to allay Pain, but do not take away the Cauſe of it, or make their Patients believe the worſt is over, and that their Diſeaſe is declining, before it be come to its ſtate; but he gives ſtrong Conſolation,<note place="margin">Heb. 6.18 Cant. 7.9.</note> 
                  <hi>ſuch as will cauſe the lips of thoſe that are aſleep to ſpeak;</hi> ſuch as will ſupport the Soul under the greateſt Troubles, or ſuppoſing the worſt that can happen. Chriſt doth in the Scriptures deal faithfully with us, not flattering us into vain hopes of Peace and Proſperity; but ſuppoſing the utmoſt that may befal us, provides ſufficiently againſt it. As when the Apoſtle would comfort the <hi>Romans</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Afflictions, he grants the worſt,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.36, 37.</note> telling them how it had been with Good men in former times (and ſo what they muſt look for) <hi>That for Gods ſake they had been killed all the day long, and appointed as ſheep to the ſlaughter;</hi> and yet they were not only Conquerors, <hi>but more than conquerors in all theſe things,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:97942:15"/>
through him that loved them,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Phil. 4.13.</note> that is, <hi>through Chriſt ſtrengthening them.</hi> We are Conquerors when we get the Victory ſo far, as not to be foiled by Tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. As <hi>Sulpitius Severus,</hi> an Ancient Hiſtorian, ſaith, <hi>Ad Annum</hi> 303. <hi>We never overcame with greater Triumph, than when we could not be overcome with Ten Years Slaughter,</hi> which was the laſt of the Ten Primitive Perſecutions under <hi>Diocleſian.</hi> But we are more than Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querors, when we rejoyce in our Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings;<note place="margin">Acts 5.41. Col. 1.11, 24. 2 Cor. 4.17. Phil. 1.12. Pſalm 68.10.</note> When our Sufferings enhance our future Happineſs; <hi>working for us a far more exceeding and eternal weight of Glory;</hi> and turn to the furtherance of the Goſpel: This is to <hi>lead captivity captive.</hi> Now our Saviour doth fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warn them of ſeveral things which ſeem to be juſt cauſe of trouble, yet he would not have them let their hearts be troubled.<note place="margin">John 15.19.</note> He had choſen them out of the World, and thereby expoſed them to the hatred of the World. Now, while he was with them, he was (as is ſaid of <hi>Job</hi>) continually ſtrengthening them by his Words, feeding them by Miracles when there was occaſion; ſo that they lacked nothing while he was with them.<note place="margin">Luke 22.35.</note> The <hi>Jews</hi> would ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times aſſault him with captious Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:97942:15"/>
but he confounded them ſo, as they durſt ask him no more.<note place="margin">Luke 20.40. John 7.44.</note> When they came to take him, they went a way, <hi>and nonedurſt lay hands on him.</hi> But when he was gone, they were left a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, and had none to ſtand by them; yea, they thought their Hopes were gone, and they were diſappointed in them. Beſides,<note place="margin">Luke 24.21.</note> it could not but be a great trouble to them, that their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter ſhould be injuriouſly and ſhameful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly intreated, when it was ſo great a Provocation to them, to ſee him ſo ſlighted by the <hi>Samaritans;</hi> and then,<note place="margin">Luke 9.54.</note> that one of them ſhould betray him, the reſt forſake him, and <hi>Peter</hi> himſelf deny him. <hi>Judas</hi> was one of their So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety, and they ſuſpected him as little as they did themſelves; and tho he were a Son of Perdition, they might be grieved for him, as <hi>Samuel</hi> was for <hi>Saul.</hi> And beſides,<note place="margin">1 Sam. 15.35.</note> when they ſaw <hi>Judas</hi> betray him, and <hi>Peter</hi> deny him, they might not know what they ſhould do themſelves: It was time for them <hi>that ſtood, to take heed leſt they ſhould fall.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 10.12.</note> And that which would further aggra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate their trouble, was, that they look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for a Temporal Kingdom here on Earth, and could not endure to think of the Croſs; and would have had
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:97942:16"/>
Chriſt to ſpare himſelf.<note place="margin">Matth. 16.22.</note> Now, after all this, it may ſeem hard that Chriſt ſhould lay this Charge upon them, that they ſhould not let their hearts be trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled. They might think that they ought to be troubled for theſe things; yea, that they <hi>could not but be troubled for them.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 12.5. Jer. 5.3. Iſaiah 42.24, 25.</note> For we ſhould <hi>not deſpiſe the chaſtening of the Lord, as we ſhould not faint when we are rebuked of him;</hi> We ſhould take heed of both extreams. It was the Sin of the <hi>Jews,</hi> that when God ſmote them, <hi>they were not grieved,</hi> and that they did not lay his Judgment to heart:<note place="margin">1 Pet. 5.6. John 11.33.</note> We ought to <hi>humble our ſelves under his mighty hand:</hi> And we find that Chriſt himſelf <hi>was troubled at the death of Lazarus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now to all this I anſwer, That we ſhould not ſuffer our ſelves to be tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſported by any Paſſion, neither ſhould Sorrow too much affect our hearts; but as it is ſaid of Chriſt in the place now mentioned, <hi>He troubled himſelf,</hi> (So it is in the Margent, according to the <hi>Greek</hi>) we ſhould in our Paſſions be not only Paſſive, but Active, <hi>ruling our own ſpirits,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prov. 16.32.</note> letting them out only ſo far as the matter requires; as it is ſaid of <hi>Lot,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Pet. 2.8.</note> That he <hi>vexed his righteous ſoul.</hi> We uſe to ſay of Fire and Water, they
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:97942:16"/>
are good Servants if they be kept with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in their bounds; but they are bad Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters when they exceed their limits. We may ſay the ſame of our Paſſions; we may yield ſo far to ſorrow as to bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſt the mind therewith, and keep it ſteddy, ſo it will <hi>make the heart better.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eccl. 7.3.</note> But we muſt not ſo far give way there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, as to overburden our ſpirits there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, ſo as to ſink them,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 2.7. Pſal. 102. Prov. 15.13. Pſal. 77.4. Job 2.13. Neh. 8.10. Job 15.11.</note> or overwhelm them; ſo as to <hi>break our ſpirits;</hi> ſo as to make us unfit for Prayer, or unca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of Counſel; nor ſo as to weaken our hands in the Lords works; nor ſo as to <hi>ſlight his conſolations,</hi> or to give o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers occaſion to think that we have low thoughts of God, as if we could not ſatisfy our ſelves with him, and his Favour (as <hi>David</hi> did in his Troubles, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 63.3, 4.) without the Addition of outward Comforts.<note place="margin">1 Sam. 1.8.</note> As <hi>Elkanah</hi> took it ill, that <hi>Hannah</hi> could not content her ſelf with him, as better than Ten Sons. <hi>Joab</hi> looked upon it in <hi>David,</hi> as a ſlighting of his faithful Subjects,<note place="margin">2 Sam. 19.6.</note> when he was ſo out of meaſure troubled for the loſs of <hi>Abſalom.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For the <hi>Second Objection,</hi> That they are things of that nature which he had forewarned them of, that they <hi>could not but be troubled</hi> at them.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:97942:17"/>I anſwer, That as Chriſt would not deceive his Diſciples with vain hopes, but tells them the worſt before-hand: So he provides a ſufficient Remedy a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Troubles which he forewarns them of. He doth not, as ſome that take upon them to confute ſome dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous Errors, when their Arguments are weak, and not ſatisfactory, and ſo they do more hurt than good, while reciting ſuch Errors, they publiſh them to the World without a ſufficient An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, not ſufficiently fortifying perſons againſt them. But as Chriſt told them ſuch things as filled their hearts with ſorrow, ſo he provides Conſolations for them anſwerable thereto; as he doth ordinarily proportion the Conſolations of his People,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 1.5.</note> to their Tribulations. He doth indeed in this and the following Chapters, propound particular Reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies againſt thoſe ſeveral Troubles which he had warned them againſt: But the great <hi>Catholicon</hi> or General Remedy which he recommends to them, is Faith in God, and in Jeſus Chriſt. <hi>Ye believe in God, believe alſo in me;</hi> which words are not only an oppoſite <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand</hi> to what he warns them againſt (as that of Chriſt to <hi>Thomas,</hi> John 20.27. <hi>be not faithleſs, but believing);</hi> but
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:97942:17"/>
alſo a means to prevent Trouble of Mind.</p>
               <p>Some queſtion how theſe words ſhould be read, becauſe the <hi>Greek</hi> word is the ſame in both places, and may be taken either indicatively (as they ſpeak) or imperatively; that is, either decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring what they already did, or requir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what they ſhould do. So that ſome read them, <hi>Ye believe in God, ye believe alſo in me.</hi> Therefore they ſhould not let their hearts be troubled,<note place="margin">Matth. 1 16.</note> as indeed they had profeſſed their Faith not only in God, but in Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Others again read them both as a Command to believe in God, and to believe in Chriſt; becauſe they think it is not likely that he ſhould commend them for their Faith, or acknowledg that they did believe, when he blames them ſo oft for their unbelief, as <hi>Matth.</hi> 6.30. <hi>and</hi> 14.31. <hi>Mark</hi> 2.40. But when there is Faith, and that to a good degree, it may fail for a time under Temptation, as <hi>Abraham</hi> did (tho he was the Father of the Faithful) both in <hi>Egypt,</hi> and in <hi>Gerar.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 12.13. Gen. 20.2. John 14.9. Heb. 1.9.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Some read it, <hi>Believe in God, and ye believe in me;</hi> as Chriſt tells them, <hi>He that had ſeen him, had ſeen the Father;</hi> becauſe he was the expreſs Image of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:97942:18"/>
his Perſon. So, he that did believe in the Father,<note place="margin">John 10.30.</note> did believe alſo in him, <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he and the Father were one.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But I think our Tranſlation doth beſt expreſs our Saviour's meaning. They did not queſtion God's Being or Vera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city, but they were required further upon pain of Damnation <hi>to believe on Chriſt.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">John 8.24.</note> And he ſaw what was like to befal him, would ſhake their Faith, as indeed it did, and they were ready to give up their Hopes.<note place="margin">John 16.32. Luke 24.21. 1 John 5.13.</note> So he may here preſs them ſtill to believe, or to conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue ſo to do; As the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Theſe things have I written to you, that believe on the name of the Son of God, that ye may know that ye have eternal life, and that ye may believe on the name of the Son of God;</hi> that is, may continue ſtill ſo to do.</p>
               <p>What is objected againſt this Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation of the Words, is not conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, <hi>viz.</hi> That it is not likely that the ſame word ſhould be taken in two ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Senſes in one Verſe. There is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more ordinary than to have the ſame words in different Moods in the ſame Verſe (which is the caſe here) as <hi>Ezek.</hi> 3.27. <hi>He that hears, let him hear; and he that forbears, let him forbear.</hi> So Matth. 19.12. <hi>He that is able to receive it, let him receive it.</hi> But it is more to
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:97942:18"/>
tranſlate the ſame words differently in the ſame place, which yet the nature of the thing, or the matter in hand doth ſometime neceſſarily require, as <hi>John</hi> 2.23, 24. many believed in his name, <hi>but Jeſus committed not himſelf to them,</hi> or durſt not truſt them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II.</head>
               <p>I Will now proceed to ſhew: 1. What it is to believe in God and Chriſt. 2. Why it is here required that we ſhould not only believe in God, but in Jeſus Chriſt. 3. What an effectual Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy this is againſt Trouble of Mind. <hi>Firſt,</hi> To believe <hi>in</hi> God, or <hi>on</hi> God and Chriſt (for both theſe Expreſſions are frequently uſed in the <hi>New Teſtament,</hi> as any one in reading may eaſily obſerve) is ſo to believe God, or Chriſt, as to truſt in him, to rely on him, <hi>to ſtay our ſelves on him,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſa. 26.4. Phil. 2.19, 24. 2· Chron. 13.18.16.7. Iſa. 50 10.</note> to <hi>roll</hi> our ſelves on him, as Dr. <hi>Hammond</hi> expreſſes it in his Practical Catechiſm, <hi>Lib.</hi> 1. <hi>Sect.</hi> 3. and before him our Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlators of the Bible in the Margent of <hi>Pſal.</hi> 22.8. To believe, we know (in its moſt proper ſignification) is to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:97942:19"/>
to any thing upon the Authority of him that ſpeaks it. <hi>Therefore he that believes not, makes God a Lyar:</hi> That is, accounts him ſuch by Interpretation, or deals with him as if he were ſo.<note place="margin">1 John 5.10.</note> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as on the contrary, <hi>he that doth believe him, or receive his Teſtimony, ſets to his Seal</hi> (that is, owns and acknowledges) <hi>that he is true.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">John 3.33.</note> But this is ſuch a Faith as wicked men may have, and not that ſaving Faith which the Scripture ſo often ſpeaks of; but that is a fiducial reſting upon him, for the accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of what he hath promiſed in the way, and upon the terms whereon he hath promiſed it, and no otherwiſe. For that would be an unwarrantable preſumption, not properly a believing in him, he having not promiſed ſuch things on any other terms.</p>
               <p>Now for the further clearing of this, we may obſerve, that there are Words not only in Scripture, but in Heathen Authors (many Inſtances of which I could give you) which they call <hi>pregnant words,</hi> which include or compriſe ſome other word in them. As where it is ſaid, all the People trembled after <hi>Saeul,</hi> as (you ſee in the Margent) the <hi>Hebrew</hi> word ſignifies,<note place="margin">1 Sam 13.7.</note> which our Tranſlators well render, <hi>They followed him trembling.</hi>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:97942:19"/>
So <hi>Joab</hi> and <hi>Abiathar helped</hi> after <hi>Ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nijah:</hi> That is, following after <hi>Adonijah,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 King 1.7.</note> helped him. <hi>So to wonder after the Beaſt, is to follow him wondering.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rev. 13.3.</note> So God <hi>heard David</hi> from the horns of the Unicorns. Which doth not imply, that God was there when he heard him, as he is ſaid to hear from Heaven his dwelling-place; but to hear him ſo as to ſave him from the danger wherein he was; which is ſet <hi>forth</hi> by that Metaphor, as in the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going words <hi>by the Lions Mouth.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 22.21. Heb. 5.7.</note> As Chriſt was <hi>heard from his Fear,</hi> or that which he was afraid of. Neither do we need to render it as it is in the Margent, for his <hi>piety:</hi> For the word doth not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſignify a religious Awe, or fear of Reverence, but a fear of danger, as is evident from <hi>Acts</hi> 23.10. In like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, <hi>God loved the Soul of Hezekiah from the Pit of Corruption:</hi> That is, as our Tranſlators render it, <hi>in love to his Soul, delivered it from the Pit of Corruption.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſa. 38.17. Acts 8.22.</note> So <hi>to repent from wickedneſs,</hi> as the <hi>Greek</hi> words imply, is ſo to repent of it, as to turn from it, or depart from it; and to be <hi>corrupted from the ſimplicity that is in Chriſt,</hi> is to be corrupted ſo as to depart from it.<note place="margin">2 Cor. 11.3.</note>
               </p>
               <p>I know ſome Learned men, obſerving how the prepoſitions both in the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:97942:20"/>
and Greek are redundant, or ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluous; that is, ſignify nothing in many places: They conclude, that to believe in God, or Chriſt, ſignifies no more but to believe them. I anſwer, that tho' we muſt ſuppoſe improprieties of ſpeech, defects, or redundancies where the nature of the thing in hand doth ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily require it: yet there is no rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon why we ſhould ſo do, when the matter in hand doth not require it, but rather that we ſhould take in ſuch words, or make uſe of them.</p>
               <p>It is further to be obſerved, that ſome words ſignify a complex act made up of many particular acts. For example, to <hi>Nurſe</hi> a Child, tho' it ſignify in the ſtricteſt ſenſe to nouriſh or feed it, by giving it meat or milk: yet in the larger and moſt ordinary ſenſe it is to take care of it, in all that is neceſſary to be done to it. So a Shepherd in moſt languages hath his name from feeding his Flock; but there is more belongs to it, than giving them Food, or le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ding <hi>them into green Paſtures.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 23.2. 1 Pet. 5.2.</note> Or if we underſtand thereby Spiritual Paſtors that are to feed the Flock of God, This ſignifies not only feeding them with the Doctrine of the word, as 1 <hi>Cor</hi> 3.2. And as ſome underſtand feeding with knowledge
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:97942:20"/>
and underſtanding, not of the manner, but the matter of feeding;<note place="margin">Jer. 3.15.</note> but it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehends the whole duty of a Shepherd, ſtrengthening the diſeaſed, healing the ſick, binding up that which is broken; bringing again that which is driven a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way; ſeeking that which is loſt;<note place="margin">Ezek. 34.4.</note> Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering the Lambs with his arms, car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying them in this boſom, gently lead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thoſe that are with young. So tho Faith (in its moſt ſtrict and proper ſenſe) be an <hi>Aſſent</hi> to the Truth,<note place="margin">Iſa. 40.11.</note> yet it comprehends many <hi>other Acts</hi> in it, when we ſpeak of a juſtifying or ſaving Faith.</p>
               <p>I may further add, That there are ſome words in Scripture which are not to be underſtood their in ſtrict and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe Senſe, but preſuppoſing ſome other things, and comprehending ſuch things as ſhould or may be preſumed to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>company or follow them. For exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, Juſtification is ſometimes aſcribed to the knowledge of Chriſt, as it is ſaid, <hi>by his knowledge ſhall my righteous ſervant juſtify many;</hi> and therefore doth the Apoſtle ſo magnify the knowledge of him, <hi>Phil</hi> 3.8. accounting all things but loſs for the excellency thereof:<note place="margin">Iſa. 53.11.</note> But it is not a <hi>bare knowledge</hi> of him that is of ſuch value and excellency, but of his Work
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:97942:21"/>
and Office, what he is, and for what he was ſent into the World; which doth ſuppoſe what our own eſtate is, and of what uſe he is to us; and ſuch a know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of him as puts us upon making uſe of him for the end for which he was given to mankind, and came into the World; then do we truly know him; as we know that we know God when we keep his commands.<note place="margin">1 Joh. 2.3. Tit. 1.16.</note> Otherwiſe we do but profeſs to know him, when in works we deny him. When <hi>Joſiah</hi> judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the cauſe of the poor and the needy, and did Judgment and Juſtice, this was to know God.<note place="margin">Jer. 22.15.16. Joh. 20.31. Acts 8.37. 1 Joh. 5.1. Mark 1.24.</note> Thus Salvation ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſeems to be ſuſpended upon our believing that Jeſus is the Chriſt, the Son of God. But this faith will not ſave, if it go no further: For the Devils be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve this, as well as that there is but one God. But as there muſt be ſuch a knowledge of him ſuppoſed, as I have before ſpoken of; ſo it muſt be ſuch a belief as brings us to him, or makes us come to him,<note place="margin">Joh. 6.35, 37. Iſa. 45.24.</note> as having both righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and ſtrength in him. This is <hi>believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with all the heart,</hi> when we do glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and willingly apply our ſelves to him for Grace and Salvation. For thus to ſeek to God,<note place="margin">Heb. 11.6.</note> or to Chriſt, is to come to him; That which is called coming to
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:97942:21"/>
God, is in the ſame verſe expounded diligently to ſeek him; ſo they ſay,<note place="margin">Jer. 2.31.</note> 
                  <hi>We are Lords, we will come no more unto thee.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 10.4 Joh. 1.12</note> 
                  <hi>The wicked through the pride of his counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance will not ſeek after God.</hi> So we muſt receive Jeſus Chriſt, that is, accept of him for our Saviour, ſubmit our ſelves to his way and method of Salvation; ſaying with <hi>Paul, Lord what wilt thou have me to do?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Acts. 9.6. Gal. 5.6.</note> So our Faith muſt work by love, his readineſs and willingneſs to ſave us at the price of his own Blood,<note place="margin">1 Joh. 4.19.</note> muſt make us love him who loved us firſt; <hi>And this love will conſtrain us, while we judg, that he dying for us when we were dead, we ſhould no more live to our ſelves but to him that died for us,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Gor. 5.14.15.</note> 
                  <hi>and is riſen again.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I will endeavour to make this more plain by a ſimilitude. There may be ſome Phyſician in the Country, whom we may reckon our ſelves happy that we ever knew or heard of: Tho' there are many that know of ſuch a perſon, and perhaps live near him, yet do not regard him, becauſe he is nothing to them, while they find themſelves well, and ſee no need of him. But we were ſick of a dangerous diſeaſe, which we never heard that any were cured of, till this Phyſician came amongſt us, but
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:97942:22"/>
hearing that he cured all that he took in hand, that would follow his directions: that he was ſo obliging, that he turned away none that came to him; that he expected neither ſee nor preſent from the poor that had nothing to give, but cured them <hi>Gratis;</hi> we choſe him for our Phyſician, applied our ſelves to him, followed his Directions, and find already ſuch a change and alteration in our ſelves, and ſo good ſucceſs, that we reſolve to ſtick to him, and follow his directions, looking for perfect cure in time from him. This is our caſe; Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt is come into the World to ſave ſinners; many know this, but are never the better for it, becauſe they not finding themſelves ſick, think they need not the Phyſician,<note place="margin">Mat. 9.12. Rom. 10.14.</note> and ſo never apply themſelves to him. But we knowing the miſerable condition wherein we were, think our ſelves happy that ever we heard tidings of him; <hi>for how ſhould we believe on him of whom we have not heard?</hi> But we looked upon it as <hi>worthy of all acceptation, That Chriſt came into the World to ſave ſinners.</hi> Hereupon we ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied our ſelves to him,<note place="margin">1 Tim. 1.13.</note> tho' we had neither price nor preſent to find accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance with him; yet did we not ſeek his favour, that we might continue in
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:97942:22"/>
Sin, but that he would ſave us from our Sins, and bleſs us in turning us from our iniquities. Thus we ſee that Faith,<note place="margin">Mat. 1.21. Acts, 3.26.</note> or that ſaving act whereby we are juſtified and ſaved, is neither a bare notional knowledge, nor a barren dead Faith, but ſuch a belief of the Goſpel, as doth ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe our miſerable eſtate by nature, as brings us to Jeſus Chriſt as our only Saviour, not only for pardon of ſin, ſo as we may avoid the wrath to come; but for entire and compleat Salvation,<note place="margin">Rom. 6.14.</note> ſo as iniquity may not have dominion over us: but that we may be freed from the bondage of it, and ſo redeemed from it, as to be a peculiar people to God, <hi>zealous of good works.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Tit. 2.14.</note> I ſhall have occaſion to add ſomething afterwards which may more fully clear up this point, and ſo ſhall at preſent proceed to the ſecond thing which I propounded to ſpeak of, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Why we are to believe in Chriſt as well as in God.</p>
               <p>Firſt, If we conſider Chriſt as God, of the ſame Eſſence with the Father,<note place="margin">Joh. 5.23. Joh. 10.30.</note> ſo we are to honour the Son as we honour the Father; for ſo he and the Father are one. But if we conſider him as Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, ſo we are to believe in him as the immediate object of our Faith, and by
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:97942:23"/>
him to believe in God.<note place="margin">1 Pet. 1.23. Joh. 17.3.</note> As the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Chriſt muſt be ſuperadded to the knowledge of God for obtaining Eternal Life; ſo Faith in Chriſt muſt be joined with our Faith in God. We muſt come to God by him.<note place="margin">Heb. 7.25.</note> None can come to the Son but by the Father, that is,<note place="margin">Joh 6.44. Joh 14.6.</note> by his grace drawing them. But none can come to the Father but by the Son. That is they muſt have acceſs to the Father through his mediation. As the <hi>Tyrians</hi> made <hi>Blaſtus</hi> their Friend when they came to deſire Peace of <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rod;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Acts 12.20.</note> So if we would have Peace with God, we muſt have acceſs to him by Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, it is he that muſt bring us to God.<note place="margin">Rom. 5.2. Eph 2.18. 1 Pet. 3.18. Epheſ. 1.6.</note> We muſt firſt by Faith come to Chriſt, and he muſt introduce us to God, that we may find acceptance with him. The Jews were ſo terrified at the giving of the Law, that they were afraid of having to do any more immediately with God, and therefore deſired that <hi>Moſes</hi> might come betwixt God and them.<note place="margin">Exod. 20.19.</note> Now as the <hi>Athenians</hi> had an obſcure notion of an unknown God, but the Apoſtle declared to them <hi>him whom they ignorantly worſhipped;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Acts 17.23.</note> ſo here the <hi>Jews</hi> had ſome Conviction of the neceſſity of a Mediator, and they pitch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on <hi>Moſes</hi> as the fitteſt perſon for it
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:97942:23"/>
that they could think of: But God an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered to the ground of their deſire,<note place="margin">Deut. 18.15, &amp;c. Epheſ. 3.20.</note> and promiſes them a Mediator (which they could never have thought of) that was fit for that Office, <hi>doing for them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove what they could ask or think.</hi> As God doth doth many times in anſwering the Prayers of his people, grant the thing which they deſire, but not in ſuch a way, or by ſuch means as they might think of, but by ſome more proper way or means which his wiſdom finds out.</p>
               <p>But further; before the Incarnation of Chriſt, they were to believe in the <hi>Meſſiah to come;</hi> but now that he was come, and had given ſufficient proof that he was the promiſed <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> by do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing theſe works which never any man did, they were to determine their Faith on him in particular,<note place="margin">Joh. 15.22. Joh. 8.24.</note> or dye in their Sins.</p>
               <p>But he doth likewiſe preſs this upon them, becauſe he foreſaw what diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragements they were like to meet with, and how likely their Faith was to be ſhaken in this particular.<note place="margin">1 Cor. 1.23.</note> 
                  <hi>A crucified Chriſt was a ſtumbling-block to the Jews, and to the Greeks fooliſhneſs.</hi> The <hi>Jews</hi> thought that the <hi>Meſſiah</hi> when he came, ſhould abide for ever;<note place="margin">John 12.34.</note> therefore his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples when they ſaw his Death, gave up
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:97942:24"/>
their hopes.<note place="margin">Luke 24.20.</note> And the <hi>Greeks</hi> looked up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it as an abſurd ridiculous thing, to believe in a Crucified Perſon, and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip one as God that died the moſt Infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous death of men. Therefore it was needful to caution them againſt ſuch a Temptation, by encouraging them ſtill to believe on him, tho' he did leave them, and by ſuch an infamous Death; And doth after his Reſurrection up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braid them for their folly in being ſo ſlow of heart to believe, becauſe this was but according to what the Scripture had foretold, that he muſt ſuffer before he entred into his glory.<note place="margin">Luke 24.26.</note> The Scripture was to be fulfilled in ſome thing which did not ſeem in themſelves ſo neceſſary, as the parting of Chriſt's Raiment and not breaking his bones.<note place="margin">Joh. 19.24, 35.</note> But But as we ſpeak of ſome things that are neceſſary, not only by vertue of a Command, or becauſe they are required, but as a mean in order to an end: So the Scripture was to be fulfilled in this, not only to ſave its veracity, or that it might not be broken;<note place="margin">Joh. 10.35. Heb. 2.10.</note> but in order to the bringing of his people to glory. For he had continued alone, if he had not died and been buried,<note place="margin">Joh. 12.24.</note> and would not have had ſuch a numerous ſeed. As a Grain of Wheat if it die in the earth, that is, cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupts,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:97942:24"/>
and ſpears, and <hi>brings forth much fruit,</hi> otherwiſe it abides alone:<note place="margin">Gal. 3.13.</note> So Chriſt was to be made perfect through ſuffering, <hi>and was to become a Curſe for us that he might deliver us from the Curſe.</hi> So that they were ſtill to believe in him, notwithſtanding all ſeeming diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragements.</p>
               <p>Indeed we are ready to be troubled at many things which if well conſidered may rather encourage our hopes. The Senſe which we have of our own vile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and unworthineſs, and the conflict which we find in our own Souls, do many times diſcourage us, as if it were not for ſuch to come to Chriſt: Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the former ſhould (as the Law) be our School-maſter to bring us to Chriſt. The greater our Sin is, the more need we have of pardon.<note place="margin">Pſal. 25.10.</note> We may plead the greatneſs of our Sin, as an argument for the pardon of it, and the pardon of great Sinners will beſt anſwer God's end in the Pardon of Sin.<note place="margin">Epheſ. 2.7.</note> Therefore this is the beſt qualification to fit us for Chriſt, which is not to make him willing to accept of us, but to make us willing to accept of him; He muſt not find us new Creatures, but make us ſuch.<note place="margin">Epheſ. 2.10.</note> And the conflict which we find in us (as it may be) is an evidence that there is in us a
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:97942:25"/>
Principle of Spiritual Life, reſiſting our natural corruption.</p>
               <p>I now ſhall ſhew you that Faith is the moſt effectual remedy againſt trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. The <hi>Apoſtle</hi> prays that the <hi>Romans</hi> may be filled <hi>with all joy and peace in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 15.13.</note> That is, that they might abound with the greateſt meaſure thereof, as this expreſſion in Scripture frequently ſignifies, not all ſorts or kinds of any thing, but an high degree of any thing in its kind. So all Faith and all know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 13.2.</note> are not all kinds of Faith, but the greateſt meaſure or degree of that Faith which he there ſpeaks of, that is the Faith of Miracles: Or of ſuch know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge as he there treats of: In like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner we are to underſtand all Wiſdom. So by believing we are not only kept in perfect Peace,<note place="margin">Col. 1.9.3, 16.</note> but rejoyce with joy unſpeakable and full of glory. Joy is more than Peace,<note place="margin">Iſa. 26.3. 1 Pet. 1.8. Pſal. 34.2. Pſal. 43.4.</note> we may thereby not only have our minds quieted and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, but may make our Boaſt of God, and with <hi>David</hi> call him our exceeding joy.</p>
               <p>I will firſt give you ſome general Proofs that it is ſo, and then ſhew you how it is ſo. We find in the Old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that this was the chief remedy that the People of God did in all their
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:97942:25"/>
troubles betake themſelves to; not only by what virtue the Apoſtle aſcribes to their Faith,<note place="margin">Heb. 11.</note> but by the frequent uſe which <hi>David</hi> makes thereof when at any time he was in any fear or trouble; when fear was on every ſide;<note place="margin">Pſalm 31.13, 14. Pſal 42.11.</note> while men took counſel together to take away his Life, he truſted in God, and ſtirs up himſelf to this when he was caſt down or diſquieted. And what time he was afraid, that is whenſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver he was ſo, he would truſt in God.<note place="margin">Pſalm 56.3.</note> And whereas it may ſeem to ſome, that this doth not ſo well agree with what he ſaith of the righteous man,<note place="margin">Pſal. 111.7.</note> That he ſhall not be afraid of any evil tidings, his heart being fix'd, truſting in the Lord: Theſe places ſhew, that tho good men may unavoidably be ſurpriſed with ſudden fear, yet Faith is the way to cure it. We ſee by experience, that there are ſome ſudden motions of the affections, which prevent all reaſonings of the Mind. As we ſometime ſtart at what we do unawares hear or ſee, but our fear is over as ſoon as we can recol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect our ſelves, and either ſee that there was no real danger, or ſecure our ſelves againſt it. So when we apprehend any ſudden danger which may alarm our fear, all is quiet when we can by Faith
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:97942:26"/>
betake our ſelves to God as our refuge, or caſt all our care upon him. And as this was the remedy which good men did then betake themſelves to;<note place="margin">Iſaiah 12.2.</note> ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the New Teſtament Chriſt imputes the inordinate cares and fears of his Diſciples to the weakneſs or want of Faith. So he reproves the weakneſs of their Faith when they were too ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitous about the things of the World, or the neceſſaries of this life.<note place="margin">Matth. 6.30.</note> One would think that it were one of the beſt uſes or advantages of riches, to free us from ſollicitous cares, and that a man might with him in <hi>Luke</hi> 12.20. diſmiſs all fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther care about theſe things, when he is richly ſtored with them: But we have ſeen often, that Faith is more ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectual for this end,<note place="margin">Heb. 13.5.</note> and that a Promiſe is better ſecurity than a great Eſtate. So when <hi>Peter</hi> was ſo afraid upon the Water, Chriſt upbraids him with the weakneſs of his Faith: And when they were in a ſtorm, and thereby put into a great fright, Chriſt asks them accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to one Evangeliſt,<note place="margin">Mark 4.40. Luke 8.25.</note> How it was that they had not faith? and according to another, Where their Faith was? they had it not actually at that time. As ſome Philoſophers make Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge to conſiſt in Remembrance, as if
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:97942:26"/>
that were not to be accounted Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge which is only habitual, and not ctual. However tho they had Faith, yet they had it to ſeek, as a Work-man that when he ſhould uſe a tool, it is laid out of the way, and ſo at preſent wants the benefit of it. As a man that is rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to faint, and may have a Cordial in his Cloſet, yet if it be not at hand when he ſhould uſe it, he may fall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a ſwoon if he do not take it.</p>
               <p>I will now ſhew more particularly how Faith is ſuch an effectual remedy againſt trouble of mind; and the chief reaſon thereof is, Becauſe thereby we have our ſins pardoned. As ſin is the Sting of Death, ſo it is alſo of every affliction; therefore he is a Bleſſed man whoſe iniquities are forgiven.<note place="margin">Pſalm 32.1.</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. III.</head>
               <p>NOw for the more full clearing of this Point, I will, firſt, ſhew you what pardon of ſin is. 2. How this is obtained by Faith. 3. How great a privilege and happineſs it is. Remiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or forgiveneſs of ſin is in its moſt ordinary ſenſe, freeing or exempting the ſinner from the puniſhment of it.
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:97942:27"/>
and ſometimes it hath reſpect only to the <hi>temporal puniſhment;</hi> ſo God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gave the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> in the wilderneſs when he did not puniſh them.<note place="margin">Num. 14.19.</note> So it is ſaid God would not pardon the Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent Blood which <hi>Manaſſes</hi> ſhed, tho it is ſuppoſed the Eternal puniſhment of it was remitted.<note place="margin">2 Kings 24.4. Matth. 6.14. Epheſ. 4.32. 1 Kings 8.34. and 39.50. Amos 7.2.</note> In this reſpect we muſt forgive each other; in this ſenſe we pray for the forgiveneſs of the ſins of a Nation; and no doubt in this ſenſe thoſe that are in a ſtate of Grace may pray dayly for Pardon of ſin. Tho' I doubt not but men that are already juſtified may pray for the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don of ſin in the moſt proper ſenſe, as Chriſt by one Sacrifice perfecting for ever thoſe that are ſanctified,<note place="margin">Heb. 10.14.</note> doth not prevent his interceſſion, or make that unneceſſary: So neither doth our full diſcharge from the guilt of all our ſins, diſcharge us from praying dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for the forgiveneſs of them. When we are in the fulleſt poſſeſſion of the greateſt abundance of the things of this Life, we are to pray for our daily bread, that is, not only for the bleſſing and comfort, but for the <hi>continuance</hi> of them. So tho' our ſins be pardoned when we firſt believe, we may pray daily for the <hi>continuance</hi> of the vertue and efficacy of the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:97942:27"/>
Blood of Chriſt upon our conſciences, for the continuance of our peace with God. But that remiſſion of ſins which we have by Jeſus Chriſt, is the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charging us from the <hi>eternal puniſhment,</hi> and is the ſame thing in effect with juſtification.<note place="margin">Acts 13.38, 39.</note> In the former verſe the Apoſtle ſaith, Through Chriſt is preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>forgiveneſs of ſins;</hi> in the latter, that whoever believes on him, is <hi>juſtified.</hi> Not that juſtification and forgiveneſs of ſins are the ſame thing in the preciſe notion of them; but where many ſay, that they are the ſame thing, they only intend thereby to exclude that ſenſe of the Word <hi>juſtifying,</hi> in which the Papiſts ſometimes take it, <hi>viz.</hi> for making righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous by Renovation, Sanctification, or infuſion of new habits. But there may be juſtification where there is not Pardon of ſin, when a perſon is acquit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted or declared free from that which he was ſuſpected of, or charged with: So not only a righteous man may be juſtified, but God himſelf.<note place="margin">Deut. 25.1. Luke 7.29. Rom 3.4.</note> And as there may be juſtification without Pardon, ſo Pardon without juſtification. I do not mean that actually, or <hi>de facto,</hi> there is Pardon, or a remiſſion of the Eternal puniſhment of ſin, where there is not juſtification: But we may conceive of a
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:97942:28"/>
Pardon without juſtification; as there are ſome that acknowledge a Pardon of ſin merely out of mercy, without reſpect to any ſatisfaction made to Divine Juſtice; and tho the Scripture ſpeaks more frequently of the juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſinners, than to have it denied; yet they ſay that juſtification is only by a <hi>Metonomy</hi> taken for pronouncing a ſinner juſt, and dealing with him as if he were righteous, freeing him from the guilt and puniſhment of ſin; and beſtowing eternal life on him. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as in the ſenſe of the Scripture, to juſtify is to acquit or diſcharge a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner from the guilt and puniſhment of ſin, upon the Imputation of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to him.<note place="margin">Rom. 4.6.</note> But as we muſt not ſuppoſe that God only deals with us as if we were righteous, which ſome ſuppoſe he might, tho Chriſt ſhould not be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to have died in our ſtead, or have born our ſin: yea, tho he had not died at all. So on the other hand, we muſt not imagine that God in imputing righteouſneſs to ſinners, doth think or ſuppoſe that <hi>they have not ſinned,</hi> or have <hi>ſatisfied the Law</hi> for their ſin. Imputation doth not imply any ſuch thing. When <hi>Shimei</hi> deſires that <hi>David</hi> would <hi>not impute iniquity</hi> to him,<note place="margin">2 Sam. 19 19.</note> we cannot ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:97942:28"/>
that he deſires that he would think or make account that he had not done iniquity, but that he would not <hi>charge</hi> it upon him, or <hi>deal with him according to it;</hi> and where it is ſaid, the Sacrifice of him that ſhould be eaten on the third day, ſhould <hi>not be imputed to him;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Lev. 7.18.</note> the meaning of it is, that he ſhould not have the <hi>benefit</hi> of it, or be dealt with accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thereto. But to keep the true mean between theſe, we muſt ſuppoſe, that God deals thus with us, <hi>not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puting our ſins to us, in conſideration of what Chriſt hath done for us, or in our ſtead.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Philem. 18.</note> As where <hi>Paul</hi> allows <hi>Philemon</hi> to put <hi>Oneſimus</hi> his wrong or debt (for which it is like he might be put into the ſame Priſon where <hi>Paul</hi> was) <hi>on his account;</hi> as he would not have him think that it was <hi>Paul,</hi> and not <hi>Oneſimus,</hi> that had wronged him; neither would he have him to puniſh it no more in <hi>Oneſimus</hi> than if he had not done it, but <hi>Paul.</hi> But he tells him, and gives it under his hand, that he would repay it, or ſatisfy him for it. So God doth not only deal with us as if we were righteous, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting our eternal puniſhment: But he doth this in conſideration of what Chriſt hath done and ſuffered for us: He having laid upon him the iniquities
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:97942:29"/>
of us all.<note place="margin">Iſaiah 53.6. Gal. 3.13.</note> And God having by his So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraignty ſo far diſpenſed with his Law, as to make Chriſt a curſe for us, he is now not only merciful and graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous,<note place="margin">1 John 1.9.</note> 
                  <hi>but faithful and juſt to forgive us our ſins,</hi> he having ſet him forth <hi>to be a propitiation for our ſins, to declare his righteouſneſs, that he might be juſt, and a juſtifier of him that believes in Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 3.25, 26.</note> It is not only that he may be juſt, tho' he juſtify ſinners, or that he may juſtify them <hi>ſaving his juſtice:</hi> But it is <hi>juſt with God to juſtify</hi> or acquit ſinners, <hi>Chriſt having born our ſins on the Croſs,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Pet 2.24.</note> 
                  <hi>that we through his ſtripes might be healed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I come now to ſhew how we are juſtified by Faith; and that we are juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by Faith, is evident beyond all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction,<note place="margin">Gal. 2.16.</note> from that of the Apoſtle. <hi>Knowing that a man is not juſtified by the works of the Law, but by the Faith of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, we have believed in Jeſus Chriſt, that we might be juſtified.</hi> So that Faith is in order to juſtification; and the <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree</hi> of juſtification doth no more infer our juſtification from Eternity, than our glorification; and tho there were a foundation laid for our juſtification in the Death of Chriſt, ſo as it is <hi>cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly future:</hi> Yet we are <hi>not actually juſtified</hi> till we believe, but lie under
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:97942:29"/>
the ſentence of condemnation.<note place="margin">John 3.18.</note> And whatever the value of Chriſt's Blood might he in reſpect of the dignity of his perſon, who was God as well as Man; yet his merit was not <hi>abſolute,</hi> but grounded upon <hi>an Act of Sovereignty,</hi> transferring our guilt to Chriſt, and his righteouſneſs to us: And upon <hi>the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of Redemption</hi> (as many call it) betwixt the Father and Jeſus Chriſt, about the Salvation of ſinners, the ſum of which we have, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53.10. God might appoint both terms and time of our par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticipation of the benefits of Chriſt's Death; and it is evident that our Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is for a long time deferred, and the redemption of our bodies longer. Why then ſhould it ſeem ſtrange to any, that our <hi>juſtification</hi> ſhould be deferred till we believe? And for that of juſtifying <hi>the ungodly,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 4.5.</note> it is true of thoſe whom God doth juſtify in a ſtrict ſenſe; for they cannot plead perfect Obedience. But if we take <hi>ungodly</hi> in the ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſenſe wherein it is taken, for an impenitent ſinner: it ſhews what thoſe have been whom he juſtifies, ſuch they were; in this ſenſe it is ſaid,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 6.11. Matth. 11.5. Matth. 15.31. Matth. 21.31.</note> 
                  <hi>the deaf hear, and the lame walk, the dumb ſpeak, the blind ſee, Publicans and Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lots go into the kingdom of God;</hi> and in
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:97942:30"/>
that very place it is ſaid, their Faith is imputed to them for righteouſneſs. Which words we need not underſtand with the Papiſts, as if Faith being a work,<note place="margin">John 6.29.</note> 
                  <hi>That,</hi> with other works, were imputed for righteouſneſs: Nor with ſome Proteſtants, by a <hi>Metonimy,</hi> for <hi>Chriſt</hi> (or his righteouſneſs) the object of our Faith, nor with the <hi>Socinians,</hi> that (by <hi>Acceptilation,</hi> as in the Civil Law it is called, when ſome ſmall thing is accept<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed inſtead of a Debt) Faith is reckoned inſtead of <hi>perfect righteouſneſs.</hi> As for thoſe Proteſtants that call Faith our <hi>Evangelical Righteouſneſs,</hi> as being that which the <hi>Goſpel</hi> requires, as the <hi>Law</hi> did perfect obedience; they do not at all ſymbolize with the <hi>Socinians</hi> (who do by their <hi>Acceptilation</hi> exclude the ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction of Chriſt) for they hold a legal righteouſneſs to be ſtill neceſſary, but lying wholly without us, as being per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed by Chriſt for us, and ſo do not reckon <hi>Evangelical righteouſneſs</hi> to be <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of that righteouſneſs, by,</hi> or <hi>for</hi> which we are juſtified, or any part of it; but only a <hi>means of our being inveſted therewith.</hi> But tho I would not, as ſome do, exagitate the Phraſe, or thoſe that uſe it, while they thus explain themſelves, for (not to ſay with <hi>Jerome, Sceteratum eſt) minus
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:97942:30"/>
Chriſtianum eſt; cum nonis ſenſum ſanum eſſe alicujus ex verbis incommodè dictis ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuere errorem;</hi> yet it is not <hi>neceſſary</hi> to make uſe of it for the interpretation of this place, there being another plain ſenſe of it; a thing is imputed to us, when we are dealt with according thereto, as I have already ſaid. So <hi>Faith is imputed to us,</hi> when we are dealt with or treated as believers; and it is impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to us <hi>for righteouſneſs,</hi> though not inſtead of it, or as the matter of it, but as it is a means of it, in any way what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever; as it was ſaid before, <hi>we have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved, that we might be juſtified.</hi> As it is ſaid, <hi>John</hi> Preached <hi>the baptiſm of repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance for remiſſion of ſins;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mark. 1.4.</note> or as Chriſt is ſaid te be <hi>given for a Covenant of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple:</hi> not that he might be a Covenant (as ſome have raſhly expounded it) as if Chriſt in a ſtrict literal ſenſe muſt be all in all.<note place="margin">Iſa. 42 6.</note> Whereas it was only that there might be a Covenant with the People; he being the Surety or Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour of it. So Faith is reckoned to us,<note place="margin">Heb. 7.22.9, 15.</note> that ſo we might be righteous, or might be juſtified, God having ſuſpended our juſtification upon that. And it doth reſult from thence (by vertue of the Goſpel Grant) as our guilt doth reſult from our ſin by vertue of the Law; tho
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:97942:31"/>
I would not be thought to aſcribe the ſame cauſality to our Faith in juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that I do to ſin in our Condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</p>
               <p>Now God is pleaſed to ſuſpend our Juſtification and Salvation particularly upon our believing.</p>
               <p n="1">1ſt. That we may return to him by the ſame way whereby we departed from him.<note place="margin">Gen. 3.6.</note> We fell from God by be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving the Devil rather than God; and we are recovered again, by believing God rather than the Devil, and <hi>ſetting to our ſeal that God is true.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Jo. 3.33.</note>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2dly, God deals with us as with ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Creatures, and will not force his favour upon us, but will have us accept of it:<note place="margin">Jo. 1.12. Act. 8 37.</note> and by Faith we receive Chriſt and his benefits; and this is that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving with all the heart which is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired, when we do freely and heartily embrace that offer which is made to us in the Goſpel;<note place="margin">1 Tim. 1.15. Rom 4.16.</note> accounting the Goſpel <hi>worthy of all acceptation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3dly, <hi>It is of Faith, that it might be of Grace;</hi> Faith receiving all from God, as Love gives all to him; ſo that thereby we give the whole glory of our Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to him.</p>
               <p>Now I come to ſhew you what mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of comfort it is, to have our Sins par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned.
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:97942:31"/>
Our Saviour bids the <hi>ſick of the Palſie, be of good chear,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Matth. 9 2.</note> 
                  <hi>becauſe his ſins were forgiven.</hi> It is true, as Diſeaſes are not always cured when ſins are pardoned. (For that ſaying, that where ſin is par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned the puniſhment is remitted, it doth not imply that all ſuffering is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved where ſin is taken away, but that what perſons ſuffer after pardon of ſin, is, not <hi>properly Penal in the ſenſe of the Papiſts, ſo as to make up what is behind of the ſufferings of Chriſt, to ſatisfy for our ſin;</hi>) So neither is the removal of Diſeaſes, or other Afflictions, an evidence of the pardon of ſin: but it is likely Chriſt ſpeaks not here of Pardon of ſin improperly ſo called, or the removal only of Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral puniſhment, but of pardon in a ſtrict ſenſe; and as when the King <hi>asked life, God gave it him, even length of days for ever and ever.</hi> So Chriſt,<note place="margin">Pſal. 21.4.</note> 
                  <hi>who doth ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding abundantly above what we ask or think.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eph. 3.20.</note> when he deſired cure for the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe of his body, cured his Soul like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe; which is a ſingular favour, and matter of great comfort.</p>
               <p n="1">1. It is a comfort in all our Afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. It is true afflictions are in themſelves part of the curſe, (as death it ſelf is) but a death having loſt its ſting, is now ours, for our advantage or gain; ſo are
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:97942:32"/>
all afflictions;<note place="margin">1 Cor. 3.22. Phil 1.21. Gen 49 7. Deut. 33.8. Rom 8.28. 2 Cor 4.17.</note> and as <hi>Levi</hi>'s curſe was turn'd into a bleſſing, ſo are our afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, <hi>working together for our good, working for us a far more exceeding and eternal weight of glory,</hi> I know ſome ſuppoſe that the merit of Chriſt being not abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute (as I ſaid before) the Law was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laxed only ſo far as was agreed on by God and our Mediator, and ſo we were delivered only from everlaſting puniſhment, and not from temporal: but afflictions ſtill remain properly pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſhments. But I think the ordinary no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Proteſtants about afflictions, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees better with the Scriptures, and ſo proceeding from love, they are as the <hi>wounds of a friend,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rev. 3.19. Prov. 27.6. Pſal. 141.5.</note> or rather as the ſmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the righteous, which is not for wounding, but for healing.</p>
               <p n="2">2. We have all our outward com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts hereby ſweetned to us; <hi>we may eat our bread with joy, and drink our wine with a merry heart,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 9.7.</note> 
                  <hi>when God accepts our work.</hi> There are two things wherein worldly men think they have the advantage of good men, that is, wiſdom and joy. But ſure thoſe that are <hi>wiſe to ſalvation,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Tim. 3.15.</note> have the advantage of the wiſe men of the world,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 2 6. Eccleſ. 2.26.</note> who with all their wiſdom come to nought. <hi>God gives to thoſe that are good in his fight, wiſdom, and knowledge,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:97942:32"/>
and joy,</hi> for getting and uſing riches, and comfort in the enjoyment of them. God doth not only fill every man's Cup, or aſſign him his meaſure of the things of this life: but he mingles their Cup as he pleaſes, mixing it with Sugar, or with Gaul and Wormwood; ſo that every condition, and every outward bleſſing is as God is pleaſed to make it. And there is nothing doth more ſweeten theſe things to us, than the ſenſe of God's favour in the pardon of our ſins, not only as we value gifts according to the mind or good will of the giver; but when our ſins are pardoned, all the bleſſings of this life are but as the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion which <hi>Joſeph</hi> had ſent to his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, for the way, till he ſhould come to <hi>Aegypt,</hi> where he ſhould have all the good things of the Land:<note place="margin">Gen. 45.18. &amp;c.</note> whereas the greateſt abundance that wicked men have, is <hi>but as the handful of Meal, and Oyl in the Cruſe, which the Widow and her Son were to eat, and die.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 King. 14.12.</note> Or like the Tyrant's Feaſt, to which he ſet the man that envied his greatneſs and plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, with a great Sword hanging over his head, in an horſes hair, with the point downward, which took away all the comfort of his Banquet. <hi>Iſrael was not to rejoyce for joy as other People when
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:97942:33"/>
they had gone a whoring from their God.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hoſ. 9.1.</note> So it is not for thoſe to rejoyce, that have not their ſins pardon'd, <hi>but are ſubject to bondage continually through the fear of death.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 2.15.</note>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. We have freedom of acceſs to God;<note place="margin">Rom. 5.2.</note> may come with a filial boldneſs to him (as a Child to a Father) <hi>to find mercy,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 4.16.</note> 
                  <hi>and obtain grace to help in time of need,</hi> or for ſeaſonable help: when ever we put up our prayers to God, the anſwer comes in when it may be moſt ſeaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; as God heard not (that is, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered not) <hi>Abraham</hi> when he prayed; but when <hi>Lot</hi> was in the greateſt danger, whom <hi>Abraham</hi> ſeemed to have chief reſpect to in his Prayers.<note place="margin">Gen. 19.29.</note> When our ſins are pardoned, God may (notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſtrictneſs of his Juſtice, and the ſeverity of his Law) pleaſe himſelf in ſhewing mercy,<note place="margin">Mich. 7.18.</note> which he takes ſo much delight in.</p>
               <p n="4">4. We have the continual Feaſt of a good Conſcience, which will be a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joycing to us not only in the time of affliction,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 1.12. Job. 18.14.</note> but in Death it ſelf, which is ſo terrible to others. As Chriſt bids his Diſciples, <hi>lift up their heads becauſe their redemption drew nigh,</hi> when the hearts of others failed them, for look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for the things that were coming
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:97942:33"/>
upon them.<note place="margin">Luc. 21.23, 28.</note> It is true, a good man's Conſcience may accuſe him as to ſome particular acts, though his ſins be par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned:<note place="margin">2 Sam. 24.10.</note> 
                  <hi>as David</hi>'s <hi>did for numbering the people;</hi> but there is proviſion made in ſuch caſes, that every particular ſin ſhall not break the peace betwixt God and us;<note place="margin">1 Joh. 2.1, 2.</note> but it is not our Conſcience accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing us in reference to ſome <hi>particular acts,</hi> but in reference to our <hi>ſpiritual ſtate,</hi> that is ſo terrible and affrighting,<note place="margin">Heb. 10.30.</note> when we are kept continually in a fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful expectation of judgement and fiery indignation.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IV.</head>
               <p>NOW tho this be ſo great a privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege and happineſs, to have our ſins pardoned; if we know it not, we cannot take the comfort of it. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I will further enquire, what aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance we have thereof by Faith. There is a great complaint that many, (if not moſt) of our later Writers and Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers have deſerted the firſt Reformers in the Doctrine of Faith; who com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly taught, that it was a <hi>perſuaſion or confidence of our own Salvation in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar by Chriſt;</hi> and that every believer
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:97942:34"/>
in his firſt believing, was to apply the promiſe to himſelf. But now it is commonly taught, that <hi>aſſurance is not eſſential to Faith,</hi> and that Chriſtians may live long in the want of it. And this they ſay doth very much weaken the hands of Chriſtians, there being ſo many graces to be acted, ſo many du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties to be performed, ſo many afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to be endured, which do require Aſſurance to encourage and enable us thereto. And if thoſe that ſuffered ſo much in the beginning of the Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, for the profeſſion of the Truth, ſhould have had ſuch a Faith as is now ordinarily taught, and not that Aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance and confidence wherein they then pleaded the Eſſence of Faith, they could not have gone ſo well through their ſufferings. Again, they ſay by this Doctrine, that men may have Faith without Aſſurance; we teach men to reſt in ſuch a Faith, and to content themſelves without Aſſurance, and then to plead their own experience, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm their Doctrine, that Chriſtians may believe ſincerely, tho they have not Aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, tho againſt the experience of the People of God both in the <hi>Old</hi> and <hi>New Teſtament,</hi> who did ordinarily pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs their own Aſſurance of Salvation.
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:97942:34"/>
Now I will not go about to juſtify what every particular perſon may ſay, in heat of Diſputation, or when they ſpeak of things which they have only dry notions (but no experimental know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge) of. But for our encouraging perſons to <hi>allow</hi> or <hi>indulge</hi> themſelves in the want of Aſſurance, by ſaying that there may be true Faith without it, we think they have leſs reaſon for their complalnt, than thoſe have that ſay we weaken the hands of Chriſtians by tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, that perfection is not neceſſary to Salvation, nor attainable in this Life, becauſe Chiſtians generally concern themſelves more to endeavour after Aſſurance, than after Perfection, both as it is more attainable and more ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to the comfort of their Lives. As for the profeſſion of the People of God in Scripture, it is not univerſally true of them; for as we meet with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of many triumphing in the aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of the love of God, and the hope of future glory; ſo we do of ſome un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der doubts and terrors; and as <hi>Moſes</hi> wiſhed (in another caſe) that all the Lord's People were Prophets; ſo I wiſh that all the Lord's People had Aſſurance: yea, I hope that if he call them to like ſufferings, he will give them like Aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:97942:35"/>
as his People had under theirs formerly; it being his ordinary way to proportion their Conſolations to their Sufferings.<note place="margin">2 Cor. 1.5.</note> Yea, we ordinarliy teach, not only that Aſſurance is attainable (with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out extraordinary Revelation) but that it is the Duty (as well as the Intereſt) of Chriſtians to endeavour after it.</p>
               <p>Having premiſed thus much briefly, I will now proceed to enquire how far Faith is attended with Aſſurance, and how it may be ſometimes without it. I will not ſay, there is a <hi>direct</hi> Act of Faith, and a <hi>reflex</hi> Act: I think not the terms ſo proper; but I own, what they call the <hi>direct</hi> Act of Faith, is the moſt proper Act of it; and that when a man hath belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, or doth believe, he may <hi>reflect</hi> upon it, and ſay with him,<note place="margin">Mark 6.24.</note> 
                  <hi>I believe;</hi> and thence he may infer his Intereſt in the promiſe of Salvation, and ſo have Aſſurance; which ſome call Aſſurance of Faith; and we may call it ſo, as it is <hi>inferr'd</hi> from our Faith, rather than as it is an <hi>act of Faith.</hi> The Scripture ſpeaks of <hi>a full aſſurance of underſtanding,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Col. 2.2.</note> which is a clear and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain knowledge of Truths. Of a <hi>full aſſurance of hope;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 6.11. Heb. 10.22.</note> that is, a certain ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation of Salvation. Of <hi>a full aſſurance of faith.</hi> Now. the Aſſurance which we are now ſpeaking of, is indeed rather
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:97942:35"/>
the Aſſurance of <hi>Hope,</hi> than the Aſſurance of <hi>Faith;</hi> tho it is indeed grounded on the Aſſurance of Faith, wherewith we ſhould draw nigh to God, not only in particular Acts of Worſhip, but in our firſt acceſs to him in Converſion; as the Prodigal firſt returned to his Father's Houſe, and when he was received into it, made his particular Addreſſes to his Father, as he had occaſion. And this full Aſſurance is not only ſuch, as that of <hi>Abraham, That what God had promiſed,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 4.21.</note> 
                  <hi>he was able alſo to perform.</hi> Nor as that of <hi>Sarah, That judged him faithful that had promiſed.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 11.11.</note> So as he will certainly make good his promiſe according to the true Tenor thereof, whether we believe or no, he cannot deny himſelf.<note place="margin">2 Tim. 2.12. Rom. 3.3.</note> And <hi>if ſome do not believe, their unbelief ſhall not make the faith of God without effect.</hi> It ſhall be fulfilled to others that do be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve. But there is a further Aſſurance of Faith (even in the firſt direct Act there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of) whereby we do apply the Grace of God to our ſelves in particular; which is not a believing that our Sins are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready pardoned, or that they ſhall be pardoned upon our believing that they are ſo, but that <hi>they ſhall be pardoned upon our believing,</hi> that is, upon our addreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing our ſelves to God by Jeſus Chriſt,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:97942:36"/>
upon our coming to him, or caſting our ſelves upon God's free Grace in Chriſt. This is that <hi>boldneſs and acceſs with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence</hi> which we have <hi>by the faith of him;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Epheſ. 3.12. Heb. 10.19.</note> that boldneſs which we have to enter into the Holieſt by the Blood of Jeſus. Boldly adventuring our ſelves on God's free Grace in Jeſus Chriſt for Salvation, fleeing for refuge to lay hold on the hope that is ſet before us,<note place="margin">Heb. 6.18.</note> in the encouragement of the gracious invitation of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel to all thoſe that are weary and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy laden,<note place="margin">Matth. 11.28. Rev. 22.18. John 6.37.</note> to thoſe that ſhall deſire really the Water of Life, and the promiſe made to ſuch. And in confidence of the gracious promiſe made to all that come to Jeſus Chriſt, that <hi>he will in no wiſe caſt them out.</hi> And tho it is true, Miniſters in their preaching do often make uſe of the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of the Lepers that ſate at the gate of <hi>Samaria,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Kings 7.3, 4.</note> who reſolved to go into the Hoſt of the <hi>Syrians,</hi> as the moſt likely way to ſave their lives, becauſe there was no other courſe that they could take wherein there was any hopes of it; for if they went into the City, they ſhould dye there; if they continued where they were, they ſhould dye. So that if there were the leaſt probability of ſaving their Lives by going to the <hi>Syrians,</hi> (this being the only way which did afford them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:97942:36"/>
hopes) it was the wiſeſt courſe they could take. So in this caſe, there being Salvation in no other,<note place="margin">Acts 4.12. Mark 16.16. John 3.18.</note> and Unbelievers being under Condemnation; If there were but the <hi>leaſt probability</hi> of finding mercy through him, it would be the ſafeſt courſe that Sinners could take: They would certainly periſh if they ſhould not believe in Chriſt, and they can but pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh if they betake themſelves to him. But all this is ſpoken, not to diſcourage the hopes, or weaken the confidence of ſuch as flee to Chriſt for refuge (as if it were doubtful whether Chriſt would ſhew them mercy, or receive them to favour) but to meet with the <hi>Scruples of Doubting Chriſtians,</hi> that fear that Chriſt may reject them, tho we do not grant that it may be ſo, while we have his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe that he will not do it. Yet ſuppoſe ſuch a thing poſſible, it is acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged by all, that we ſhould take the <hi>ſafeſt</hi> way; ſo that if there were only a <hi>poſſibility,</hi> much more if there be a <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bability</hi> of Salvation by Chriſt, and no poſſibility thereof any other way, it is certainly the beſt way for us to betake our ſelves to him. It is in this caſe, as if a Phyſician ſhould come to a ſick Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and tell him his Condition is very dangerous, and there is but one Reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:97942:37"/>
that will ſave his Life, but if he will make uſe of that, he doth not doubt of his recovery. The ſick Perſon is appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſive enough of his danger, but he hath not much confidence in this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy, but doubts whether it will cure him or no. His fears may be ſuch, and his Melancholly prevail ſo far, that the Phyſician can hardly hope to free him from his fears at preſent, but may think it an unanſwerable Argument to perſwade him to uſe ſuch a Remedy, that if he do not uſe it, there is no way but Death; but if he do uſe it, he may live. So, when Chriſtians are under Temptation, and the Power of Melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholly, we may more eaſily prevail with them to venture their Souls on Chriſt for Salvation, tho it ſhould be as they imagine that Chriſt <hi>may caſt them out,</hi> than convince them that he <hi>will not caſt them out.</hi> Yet we ſtand by it as a certain truth, that thoſe that come to him wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and heavy laden, ſhall find reſt to their Souls;<note place="margin">Acts 10.43.</note> and <hi>that whoever believes on him, ſhall receive remiſſion of ſins.</hi> And that in confidence of this promiſe <hi>of God that cannot lie,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Tit. 1.2.</note> a Sinner may draw nigh to him with full aſſurance of Faith. And in this confidence, many are <hi>filled with all joy and peace in believing,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 15.13.</note> even in this firſt direct act of Faith.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:97942:37"/>But it is obſerved, That (as we have ſometimes ſeen a clear Morning without any Cloud, overcaſt and grow Dark and Gloomy; ſo) we have ſeen Clouds to darken the cleareſt and brighteſt Comforts of Chriſtians: And we make various Conjectures at the reaſon of it. Sometimes thinking, that as God under the Law did ſo far indulge new-mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried perſons, as to exempt them from any buſineſs (for the firſt year) which might occaſion their abſence from each other till their Affections were firmly ſetled, and till they were well cement<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed together;<note place="margin">Deut. 24.5.</note> ſo God is pleaſed to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulge ſuch as are newly betrothed to him, till their Affections be fixed or knit; but afterwards, tho he may retain the ſame kindneſs to them, yet he doth not make them fare deliciouſly every day. Sometimes we are ready to think, that they have left their firſt love, and ſo God hath withdrawn the ſenſe of his Love from them; and ſeveral other reaſons may be ſuppoſed thereof; but I queſtion not, but the chief reaſon is, becauſe they do, as I ſaid at firſt, flee to Chriſt for refuge, in confidence of the Invitation and Promiſe of the Goſpel; and this confidence doth for ſome time abide with them; but as thoſe that fled from the wrath to come, were to <hi>bring
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:97942:38"/>
forth fruits meet for repentance;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Matth. 3.8.</note> ſo thoſe that have by Faith fled to Chriſt for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge, are to bring forth fruits meet for Faith, or ſuch as may be ſuitable to Faith in Jeſus Chriſt: And having a freſh and lively ſenſe of the Love of Chriſt,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 5.14.</note> they think this ſhould conſtrain them, ſo as they ſhould for the future not live to themſelves, but to him that died for them: And that they ſhould be ſuch manner of Perſons in all Holy Converſation and Godlineſs,<note place="margin">2 Pet. 3.11.</note> as that for the future they think they ſhall live more like Angels than Men, and that <hi>their converſation ſhall be in heaven.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Phil. 3.20.</note> But we find our ſelves to fall far ſhort of what we propounded to our ſelves, and that <hi>there is a law in our members, warring,</hi> and rebelling,<note place="margin">Rom. 7.23.</note> 
                  <hi>againſt the law of our minds,</hi> ſo that we cannot do what we would; and we now begin to reflect on our Faith, and to conſider that there is a dead faith that profits not;<note place="margin">James 2.18, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> that there is a temporary Faith, through which a man may for a time receive the word with joy,<note place="margin">Matth. 13.21. Luke 8.13. Gal. 5.6.</note> but afterwards fall away in time of Temptation. And it is a <hi>faith which works by love, which avails in Chriſt.</hi> And now Doubts and Fears begin to ariſe in our hearts, leſt we ſhould de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive our ſelves. And thoſe that require Aſſurance in the direct Act of Faith, and
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:97942:38"/>
that we ſhould renew ſuch Acts of Faith, tho we are ſollicited by Doubts, yet acknowledg that Aſſurance will not continue without the tryal of our Faith by the inſeparable Properties of a true Saving Faith; and that we muſt exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine the fruits of our Faith, and try whether we can ſhew our Faith by our Works, that we may be ſure not to be deceived in our Judgment concerning it. Now this doth well agree with what the Scripture teaches concerning Aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, where the Apoſtle ſpeaks of <hi>gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving all diligence</hi> (that is, the greateſt diligence) <hi>to make our calling and election ſure.</hi> He doth not mean,<note place="margin">2 Peter 1.10.</note> that this ſhould be the immediate matter of our Care and Diligence; but having exhorted them in the firſt Verſe, to give all di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence to add one Grace to another, and one degree of Grace to another, that they might not be barren or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fruitful in the Knowledge of Jeſus Chriſt; in this Verſe he enforces the ſame Exhortation, they ſhould the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>give diligence to make their calling and election ſure;</hi> that is, to the end that they might hereby make them ſure; our calling firſt, and thereby our Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. Tho the Thunder be before the Lightning, yet the Lightning gives notice of the Thunder. So, tho our
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:97942:39"/>
Election be from <hi>before the foundation of the world,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eph. 1.4.</note> yet we have firſt notice of it by our Calling. I know ſome do in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpret that place otherwiſe than Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants do ordinarily interpret it: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe, ſuppoſing the word which is ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred to <hi>make ſure,</hi> is rather to make <hi>firm,</hi> than to make <hi>evident:</hi> And looking upon Election as <hi>conditional,</hi> or ſuſpend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on ſomething to be performed by us; they reckon that it becomes abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute, and ſo ſure to us upon our dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence. But as we are not choſen if we be holy,<note place="margin">Eph 1.4</note> but that we may be holy; ſo the word here uſed, doth not only ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nify making a thing firm,<note place="margin">Heb. 9.17. Mark 16.20. Heb. 2.3, 4.</note> but evident, or giving evidence of the truth of it. And whereas they ſay, our calling is a thing ſo evident, there needs no ſuch diligence for the making of that ſure. I anſwer, If our Calling were nothing, but making us Chriſtians by outward Profeſſion, it might be eaſily known; but this is not the Calling that will prove our Election:<note place="margin">Matth. 20.16.</note> 
                  <hi>For there are but few choſen of thoſe that are thus called.</hi> But there is another Calling ſpoken of in Scripture, which is termed Effectual Calling, becauſe men hearken to that Calling, and come in at it; and this is inſeparable from Predeſtination, Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.20.</note> and Glorification. And it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:97942:39"/>
much diligence to know this. So if we would have full aſſurance of Hope, or a confidence of future Glory, it muſt be by diligence, and <hi>following thoſe who through faith and patience have inherited the promiſes.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 6.11, 12.</note> For thoſe words in the cloſe of the Verſe, may either be referred to our ſhewing the ſame dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, or to the words, the <hi>full aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of Hope;</hi> we muſt perſevere in our diligence, if we would maintain the aſſurance of our Hope. We do not ſay as the Papiſts, (at leaſt, in their ſenſe) that Faith is neceſſary to the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of our Juſtification, but Works to the continuance of it; for they ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, that they that are once juſtified, may ceaſe ſo to be, and fall again un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Condemnation. But we may juſtly ſay, That tho the beginning of our Aſſurance be from Faith in the direct act of it, yet the continuance of it muſt be from Works; for we ſhall have too much ground to ſuſpect that our Faith is not an unfeign'd Faith,<note place="margin">1 Tim. 1.5. 2 Tim. 1 5. Tit. 1.1.</note> 
                  <hi>or the Faith of Gods elect,</hi> if it do not work by love.</p>
               <p>It is further evident, That Aſſurance muſt be maintained by Reflection, or Self-Examination, becauſe the Apoſtle makes that to be the ſcope of his Epiſtle, That thoſe <hi>who believe on the name of the
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:97942:40"/>
Son of God, may know that they have eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal life;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 John 5.13.</note> and may ſtill believe, or be confirmed in their Faith. If any doubt what thoſe things are that he refers to; doubtleſs, they are not the things im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately going before, but the Epiſtle in general: In ſeveral places of which he ſhews what doth evidence a ſtate of Salvation, and what is inconſiſtent therewith, as <hi>Ch.</hi> 1.6, 7. <hi>Ch.</hi> 2.3, 15. <hi>Ch.</hi> 3.14. <hi>Ch.</hi> 5.1, 4.</p>
               <p>Now, after all this, ſome are unſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied with this way of attaining Aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, or rather maintaining it, as being neither ſatisfactory nor neceſſary; and it ſeems to found our Aſſurance and Comfort on ſomething in <hi>our ſelves.</hi> For this laſt Objection, (to diſpatch it in few words) As fruit, tho it grow <hi>from</hi> the Root, yet <hi>grows</hi> upon the Branches; ſo tho all our Hope and Comfort be originally from the Grace of God, yet this manifeſting it ſelf in its effects, we may comfort our ſelves in what God hath wrought in our ſelves, as well as rejoice in behalf of others, when we ſee them walking in truth,<note place="margin">2 John 4.</note> or ſee in them thoſe <hi>things that accompany Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 6.9.</note> or have Salvation following on them. And if any ſay, this may ſuffice for a Judgment of Charity, which is all that is required of us in reference to
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:97942:40"/>
others; but it is not ſufficient to that judgment of certainty which we ſhould have concerning our ſelves. This will receive an anſwer from what I have to ſay upon the two other exceptions.</p>
               <p>Now whereas it is ſaid, that this way of ſelf-examination leaves Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans at great uncertainty about their Spiritual Eſtate; and the evidences that are uſually given for ſatisfying them, are not ſo convincing, but Chriſtians are perplexed ſtill with fears and doubts. I anſwer,</p>
               <p>That we ſhould not go to Miniſters either in hearing, or reading, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring, as <hi>Naaman</hi> went to the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet to be cured of his Leproſie, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting that he ſhould do it with a word of his mouth, and a ſtroke of his hand.<note place="margin">2 King. 5.11.</note> We cannot expect that they ſhould preſently reſolve us about our Spiritual condition; but there is much <hi>diligence</hi> to be uſed by our ſelves, as there is in all things of any worth, which are difficult. As this deſerves our di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence, ſo it requires our diligence, not only for the tryal of our Grace, but for the exerciſe of it. It is obſerved by ſome, that Chriſtians in our days have not ordinarily that Aſſurance which o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers have had in former times: and I doubt the obſervation may be true:
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:97942:41"/>
but I think it proceeds not ſo much from any <hi>error about the nature of Faith,</hi> as from <hi>decay in Grace,</hi> and that manifeſt declining that there is in the practice of Religion; and it is no wonder that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors of Religion are ſuch ſtrangers to Aſſurance, and Spiritual Comfort, while there is ſuch a manifeſt difference betwixt the Chriſtians of theſe days, and of former times; and I deſire that the words of one ſuſpected by none to derogate from the Grace of God, or the operations of his Spirit in reference to man's Salvation, may be diligently heeded. <hi>It is</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>impoſſible that many profeſſors whom we ſee and converſe withal, ſhould have any ſolid peace with God. It is a fruit that will not grow on an earthly ſelfiſh frame of mind and conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation. God forbid but that our utmoſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence and continued endeavours to thrive in every Grace, ſhould be required there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now in this caſe, I neither think it ſo <hi>eaſy</hi> a matter as ſome do to attain Aſſurance, nor ſuch an <hi>impoſſibility</hi> as others do. Some Learned Men think that Aſſurance doth generally accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany ſaving Faith, becauſe they ſuppoſe the Soul muſt needs know its own acts, and ſo muſt neceſſarily know when it believes, and when it repents,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:97942:41"/>
and conſequently infer its own Juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation. But tho it be eaſy to know our own acts conſidered <hi>Phyſically</hi> or <hi>Naturally,</hi> that is, when we put forth ſuch an act in general, as when we believe, or repent, or know God; yet it is another thing to know our own acts <hi>morally</hi> conſidered, or as they ought to be qualified in order to ſuch ends as they are appointed to. There may be a Faith which is but temporary,<note place="margin">Mat. 13.21.</note> or for a ſeaſon; there may be a repentance like that of <hi>Nineveh,</hi> which may avail to the preventing of temporal Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, but not to Salvation. There may be ſuch a knowledge, <hi>whereby we do not know things as we ought to know them:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 8.2. Tit. 1.16.</note> ſo we may only <hi>profeſs that we know God.</hi> But we muſt know that we know him,<note place="margin">1 Jo. 2.3. Jer. 22.16.</note> by our Obedience as the fruit or effect thereof: ſo it requires ſearch and ſelf-examination,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 13.5.</note> to know <hi>whether we are in the Faith,</hi> or in the ſtate of true believers. But on the other hand, ſome ſuppoſe it <hi>impoſſible</hi> to attain Aſſurance by reflecting upon any thing in our ſelves as an evidence of God's ſpecial Grace or favour towards us: and that they may wholly diſable Chriſtians for inferring any Aſſurance from any thing in themſelves, they deny both propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions from whence they ſhould draw
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:97942:42"/>
their concluſion. For example, we ſay, that <hi>thoſe who love the brethren are paſſed from Death to Life.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Jo. 3.14.</note> By re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flecting upon our ſelves, we add fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that we love the brethren, thence we conclude that we are paſſed from death to life. Now theſe men with whom we have now to do, deny both the Propoſitions; that is, they deny we know that we our ſelves are paſſed from death to life, by our love to the bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren; making this to be rather a ground of a judgment of Charity con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning others, than a judgment of certainty concerning our ſelves; for we may ſurely make a better judgment of our own love to the brethren, than of the love of others; only they think a judgment of Charity may ſuffice to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards others; but we are now ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Aſſurance of our own love; but in this argument they inſiſt on the ſecond Propoſition, denying abſolutely that we can know our own love to the bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, or at leaſt that Chriſtians can ordinarily know it, there being ſo many properties of it which it is hardly poſſible for any Chriſtian to find in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf:<note place="margin">1 Cor. 13.4, &amp;c.</note> but further, we muſt know them to be brethren (they ſay) otherwiſe Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts or any ſort of perſons love thoſe of their own way, looking upon them
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:97942:42"/>
as brethren. Yea, we ſee ſuch Diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and Animoſities, and mutual Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acerbations among Chriſtians, as it ſeems impoſſible either to attain to a judgment of Charity concerning others hereby, or to a judgment of certainty concerning our ſelves.</p>
               <p>Now in anſwer to theſe things, I ſay firſt, That however Chriſtians, or Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Graces may be deſcribed in their own nature, and as they ſhould be; yet when we conſider them as they are or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily found, there is an allowance to be made for human frailty: as <hi>Hezekiah</hi> prays <hi>that God would pardon every one that prepared his heart to ſeek him,</hi> tho he were not <hi>cleanſed according to the Purification of the Sanctuary;</hi> that is, if they had endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to bring their hearts into a right frame, tho they did not reach to that purity which was in ſtrictneſs required.<note place="margin">2 Chron. 30.18, 19.</note> He may indeed ſpeak there of legal or ritual Purification, but that was ſtrictly enjoined then. There are indeed ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral ſorts of perſons that plead for Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, but none of them for abſolute Perfection, as neceſſary to Salvation. Grace muſt be ſincere, and of the right kind, tho it may not reach to that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree which is our duty (for if perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on were not our duty, our imperfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons were no ſins). Gold muſt hold at
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:97942:43"/>
the touchſtone, though it may not hold at the balance without ſome grains of allowance. If we will deal plainly and faithfully with our own hearts, we may appeal to God for the ſincerity of our love to our brethren, as <hi>Peter</hi> did for the ſincerity of his love to Chriſt,<note place="margin">Jo. 21.17.</note> 
                  <hi>Lord thou knoweſt all things, thou knoweſt that I love thee. And if our hearts condemn us not,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Jo. 3.21.</note> 
                  <hi>we may have confidence towards God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2dly, Brethren may deal unkindly with each other, when they meet in the dark, or when they meet with each other in diſguiſe: that is, through ignorance Chriſtians may miſtake their brethren, or thoſe that are their bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren may ſometimes appear unlike themſelves. But where it is true love, it is not to thoſe of our own way or opinion only; it is not proportionable to what they reſemble us in, but ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their meaſure of Holineſs, wherein they are like to God: where love is right, Chriſtians love others more that are eminent in Grace and Holineſs, tho differing in their judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments from us, than thoſe that are of our mind and way in ſome things of leſs importance, but more defective in the more eſſential parts of Religion.</p>
               <p n="3">3dly, There may be differences among Chriſtians, where there is a ſincere love
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:97942:43"/>
to each other; and the more zeal they have for the Truth, and the Service of God, the greater their differences may be. As differences may ſometimes hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen in Families, betwixt perſons that have an entire Affection to each other, and theſe differences being about things that do nearly concern their Family, as about the government and manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of their Children; the greater their Affection is towards their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, or care for them, the warmer are their debates about them. Thus it happens among Chriſtians that cannot be of one mind in things pertaining to the Honour and Service of God; the greater their zeal is, the greater are their differences: and however Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian prudence and meekneſs ſhould make us forbear each other in love, yet that perfection is not found among Chriſtians, as always to make them carry it with due Calmneſs, Tenderneſs, and Moderation to each other. We have an Example in <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas,</hi> two excellent Perſons, and dear Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions in Labours and Sufferings for Chriſt: yet they were exaſperated ſo againſt each other, that they parted and went ſeveral ways, tho the thing which they parted about ſeems to be of no great moment.<note place="margin">Act. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 36. &amp;c.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="62" facs="tcp:97942:44"/>I may not ſtand to examine parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular objections, which they make a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt other evidences of ſaving Grace: But conſider what proviſion they make for the ſatisfying of Chriſtians concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Spiritual ſtate. The Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle's <hi>power was given him not for deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 13.10.</note> but for edification.</hi> We ſhould at leaſt, if we deſtroy the foundations on which Chriſtians build their hopes and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, teach them whereon they ſhould build them. Now for this they ſend them to that Spirit which is ſo oft called the Comforter, who doth as they ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe ſpeak particularly in the heart of a Believer, <hi>Son be of good chear, thy ſins are forgiven thee;</hi> and when the Spirit ſaith this to the Soul, this ſilences all objections which did before diſturb and diſquiet it. I know God can when he pleaſes ſatisfy the Soul, ſo as there ſhall no doubt remain to trouble our ſpirits: but tho he that is awake may know certainly that he is ſo, and that he is not in a Dream: yet he that is in a dream may verily think that he is awake. So he that hath the witneſs of the Spirit, may certainly know that it is no deluſion: but he that is under a deluſion, may verily think that he hath the teſtimony of the Spirit. Therefore that we may not miſtake in this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:97942:44"/>
they ſay the Spirit of God never ſpeaks to the heart of any believer, but it ſpeaks according to the word of Grace revealed; and ſo I believe. But I know not well how to reconcile it to what was before objected, againſt our inferring our Juſtification from our Love to the Brethren. For if we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not find in our ſelves that Love which the Apoſtle ſpeaks of,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 13.3.</note> all is nothing without it; therefore it is hard to receive any Teſtimony concerning our Spiritual eſtate, where we have not ground to believe that we have this Love in us, notwithſtanding the many properties of it which are there ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. Far be it from me to dero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate from the work of the Spirit in ſatisfying and comforting troubled Souls, whoſe comforts are my greateſt hope in the time of trouble, and at the hour of death. I am not of thoſe that the Philoſopher ſpeaks of, that meaſure Vertue by themſelves, and think none attain to that which them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves have not attained to: therefore will not deny any ſuch way of Aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance as I have not had experience of. I deſire (without the offence of thoſe, in compariſon with whom I think of my ſelf as the Spies did <hi>when they ſaw the Giants,</hi> Numb. 13.33.) to ſpeak my
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:97942:45"/>
mind in this matter, after long ſearch and often renewed thoughts. I queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on not but God can ſpeak, or commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate himſelf to our ſpirits, as Angels do to each other: yea, I am fully ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied, that he doth thus ſpeak Peace to his people at the hour of death, or before, or after ſome great Conflict or Temptation: as thoſe may know that have either converſed with ſerious ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perienced Chriſtians, or but read the Lives and Deaths of Martyrs, or ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferers for Chriſt. Such may obſerve what ſudden tranſports of joy eminent Chriſtians have ſometimes had, which have not been the effect of more ſtrict Tryal, and Examination of their Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Eſtate by the Word of God, which they have not had freedom and preſence of mind for, under ſuch Fears, Pains, Bodily-weakneſs, as they have laboured under: much leſs from any briskneſs of ſpirits, or working of fancy: but it muſt be imputed to God's immediate ſupport, <hi>putting Glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs into their hearts,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſ. 4.7.</note> 
                  <hi>ſhedding abroad his love in their hearts, by the Holy Ghoſt given to them.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 5 5.</note> But to ſuppoſe this to be God's <hi>ordinay way</hi> of dealing with his People, and to allow them <hi>no Aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance</hi> but what God gives them in ſuch an <hi>immediate way,</hi> would leave many,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:97942:45"/>
humble ſerious Chriſtians, (that dare not boaſt of what God hath not wrought in them) under perpetual doubts and fears. And becauſe many are ready to think that what the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſpeaks about the witneſs of the Spirit, the ſeal of the Spirit, and the earneſt of the Spirit, do imply ſome immediate way of the Spirit, commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicating himſelf to Chriſtians: I will endeavour to ſhew you what may be the true and proper import of ſuch Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions.</p>
               <p>As for that, the Spirit's witneſſing with our ſpirits, or to our ſpirits, <hi>that we are the Children of God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 8.16.</note> ſuppoſing what I before ſaid about his immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate Comforts in extraordinary Tryals and Temptations, which ſeems to be the ſtate of Chriſtians at that time; the Spirit may ordinarily be ſaid to witneſs with our ſpirit, or to our ſpirit.</p>
               <p n="1">1ſt, With our ſpirit; and for the clearing of this, we muſt conſider, that whatever is written in Scripture, is the Teſtimony of the Spirit, he doth therein teſtify;<note place="margin">1 Pet. 1.11.</note> and it is ſaid particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly, that the <hi>Holy Ghoſt is a witneſs to us</hi> of the perfection of Chriſt's Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice; and this he is in the Scripture,<note place="margin">Heb. 10.15.</note> or what he hath there teſtified, as is
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:97942:46"/>
evident from the words following. Now it no where ſaith in Scripture, that this or that perſon is the Son of God; our Names may be written in Heaven, but not in the Scripture: ſo it is ſaid to teſtify of Chriſt, but not by Name; but deſcribing him by his works, which <hi>verſe</hi> 36. are ſaid to teſtify of him, or <hi>to bear witneſs that his Father had ſent him:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Joh. 3.39.</note> theſe put together, the teſtimony of the Scripture, and his own works, did wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs that he was the <hi>Meſſiah.</hi> Thus the Spirit of God witneſſes in general who are the Sons of God; giving Characters whereby they may be known, as <hi>walking after the Spirit, loving the Brethren, &amp;c.</hi> This we know by the Spirit of God ſpeaking in the word: but that we do theſe things, we know by our own ſpirits, which we muſt appeal to, and examine about it, this being the Candle of the Lord which ſearches the hidden parts of the belly,<note place="margin">Prov. 20.27. 2 Cor. 1.12.</note> that is, our moſt ſecret thoughts, and the witneſs thereof is the teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of our Conſciences; therefore if we would have the witneſs of the Spirit, we muſt ſee in the Scripture what that witneſſes about thoſe that ſhall be ſaved, and then conſult our own ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, and if we find thoſe things in our ſelves that do accompany Salvation,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:97942:46"/>
the Concluſion follows, that we ſhall be ſaved.</p>
               <p>But further, it may be ſaid to witneſs <hi>to or with our</hi> ſpirits, as it witneſſes in its <hi>effects,</hi> which the Spirit it ſelf may be properly ſaid to do: things are ſaid to witneſs in Scripture, when they are a real proof of any thing, as <hi>the ruſt of Silver and Gold witneſſeth againſt the owners.</hi> So mens wickedneſs ſaith, or teſtifies,<note place="margin">Jam. 5.3. Pſal. 36.1.</note> 
                  <hi>that they have no fear of God before their Eyes.</hi> So perſons are ſaid to teſtify or bear witneſs by their Works, as the Holy Ghoſt is a witneſs of Chriſt's Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>altation, by the Miracles which he wrought;<note place="margin">Act. 5.32.</note> and <hi>God did bear the Apoſtles witneſs both with ſigns and wonders, and divers gifts of the Holy Ghoſt:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 2.4.</note> and thus the Spirit bears witneſs with our ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, that we are the Children of God,<note place="margin">Ezek. 36.27.</note> by that filial frame or Spirit of Adop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <hi>which he puts in us.</hi> And by bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forth in us the fruits of the Spirit,<note place="margin">Gal. 1.16.</note> ſhe <hi>reveals his Son in us. We knowing that he abides in us,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Jo. 3.24.</note> 
                  <hi>by the Spirit which he hath given us.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I will now proceed to ſpeak of the <hi>ſealing</hi> of the Spirit; and I deſire this may be obſerved, that whenever the Scripture ſpeaks thereof, it doth not ſpeak of the Covenant, or of our Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation being ſealed to us: but of <hi>our be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:97942:47"/>
ſealed.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Cor. 1.22 Eph. 1.13.4.30.</note> Now we muſt know, that a Seal is not a Natural, but an Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Sign: and it being a particular mark belonging to ſome perſon, it ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies his ratifying or confirming any thing that it is applied to. And Seals were uſed in three Caſes: 1ſt. For the confirming of Writings, being an Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of a man's conſent to what he hath ſet his Seal to.<note place="margin">Eſth 3 12. Jer. 32.10. Dan. 6.17.</note> 2dly, It is for keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a thing ſure, as the <hi>Lyons Den,</hi> and Chriſt's Sepulchre, not by force; Wax is not proper for that; but for ſecuring it ſo as none can meddle with it but it will be known. 3dly, It was uſed for marking things that they might be known to whom they did belong, and to diſtinguiſh them from other mens; and they did not only mark things or Goods, but Perſons. We read in <hi>Heathen</hi> Authors, as <hi>Plutarch</hi> in <hi>Nicias,</hi> that they did ſometimes mark their Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives or Servants in the Forehead. And hence probably the Scripture ſpeaks ſo oft of Marking and Sealing the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of God;<note place="margin">Ezek. 9.4. Rev. 7.3, 4.9.4. Rev. 13.16. Pſ. 4.3.</note> ſo the Beaſt is ſaid to mark thoſe that did enjoy any privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leges under him. Thus when <hi>God doth ſet apart</hi> any for himſelf, as <hi>David</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſes it, he ſeals them, or marks them for his own. And as the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perors had not only their Superſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:97942:47"/>
but their Image impreſſed on their Coin;<note place="margin">Matth. 22.20. Col. 3.10.</note> ſo God impreſſes his own Image on his People, or renews them after his own Image.</p>
               <p>And if it be ſaid, That they were ſealed with the Holy Spirit of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe <hi>after they believed;</hi> as if it were not the Impreſſion of the Image of God upon us at our firſt Converſion, but ſome work of the Spirit after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards.</p>
               <p>I anſwer, Thoſe that make this ſeal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to be the confirming or aſſuring our Juſtification and Salvation to us, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe it is done at our firſt believing in the direct Act of Faith: So, if they make this Objection, let them Anſwer it themſelves. I add, that this is not an Act finiſhed in a moment, as a Seal may be ſet upon Wax; but a Progreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive Work, and the Impreſſion is made clear and deeper by degrees: We <hi>being changed into his image from glory to glory.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Cor. 3.18.</note> And laſtly, The <hi>Greeks</hi> take much liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in the change of their Tenſes, and there is the ſame Tenſe uſed here, which is uſed where it is ſaid,<note place="margin">Mark 16.16.</note> 
                  <hi>he that believes ſhall be ſaved.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I will now add ſomething briefly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the earneſt of the Spirit, which the Scripture ſpeaks ſometimes of.<note place="margin">2 Cor. 1.22. Chap. 5.5. Eph. 1.14.</note> By the laſt of which places it is evident,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:97942:48"/>
that by the earneſt of the Spirit, he means the Spirit as an earneſt, <hi>as the ſign of Circumciſion</hi> is Circumciſion for a Sign.<note place="margin">Rom. 4.11.</note> Some take the word (which is borrowed from the <hi>Eaſtern</hi> Languages) in a large ſenſe, for a <hi>pledge, pawn, or earneſt;</hi> but in this caſe it is properly rendred <hi>earneſt;</hi> for there is a great dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference betwixt a Pawn, or Pledge, and an Earneſt: The former is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing depoſited or left with another for ſecuring what hath been taken up or borrowed; and it is ſomething of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther kind, and of greater (or at leaſt equal) Value with what it is left in pawn for. But an earneſt is ſomething given at the making of a Bargain, for the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifying and confirming of it; and it is of the ſame kind with what is after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards to be paid, and but a ſmall part of it. Now we can have <hi>no Pledge</hi> of future Glory, there being nothing of equal value to it; but God gives us his Spirit, or as he doth ſometimes ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs it,<note place="margin">1 John 3.24. Chap. 4.13.</note> 
                  <hi>of his Spirit;</hi> of the Gifts and Graces of it; and this is the <hi>Earneſt</hi> of our Inheritance, Grace differing from Glory in degree only, not in kind: As here we know <hi>but in part, but then ſhall know as we are known;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 13.9, 12.</note> and as our Knowledg, ſo our Love and Joy ſhall then be perfected; and what we receive
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:97942:48"/>
here of the Spirit, doth aſſure us of receiving the full ſum of the Glory promiſed.<note place="margin">Phil. 1.6.</note> And as the Earneſt that we receive at the making of a Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, doth not only confirm the Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, but is of ſome <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> to us at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, tho it be but a ſmall part of the whole; ſo thoſe Graces of the Spirit which he here works in us, are (in the exerciſe thereof) our greateſt Comfort and Happineſs in this World, and are Prelibations and Foretaſts of our Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Happineſs, and are therefore called <hi>the firſt fruits of the ſpirit;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 8.23.</note> being a ſmall part of the full Harveſt of Glory, which we ſhall reap hereafter. In ſhort, We do <hi>by the Spirit of God know the things that are freely given to us of God:</hi> He en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abling us to <hi>diſcern Spiritual things,</hi> and to make a right Judgment of them;<note place="margin">1 Cor. 2.12, 13, 14, 15. Epheſ. 4.23.</note> 
                  <hi>renewing us in the ſpirit of our minds,</hi> as well as in our inferior Faculties; ſo, that as there is a ſaving work upon the whole Soul, which we are to make a Judgment of, there is likewiſe Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg and Judgment, or <hi>Wiſdom and Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Phil. 1.9. Col. 1.9.</note> to determine con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning our Spiritual Eſtate: As thoſe of full Age <hi>by reaſon of uſe, have their ſenſes exerciſed to diſcern both good and evil.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 5.14.</note> But that <hi>communion of the holy ghoſt</hi> which the Apoſtle prays might be with
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:97942:49"/>
all the <hi>Corinthians,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Cor. 13.14.</note> and ſo with all Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers, whereby he communicates to us all thoſe good things which Chriſt hath obtained for us,<note place="margin">John 16.15.</note> is known only to thoſe humble and circumſpect Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians which love God, and give proof of it by <hi>keeping his Commandments.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">John 14.23.</note> So that as it is the Bleſſing of the Lord that <hi>makes rich; yet the hand of the dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prov. 10.4, 22.</note> 
                  <hi>the bleſſing of the Lord</hi> going along with our diligence. So it is by the Spirit of God, that we know the things given to us of God; yet by gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving all diligence, we make our Calling and Election ſure; the Spirit of God both exciting us to, and aſſiſting us in the exerciſe of Grace, and encouraging ſuch diligence by Spiritual Comforts. And as thoſe that <hi>do his will, ſhall know of the doctrine whether it was of God, or whether he ſpake of himſelf.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">John 7.17.</note> So they ſhall know the Work which they find in themſelves, whether it be from moral Principles, fleſhly Wiſdom, reſtraining Grace, or from renewing Grace, and ſo of thoſe <hi>things that accompany Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 6.9.</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:97942:49"/>
               <head>CHAP. V.</head>
               <p>THAT I may do ſomething towards the helping of Chriſtians in the trial of their Spiritual ſtate, I will firſt premiſe ſome general Obſervations.</p>
               <p n="1">1ſt, Some perſons may have much advantage of others before their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion, and by reaſon of Natural Temper, Fleſhly Wiſdom, Education, Reſtraining Grace, or other things which keep them from the Polutions of the World, and bring them to a form of Godlineſs. Now it will be harder for ſuch to judge of their Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual ſtate, than for others. Sometimes the Nights are light by reaſon of the Moon ſhining; and it is not ſo eaſy then to diſcern whether it be Day: Yea, if the fore-part of the Night be dark, and the Moon riſe before morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, a man may think it Day before it is ſo: and having found his error, he may (that he may not be deceived again) be backward to believe that it is Day, when it is really ſo. In like manner ſome may (as I ſaid) be free from the more groſs Follies and Vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of Youth; others may have been Profane and Wicked in their Younger Years; but through ſome Affliction, or
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:97942:50"/>
ſome ſpecial Providence of God, or happening into ſome Religious Family, or into ſome place where the Word of God is Zealouſly and Faithfully Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, their Conſciences are awakened, and they leave thoſe ſins which former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they lived in, and there is a great change wrought in them, but not a ſaving-change: this is but as the light of the Moon before Day; hereby they may be deceived into a falſe opinion of their own ſtate; and when they come to ſee their own miſtake, may be more back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to believe a real thorough change in themſelves when it is wrought. There have been thoſe that have dated their Converſion after they have not only done much, but ſuffered much in the ſervice of Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="2">2dly, It may ſo happen, that perſons may at ſome times ſeem better or worſe than they are. We are upbraided by ſome for painting Hypocrites, or ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what they may attain to, ſo as to repreſent them better than we can or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily find ſincere Chriſtians to be. And on the other hand in ſpeaking of the Infirmities of the Saints, we make them worſe than moſt Hypocrites. But as the Wiſe-man complains of it as a vanity upon the Earth, that there <hi>be juſt men to whom it happens according to the
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:97942:50"/>
work of the wicked, and wicked men to whom it happens according to the work of the righteous;</hi> So it is in their Morals;<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 8.14.</note> if we read 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 11. we ſhould judge (looking no further) that <hi>David</hi> was a grievous Apoſtate, conſidering what profeſſion he had before made, which we may eaſily ſee in the 34. and 63. <hi>Pſalms,</hi> and that he had now ſung a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way care, that there was no fear of God before his eyes: but we ſee after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards by the 51. <hi>Pſalm,</hi> that the root of the matter was in him, and his Grace did again flouriſh. We have o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther inſtances in Scripture, as <hi>Aſa, Peter.</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 16. <hi>Matt.</hi> 26.70, 74. And on the other hand, we ſee what account <hi>Paul</hi> gives of himſelf,<note place="margin">Phil. 3.5, 6.</note> Tho he was then <hi>in the gall of bitterneſs and the bond of iniquity,</hi> and reckoned that he was then <hi>the chief of ſinners.</hi> So that in judging our ſelves or others, we muſt uſe much caution, and have reſpect not to our preſent frame or practice as it may be at ſome times, but to what is the ordinary habitual frame of our hearts, or courſe of our lives. Gold may ſometimes be ſo ſullied with ruſt and duſt, as it may look worſe than Copper doth ordinarily; and on the other hand, Copper may be ſo burni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed and embelliſhed, that it may look
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:97942:51"/>
more bright, and give a greater luſtre than moſt Gold doth. So that there is required both judgment and attention of mind, to diſtinguiſh the one from the other.</p>
               <p n="3">3dly, We muſt have reſpect to na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural temper in judging our ſelves or others. As it is ſaid, A little Sugar will ſerve for ſweet Wine; and a little Grace makes much more ſhew in ſome than in others: it is true, all are defiled by original ſin. But whether there be, as the Philoſopher ſays, a certain Genius (as I may ſpeak) or diſpoſition to vertue, or rather ſomething like vertue; ſome mens natural temper is quick, and ſoon moved; others are as Doves or Lambs in their natural temper; but meekneſs in theſe Creatures not being from choice and judgment, is no vertue in them. In judging our ſelves, we muſt conſider how Grace falls in with Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, or how it ſtrives againſt it. A gentle gale with the Tide or Stream, may make good riddance: but it muſt be a brisk gale to carry a Veſſel againſt them. One undertaking to tell what mens natural temper was, by his skill in Phyſiognomy, he being asked what he thought of a certain perſon, ſaid, he was of a very ill temper, and natural diſpoſition: thoſe preſent, derided him
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:97942:51"/>
for being ſo miſtaken in his conjecture, they looking upon him as a perſon of ſuch an excellent temper. But he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf did vindicate the man, and told them he had judged right; for his na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural temper was very bad, but he had corrected it by Philoſophy. Now there might be more of moral vertue in him, than in <hi>Veſpatian,</hi> who for the ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of his Nature, was called the Dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of mankind. A little Grace will make a great ſhew in ſome Natures, when a far greater meaſure will make but a little ſhew in others, where it hath no help from Nature.</p>
               <p n="4">4thly, We muſt conſider the circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances wherein perſons are; what are their temptations on one hand, and their advantages on the other hand. Some enjoy more health than others, when it is not becauſe they have ſtronger bodies, or are of a more hail conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; but it is by reaſon of their cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances; one can command his buſineſs, and that he goes out only at ſeaſonable times, or he is ſo accommoda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted as to ſecure himſelf againſt the inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the weather; they work only ſo as may be for their health, and need not tire themſelves, or over-heat them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves: they have wholſome Diet, and they have Cordials by them, to relieve
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:97942:52"/>
or fortify Nature when it is too hard put to it. And by theſe means, thoſe who are more weakly, prevent ſickneſs; whereas others (tho they be naturally ſtronger) are forced to be out at all hours, in all weathers, to endure heats and colds, eat and drink what they can get, have little wholeſome diet; if they ayl any thing, have no Cordials or Remedies at hand to help themſelves. So it is with men in reſpect of their Souls; ſome have a competent Eſtate, and are put neither upon the tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of adverſity, nor proſperity: while others (through ſtraits in their Eſtates) are put upon mean things, and ſometimes upon ſinful ſhifts. And others are rich, and in great places; and others are hardly able to judge of their temptations, how hard it is to be high in the World, and not high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minded; to exerciſe ſobriety and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance in plenty and abundance. Some have little to do in the World, abroad or at home, in trading or in their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies; have few to deal with, few Children or Servants; others muſt go into all companies, converſe with all ſorts of perſons, meet with provoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions from ſome, temptations from o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to comply with their ſinful hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours for their own advantage: they
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:97942:52"/>
may have unfaithful Servants, unduti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Children, and ſo more trial of their Grace, more exerciſe for it, and ſo may diſcover ſome weakneſs of Grace, tho not the want of it. So ſome may have the advantage of good converſation, may live in good Families or Neighbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoods, where they have good examples to provoke them to love and to good works, and are oft called upon and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſhed if they fail in any thing: they may live under a lively Miniſtry, whoſe Sermons may be <hi>as nails to faſten,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 12.11.</note> 
                  <hi>as goads</hi> to excite or quicken; they may have good books to read, and time and opportunity to read them, which is a great help to Chriſtians: whereas on the other hand, ſome perſons are caſt into prophane places, or Families, or company, where they meet with thoſe that will be drawing and enticing them to ſin, ſcoffing at them, threatning, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraging them; and it may be ſuch as they have ſome dependance upon: they ſeldome hear an awaking Sermon, or <hi>ſound doctrine,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Tim. 4.3. Epheſ. 4.29.</note> ſuch as may breed good nouriſhment; or ſuch diſcourſe as <hi>may miniſter grace to the hearers;</hi> ſeldom meet with a good book, or it may be if they do, cannot read it. It is true, we muſt hold faſt Chriſt's Name, and not deny his Faith, even <hi>where Satan dwells, and hath
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:97942:53"/>
his ſeat.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rev. 2.13.</note> But we cannot expect that Grace ſhould thrive much under ſuch Diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragements and Diſadvantages.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VI.</head>
               <p>I Shall proceed yet further, to ſhew how Chriſtians that are ſincere may be diſtinguiſhed from others, tho they have their ſinful Infirmities. We ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times obſerve Perſons of Good Families reduced to ſtraits, and go meanly; but yet, if they come to beg at our Doors, if we meet them in Company, we ſee ſomething in them which bewrays or diſcovers what they are, either in their Geſture, Speech, Civility. So thoſe that are born of God, it may be in ſhew or appearance fall far below their Rank, they may have ſinful Infirmities;<note place="margin">Rom. 7.15, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> they may find Evil preſent with them when they would do good; they may be led Captive to the Law of Sin which is in their Members; they may not do the Good which they would, but the Evil which they would not; but yet the Spirit luſts againſt the Fleſh, they hate the Evil which they do; they would do the Good which they do not; they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wail their Bondage to Sin; long to be delivered from the Body of Death, and
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:97942:53"/>
are thankful that they are ſo far deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered from it by Jeſus Chriſt. Theſe things, I confeſs, diſcover our Spiritual State chiefly to our ſelves, but it is that which I would help Chriſtians in. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, you may obſerve a difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt Perſons that are nice and neat in their Nature and Temper, and thoſe that take care only to make a good ſhew. The former would not only ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear neat outwardly, but they are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſy if they have any thing about them which is not neat and cleanly. Again, tho they may think themſelves more obliged to go according to their Rank when they are Abroad, or in Company, yet you ſhall never ſurprize them in any ſordid or unhandſome Dreſs. The lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter care not what they wear, ſo they have ſomething that is fine to caſt over all: Their Natures will bear ſordidneſs and naſtineſs, if they can hide it; and if they can appear Fine abroad, care not what they wear at home. So ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere Chriſtians <hi>take heed to their ſpirits,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Matth. 2.15. Pſalm 51.10.</note> and pray daily that God would <hi>create in them a clean heart, and renew in them a right ſpirit.</hi> Their <hi>ſecret ſins</hi> are a trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and burden to them.<note place="margin">Pſalm 19.12.</note> They would eſpecially <hi>let their light ſhine ſo before men, that ſeeing their good works, they may glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rify their father which is in heaven.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Matth. 5.16.</note> But
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:97942:54"/>
yet they will walk in the midſt of their Houſes with a perfect heart; car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry themſelves amongſt Servants and Children, as remembring that they are under the eye of God, and ſhould be Examples of Holineſs to thoſe under their own Charge.<note place="margin">Pſal 101.2. Matth. 23.27. Luke 11.44.</note> Whereas others are like <hi>painted Tombs,</hi> and <hi>whited Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulchres, which within are full of rotten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and dead mens bones.</hi> So they put on their beſt Dreſs when they go out, that they may make a fair ſhew before others; but ſurprize them at home, when they do not ſtudy their Carriage, and they are quite other manner of Perſons, and care not how they appear in their own Families before their Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants and Children. Again, We may obſerve, That ſome Perſons have <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian</hi> or <hi>Quartan</hi> Agues; on the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting days they are ordinarily as well as other Perſons; but we muſt not therefore conclude when we ſee them wdl, that they have loſt their Ague, or are cured; for when the Fit-day comes, they are as bad again as ever; yet he that is cured, may once in a long time, perhaps on occaſion (if he have ſome way neglected or diſorder'd himſelf) have ſome remembrance of his Ague (as we ſpeak) in a Fit and away. So in this caſe we ſometimes
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:97942:54"/>
ſee Perſons abſtain from Sin, and carry themſelves very well for ſome time to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether; but this is only an Intermiſſion, they have been kept from Temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons or Occaſions of Sin; but when they meet with an Occaſion or Tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, they are the ſame Perſons that they were, and ſo <hi>toties quoties</hi> (as we ſay) as oft as they meet with occaſion, they fall again into Sin; theſe are not cured; but thoſe that are freed from their Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe, may perhaps at ſome time be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken with Sin, and we cannot deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine how oft; but if the general tenor of their Lives be as becomes the Goſpel, tho they do Sin,<note place="margin">1 John 2.1.</note> they <hi>have an Advocate with the Father.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VII.</head>
               <p>I Will now ſhew you ſome Characters whereby you may make ſome Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of your Spiritual State. And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt many which others lay down, I ſhall inſiſt only on ſome few, which are moſt eaſy to be diſcerned in our ſelves. I never ſtudy to ſpeak (I will not ſay, all that may be ſaid, but) all that I can ſay on any Subject, remembring that of the Orator, <hi>Dictis eſt electio &amp; modus;</hi> for tho I reckon not my ſelf among
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:97942:55"/>
Learned men, yet I would follow them at a diſtance. And,</p>
               <p n="1">1. Obſerve what it is that you are chiefly guided by in the general courſe of your Life. What we chiefly mind, doth influence us in all the paſſages of our Lives: <hi>And they that are after the fleſh, mind the things of the fleſh; and they that are after the ſpirit,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 8.5.</note> 
                  <hi>the things of the ſpirit.</hi> That is, thoſe in a Natural ſtate chiefly mind, that is, ſavour and reliſh, ſet their affections on, are taken up in the purſuit of carnal things. The ſame word is uſed, <hi>Matth.</hi> 16.23. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.19.<note place="margin">John 3.5. Rom. 8.1.</note> 
                  <hi>Col.</hi> 3.2. So thoſe <hi>that are born of the ſpirit, walk after the ſpirit;</hi> are led by the Spirit, Savour, and Reliſh, ſet their Affections on, ſeek after Spiritual things. Now let us examine what it is that doth chiefly influence us in the ſeveral turnings of our lives. We con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider what will ſtand with, what will chiefly further that which is our great concernment; not what ſhould be ſo, but what we really make ſo. In chuſing Callings or Imployments, Relations, Places of abode, let us conſider what we look chiefly at, what ſways us moſt therein; whether we chuſe ſuch a Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, or way of Life, which will moſt advance us in the World, wherein we are moſt like to get great Eſtates, to
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:97942:55"/>
live at Eaſe, in Pleaſure; or whether in our choice we conſider rather what will moſt help us, or leaſt hinder us in the way to Heaven; where we are like to meet with feweſt Temptations. I deny not, but we may conſider how to live, ſo as we may be in a capacity <hi>to give rather than to receive;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Acts 20.35. 1 Theſ. 4.12.</note> 
                  <hi>That we may walk honeſtly towards them that are with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, having lack of nothing: but may pay every one their own, and be burden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome to none.</hi> But that which we ſhould, and ſhall ſeek in the firſt place, if our hearts be right within us, <hi>is the kingdom of God and his righteouſneſs.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Matth. 6.33.</note> Not for worldly advantage, chuſing for our ſelves, or ours, ſuch Imployments or Callings as may take up our time, ſo as we cannot <hi>wait upon the Lord without diſtraction;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 7.35.</note> or which may caſt us upon Temptations to exceſs, man-pleaſing, or other like Sins, which may deprive us of the benefit of the Ordinances of God, and force us to live amongſt Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laters or Heathens. If any ſay, ſome muſt follow ſuch Callings; leave them to ſuch as mind earthly things, and govern themſelves thereby. So it is in chuſing Relations; Let Perſons deal plainly and faithfully with themſelves, and they may know what it is that makes Matches for them, by their choice
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:97942:56"/>
therein: We may ſee (to allude to the words of <hi>Joſhua) whom they chuſe to ſerve;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Joſhua 24.15.</note> Whether their God is their Belly, and they chuſe to live at Eaſe, and in Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure; whether they be covetous Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laters, and look chiefly after great E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates; whether they do as thoſe that <hi>chuſe chief rooms at feaſts;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luke 14.7.</note> Crowding to get as high as they can, to get as near as may be towards the upper end of the World. I allow it to be not only law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, but prudent, for Perſons (ſo far as they can) to match within their own Rank; But as our Saviour ſaith in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther caſe, <hi>Theſe things ought ye to have done,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Matth. 23.23.</note> 
                  <hi>and not to leave the others undone.</hi> God in Judgment oft leaves Perſons to their own choice, ſo that they that will be rich, ſhall be ſo; and thoſe that ſeek Glory from men, ſhall have it. But where Men or Women ſet their Faces ſtedfaſtly to go to Heaven (to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lude to thoſe words, <hi>Luke</hi> 9.51.) they will conſider what help or encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment they ſhall meet with in the way thither; Conſidering what the Apoſtle means by <hi>marrying only in the Lord;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 7.19.</note> with one that is going the ſame way with us, whoſe Examples, Counſels, Prayers, we may have the help of, and with whom we may walk hand in hand to Heaven,<note place="margin">1 Peter 3.7.</note> 
                  <hi>as being heirs together of the ſame
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:97942:56"/>
grace of life.</hi> So in chuſing Services, what is it that you chiefly propound to your ſelves? Thoſe that are moſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent on profit, will inquire what Wages, what Vails, what Way of improving what they have; what Work for wear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and tearing their Cloaths: If Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons chiefly mind their Eaſe and Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, their enquiry is what Houſe they keep, what work they hold their Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants to, what liberty they give, what merry Company there is in the Family, or in the Neighbourhood. But thoſe that mind heavenly things, will conſider what help or furtherance they may have therein, whether God be ſerved or worſhipped in the Family, what Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry or Means of Grace they ſhall live under; what Servants or Neighbours there are, by whoſe Converſation they may gain any Spiritual Advantage, or be furthered in the way to Heaven. If we will commune with our own hearts about theſe things, and deal plainly with our ſelves, we ſhall eaſily ſee what is the bent and inclination of our minds.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Obſerve how you ſtand affected in hearing the word; many may take delight therein, but there is no certain judgment to be made of perſons there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by. There are ſeveral Herbs or Plants in the ſame field, yea, ſeveral parts of
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:97942:57"/>
the ſame plant or herb, which ſeveral Creatures of different kinds may delight in, or feed on; there are ſeveral Sermons, yea, ſeveral parts of the ſame Sermon, which divers perſons may be taken with. The Sheep perhaps feeds only on the tender leaf; the Horſe may perhaps eat the ſtalks with it; the Swine may feed on the root; the Bee on the flower; the Bird on the ſeed: ſo in hearing the word, ſome perſons may be pleaſed with flaſhes of wit, and flights of fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy; ſome with ſtrength of Reaſon, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilty of Argument, depth of Judgment; ſome with Hiſtories or Antiquities, ſome with Satyr or Invectives againſt thoſe that they are at variance with:<note place="margin">1 Pet. 2.2.</note> But o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers deſire rather <hi>the ſincere milk of the word, that they may grow thereby;</hi> The plain truths of the Goſpel, which may further them in the way to Heaven; ſuch things as may beſt diſcover their ſpiritual ſtate to them, that they may not be deceived in a matter of ſo great moment; ſuch things as will awaken him out of his drowſineſs and ſecurity, as will direct him in the way wherein he ſhould go;<note place="margin">Rev. 3.2.</note> as will <hi>ſtrengthen in him thoſe things which are remaining in him, and ready to die;</hi> ſtrengthen our faith, quicken our affections to heavenly things, build us up on our moſt holy faith. Some that
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:97942:57"/>
have good appetites, may love to have their meat well dreſſed, and ſerved hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomely in, but they can eat good meat without ſawce, and prefer the meat to the ſawce, or a ſubſtantial diſh to new-fangled diſhes, which are rather for ſhew and pleaſing the pallate, than for nouriſhment. Some may love to have their ſpiritual food brought to them, or conveyed to them in good and proper Language, who yet may more mind things than words, and the matter ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than the manner of delivery. God is pleaſed ſometimes ſo far to condeſcend to mens Temper and Genius, as to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vey the ſaving-truths of the Goſpel to their hearts in ſuch words as are plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and delightful to them; as Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians convey their Medicines to the Stomach in ſome vehicle that may be grateful to it: So <hi>Auſtin</hi> was a great Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, and one that taught Rhetorick; and <hi>Ambroſe</hi> being an eloquent Preacher, he was much delighted with his preaching, and it pleaſed God by thoſe words which he chiefly minded, to inſinuate into him thoſe things which before he minded not. He was very much pleaſed with <hi>Tulli</hi>'s Works, and (as <hi>Pelitian</hi> prefer'd <hi>Pindar</hi>'s Odes before <hi>David</hi>'s Pſalms, ſo he) preferred his Style to that of the Scripture, when he firſt began to read
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:97942:58"/>
them, but afterwards he blamed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf for it; and when he read his <hi>Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſius,</hi> which before he had been pleaſed with above the reſt of his Works, he diſliked it, becauſe he found not the Name of Chriſt there. Mr. <hi>Robert Bol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> having heard the Fame of Mr. <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kins,</hi> going at a Commencement to <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge,</hi> went to hear him preach, and having heard him, he ſaid, he was a paſſing mean Scholar, and a barren em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pty fellow: but when God changed his heart, he changed his opinion of Mr. <hi>Perkins,</hi> accounting him as learned and godly a Divine as this Church had for many years enjoyed, conſidering his age; for he was born and died in the Reign of Queen <hi>Elizabeth:</hi> It is ſaid of him, That he taught <hi>England</hi> to preach; and a learned Prelate gives this Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of him, that he excelled in a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct Judgment, and a rare dexterity in clearing the obſcure ſubtilties of the School, and eaſy explication of the moſt perplexed Diſcourſes. A ſick perſon that deſires Cure and Health, is not ſo much for a learned and ingenious Phyſician, that is good company, and one that will diſcourſe aptly and pertinently on any Subject; but he is for a skilful and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Phyſician that underſtands his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe, and will apply proper Remedies,
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:97942:58"/>
and ſuch Phyſick as will rather work ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually, than pleaſe his Taſte, or not make him ſick. We value or chuſe things according to the tendency which they have to the end which we aim at, or propound to our ſelves. So men <hi>heap up to themſelves teachers after their own luſts,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Tim. 4.3.</note> ſuch as may pleaſe or gratify their cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt inclinations. As if men be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted to Debauchery or Drunkenneſs;<note place="margin">Mic. 2.11.</note> he that <hi>will propheſy of wine and ſtrong drink, ſhall be the prophet of ſuch a perſon;</hi> he that will encourage him in his wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs. So on the other hand, If a man ſeek the Kingdom of God and his Righteouſneſs in the firſt place, or above all other things, he is for ſuch an one, and for ſuch preaching as will direct and help him in his way thither.</p>
               <p n="3">3 Let us examine what it is that we chiefly deſire of God in our Prayers; this will diſcover much of the bent and inclination of our hearts, and what it is that we chiefly mind. I ſpeak not of the Prayers which we utter in the publick Congregation, or in our Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, or before others on any occaſion: In theſe caſes perſons do not always ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter their own deſires, but many times at beſt ſuch things as may expreſs the deſires of thoſe with whom they pray, or the deſires which they know in their
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:97942:59"/>
own Conſciences they and others ought to have: but many times men pray for oſtentation, or for a pretence, to ſhew their talent in expreſſing themſelves, or to ſeem more religious than they are: but thoſe Prayers whereby we may make a judgment of our ſelves, are the pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers which we pour out to God in ſecret, not by rote or by book, but from the bottom of our hearts, which we may know by dealing faithfully with our ſelves. Men indeed ask for ſuch things as they are convinc'd they ought to pray for, or as they have accuſtom'd them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to pray for, or which they have learned to pray for by hearing good Men pray, or out of good Books, it may be out of the Lord's Prayer: But theſe are not their real deſires, and they would not be willing to be taken at their word, to walk ſo ſtrictly as they pray that they may walk, to do the Will of God on Earth as it is done in Heaven; to have their ſins forgiven, only as they forgive others: But what are our real <hi>requeſts which we make known to God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Phil. 4.6.</note> which our hearts do ſincerely concur with; or what are theſe requeſts uttered by others with whom we join in prayer, that our hearts do cloſe with, and which we add our hearty Amen to; It is but a word of courſe with many,
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:97942:59"/>
and they deal with themſelves as men deal many times with others, ſetting their hand to petitions which they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver gave their conſent to: but what are the petitions which we really own, and would gladly have anſwered? Are they for <hi>Solomon</hi>'s Leavings, Riches, long Life, the lives of our Enemies? Are they ſuch as the Sons of <hi>Zebedee</hi> asked,<note place="margin">Matth. 20.21.</note> Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours and Preferments? or rather ſuch as <hi>Solomon</hi>'s petition was, for Wiſdom, not to govern a Kingdom, but to get a Kingdom? <hi>to make us wiſe to Salvation,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Tim. 3.15. Prov. 16.32. Pſal 4.7. Pſal. 119.80. Pſal. 119.4, 5.</note> to rule our own ſpirits? that he would lift upon us the light of his Counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance; that our <hi>hearts may be found in his Statutes?</hi> do we turn <hi>precepts</hi> as well as promiſes into Prayers? deſiring that God would direct or incline our hearts to what he requires us? Do we pray rather for the fruit, or a ſanctified uſe of Affliction, than deliverance from it;<note place="margin">Heb. 12.1. Pſalm 89.15. Pſalm 119.10.</note> that tho we cannot <hi>walk in the light of God's Countenance,</hi> yet we may walk by the light of his Word; that though we may not with <hi>John, lie in Chriſt</hi>'s <hi>boſom,</hi> yet we may with <hi>Mary,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Jo. 13.23.</note> 
                  <hi>ſit down at his feet to hear his word, fearing the Lord,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luc. 10.39.</note> 
                  <hi>and obeying the voice of his ſervants, tho we walk in darkneſs, and ſee no light,</hi> have nothing of comfort.<note place="margin">Iſ 50.10.</note>
               </p>
               <p n="4">
                  <pb n="94" facs="tcp:97942:60"/>4. Let us examine our ſelves by our company. Here the rule holds, <hi>Noſcitur ex ſocio,</hi> &amp;c. If we know not what a man is, we may give a near gueſs by his company; if a ſtranger come amongſt us, we may conjecture at his temper, tho we never come near him, by the company that he chuſes, and ordinarily aſſociates himſelf with. It is true, it may be our unhappy lot to be caſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong ſuch whoſe ſociety may be a bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den to us,<note place="margin">Pſa. 120.5.</note> and we may be neceſſitated by our worldly occaſions to keep com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany with prophane and wicked per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons:<note place="margin">1 Cor. 5.10.</note> But who are they in whoſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany we chiefly delight, or whom we chuſe to make our familiar friends and companions?<note place="margin">Pſal. 16.3.</note> all <hi>David</hi>'s <hi>delight was in the Saints,</hi> thoſe he accounted the moſt excellent perſons. <hi>He was a companion of thoſe that feared God, and invited ſuch to turn to him;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 119.63, 79.</note> they are ſuch that the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere Chriſtian makes choice of as his boſome friends, not only as they are dear to God;<note place="margin">1 Jo. 5.1.</note> 
                  <hi>and ſo loving him that he begat, he loves him that is begotten of him,</hi> and would <hi>ſhew kindneſs to ſuch for his ſake,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Sam. 9.1.7.</note> as <hi>David</hi> ſhewed <hi>kindneſs to</hi> Mephi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boſheth <hi>for</hi> Jonathan's <hi>ſake.</hi> But like will to like. It is natural in brute Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; and perſons are in their element when they are converſing with thoſe
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:97942:60"/>
like themſelves. we may obſerve ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily, at any publick meetings where there are ſeveral ſorts of perſons, who they are that get together, and how they ſort or divide themſelves. If there be Scholars or Learned Men, they will be together; Husbandmen will aſſoci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciate together; ſo Merchants or other Trades-men: not only as they can beſt bear a part in ſuch diſcourſe as perſons of their own way have together, and are not, as the Apoſtle ſaith in another caſe, <hi>Barbarians</hi> to each other; but they reliſh ſuch diſcourſe as is of things in their own element, as we ſpeak: and which is more, they may get a further inſight into their own Calling or Buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, by the experience of others which they communicate to them; ſo it is with Chriſtians, when they meet with thoſe that ſpeak of things pertaining to the Kingdom of God; It is like one fallen into the company of thoſe that ſpeak their own Language, or Diſcourſe of matters belonging to their own cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling; we may gain experience by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſing with ſuch. As the Apoſtle <hi>longed to be at Rome, that he might not only im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part ſome ſpiritual gift to them,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 1.11, 12.</note> 
                  <hi>but that he might be comforted together with them, by their mutual faith.</hi> Chriſtians may be helpful to others that are far above them
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:97942:61"/>
in gifts and knowledge; as <hi>Junius</hi> ſaith of himſelf in his own Life, tho he was a means of increaſing the knowledge of an honeſt Countryman that he acciden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally met with, yet the Countryman was a means of inflaming his Zeal; he ſpeaking with ſuch feeling and ſuch a ſavoury reliſh of the matters of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, as made him think there was ſomething yet further in Chriſtianity than he had attained to; ſo that Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians ſharpen each other by their mutual converſe,<note place="margin">Prov. 2.7.17. Pſalm 66.16. Pſal. 34.2.</note> 
                  <hi>as Iron ſharpens Iron. David</hi> would tell others <hi>what God had done for his Soul; and the humble,</hi> (thoſe that were brought low by affliction, and not too proud to learn) <hi>ſhould bear thereof, and be glad,</hi> that there had been others in like con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition with themſelves, and yet had ſound mercy and help; yea, they ſhould ſay,<note place="margin">V. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>This poor man cryed, and the Lord heard him, and ſaved him out of all his trouble.</hi> They ſhould not conſider him as a King, as a Prophet, as a man after God's own heart, for the eminency of Grace; but as a poor man ſeeking ſhelter among ſtrangers,<note place="margin">1 Sam. 21.11, &amp;c.</note> and (which is worſe) uſing ſuch poor mean ſhifts as he did; deba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting himſelf ſo far below that Courage and Faith which he had at other times: for this Pſalm was compoſed upon <hi>his changing his behaviour before</hi> Abimelech,
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:97942:61"/>
when he drove him away, and he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted; the ſtory of which we have 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 21.11, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> on ſuch grounds a godly man will chuſe ſuch for his ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſaries, his near or familiar friends.</p>
               <p>Theſe are the few things amongſt many, about which I would have Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians to examine themſelves, that they may be the better able to make a judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment concerning their Spiritual State, and to take the comfort of their Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Privileges, eſpecially in times of trouble, and when we approach to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards our latter end.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VIII.</head>
               <p>FAith is yet a great help againſt Trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, as we thereby have the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort and benefit of the Promiſes of God, which are ſo <hi>exceeding great and precious.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Pet. 1.4.</note>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. It is a great thing for God to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige himſelf to us by promiſe, as <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſaith, Confeſ. <hi>L.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 9. <hi>Thou art pleaſed, becauſe thy Mercy endures for ever, to become a Debtor by thy pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, to thoſe to whom thou haſt for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>given all their Debts.</hi> We love to be free and diſengaged, and would have others ſtand to our courteſy for that which we intend to give them: but
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:97942:62"/>
we would not give them that advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage againſt us to challenge us upon our word. But it hath pleaſed God for our more abundant conſolation, ſo far to condeſcend to poor ſinners, that we may, as <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſaith (in the place be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore cited) of his Mother, urge upon him his own hand-writing, or plead as <hi>David,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 119.49. 1 Jo. 5.10.</note> 
                  <hi>Remember thy word to thy Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, on which thou haſt cauſed me to hope.</hi> For we make him a lyar if we do not truſt his promiſe.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The promiſes of God are exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing great and precious in reſpect of the <hi>matter</hi> of them: he having promiſed ſo many and ſo great things which we ſhould not have had the confidence to ask or think, if he had not encouraged us by ſuch promiſes. And as there are in Phyſick ſome <hi>Catholick</hi> remedies, and ſome particular Medicines for particular Diſeaſes; ſo there are ſome <hi>general</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſive promiſes, as that great pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe in which all the promiſes of the life that now is, and that which is to come are ſummed up, That God will be our God, or that he will be a God to us.<note place="margin">1 Chr. 17.24. Heb. 8.10.</note> So that promiſe which occurs ſo oft in Scripture, that God will be with us: which is not to be with us as he is <hi>in all places,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Jer 23.24.</note> or ſo as to be an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concerned ſpectator of what befalls us;
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:97942:62"/>
but ſo as to deal well with us, as <hi>Jacob</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounds it, as we ſhall ſee by comparing <hi>Gen.</hi> 31.3. with <hi>Gen.</hi> 32.9. So there are ſome promiſes wherein ſeveral things are put together as many ingredients in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to one Cordial: ſuch is that promiſe,<note place="margin">Pſ. 84.11.</note> 
                  <hi>that God will be a Sun and Shield, that he will give grace and glory, and will withhold no good thing from ſuch as walk uprightly.</hi> ThiS pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe comprehends all the good things of the life that now is, and of that which is to come. And I know not but the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle may have particular reſpect to this promiſe, there being a promiſe of things Temporal, Spiritual, Eternal;<note place="margin">1 Tim. 4.8</note> of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, Direction, Protection, Proviſion. But there are <hi>particular</hi> promiſes ſuited to the ſeveral conditions of Chriſtians, which are by ſome reduced to ſeveral heads, and brothers ſummed together in the order wherein they ſtand in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. So that whatever circumſtances we are in, we may find promiſes ſuited thereto. And as they are exceeding great and precious in reſpect of the <hi>ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> and great <hi>variety</hi> of them; ſo they are precious in reſpect of the <hi>truth and certainty</hi> of them. This is it that makes other promiſes from men of ſo little value, that every man is a lyar.<note place="margin">Pſal. 116.11.</note> 
                  <hi>David</hi> indeed ſpake that raſhly, and it may be therein might have reſpect to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:97942:63"/>
which were made to him from God by <hi>Samuel</hi> or <hi>Nathan,</hi> as under temptation he ſaid he ſhould <hi>one day periſh by the hand of Saul,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Sam. 27.1.</note> and then the promiſe would have failed. But he did more deliberately ſay, <hi>men of low degree are vanity, and men of high degree a lye;</hi> deceiving others either through weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs or wickedneſs;<note place="margin">Pſal. 62.9.</note> either not being able to make good what they have un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adviſedly promiſed, or willingly flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering them into vain expectations of what they never intended to do for them. But theſe are <hi>promiſes of God that cannot lye.</hi> As he is <hi>faithful that hath promiſed,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Tit. 1.2. Heb. 11.11. Rom. 4.2. Pſal. 77.8.</note> ſo he is able alſo to perform; and tho we are ready to ſay ſometimes, <hi>doth his promiſe fail for evermore?</hi> We do either through ignorance miſtake the meaning of them, as the <hi>Jews</hi> of Old, and many ſtill are ready to expound many promiſes too rigidly according to the letter: or we are ready to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand thoſe things abſolutely, which are to be underſtood with that limita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſo far as they are for our good,<note place="margin">Pſal. 34.10 84.11. Eccleſ. 6.12.</note> which we are not always competent judges of; or we are too quick and impatient of delays: the viſion is for an appointed time;<note place="margin">Hab. 2.4.</note> and the things which <hi>God hath promiſed ſhall be fulfilled in their ſeaſon.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luk. 1.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>0.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="101" facs="tcp:97942:63"/>I will now ſhew you how by Faith we have the comfort and benefit of theſe promiſes.</p>
               <p n="1">1. By Faith we have an intereſt in the promiſes. We read of the <hi>covenants of promiſe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eph. 2.12.</note> whereby we may either un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the promiſes of the Covenant, there being the like <hi>Hypallage</hi> oft found in Scripture;<note place="margin">Rom. 9.31.</note> as by the <hi>Law of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs,</hi> is meant <hi>the righteouſneſs of the Law. And the Nations of thoſe that ſhall be ſaved,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rev. 21.24.</note> are <hi>thoſe that ſhall be ſaved of the Nations.</hi> And it may be called the Covenants, becauſe tho it be one in the ſubſtance of it, yet it is diverſe in reſpect of its adminiſtration; on which account it is called both Old and New.<note place="margin">Heb. 8.13.</note> Or it is called the Covenants of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, as being founded on, and conſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in promiſes. In Scripture we find promiſes frequently called Covenants,<note place="margin">Gen 6.18. 2 Chron. 7.18. Ezr. 10.3. Neh 9.38.</note> Covenants conſiſting of mutual pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes or engagements: and where the promiſe on one ſide only is expreſſed, the engagement on the other ſide is ordinarily implied. Now there is no <hi>caſe</hi> wherein the words <hi>Promiſe</hi> and <hi>Covenant</hi> may with more reaſon be uſed promiſcuouſly than in this caſe in hand,<note place="margin">Gal. 3.17.22.</note> and ſo they are uſed by the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle; for tho this Covenant be not an abſolute promiſe, there being ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:97942:64"/>
to be done by the Mediator of it for the confirmation thereof, as likewiſe by us for partaking of the benefit of it: yet it is <hi>ordered in all things and ſure;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Sam. 23.5.</note> and not ſuſpended on any uncertain condition, depending on our fluctuating will; but what is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired on our part is likewiſe promiſed to be wrought in us.<note place="margin">Jer. 31.33. John 6.37. Eph. 2.8.</note> So that as there are promiſes <hi>to conditions,</hi> which I may ſpeak without the offence of thoſe that underſtand what is ordinarily or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly meant by a condition: ſo there are promiſes <hi>of thoſe conditions.</hi> Now this promiſe or Covenant <hi>by faith of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gal. 3.22.</note> 
                  <hi>is given to them that believe;</hi> Faith intitling us to the grand promiſe, whereof all the reſt are branches: all theſe being <hi>yea and amen, faithful and true in Jeſus Chriſt;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Cor. 1.20. Dan. 9.27.</note> who as Mediator of the Covenant, died for the confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of it. For the further clearing of this matter, we muſt know, that many of the promiſes in Scripture were made to particular perſons, and on ſome ſpecial occaſion: yet we muſt not look upon ſuch things as the caſes of thoſe perſons only (as ſome call them) that do not concern others: for what is put into the Canon of Scripture, is there left on Record for our Inſtruction and Comfort.<note place="margin">Rom. 15.4.</note> So that we ſhall find the things therein ſpoken, applied to ſuch
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:97942:64"/>
as lived many Hundred years after, as if they had been directed particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly to them. So the Prophet ſaith,<note place="margin">Hoſ. 12.4.</note> that God ſpake <hi>with them,</hi> that which he ſpake to <hi>Jacob</hi> in <hi>Bethel,</hi> ſo many Hundred year before. And that which was ſpoken to <hi>Moſes</hi> is ſaid to be <hi>ſpoken</hi> to the <hi>Jews</hi> in Chriſt's time;<note place="margin">Exod. 3.6. Matt. 22.31. Prov. 3.11. Heb. 12 5. Joſ. 1.5.</note> and what was ſpoken in <hi>Solomons</hi> time is applied to the <hi>Hebrews</hi> in the Apoſtles time. And ſo the promiſe that was made to <hi>Joſhua</hi> upon a particular occaſion, is applied to the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> tho in another caſe; God being always the ſame, and bearing the ſame love to his People, and ſo is with them, as I ſaid before, to deal well with them, and to do for them as the matter requires. And tho we cannot ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect, that God ſhould deal with us in every reſpect according to his promiſe made to others, yet we may take en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement from thence to hope, that he will deal proportionably with us. Miniſters of the Goſpel cannot expect that God ſhould enable them to work Miracles, becauſe of what he promiſed to the Apoſtles when he ſent them forth;<note place="margin">Mark. 16.17.</note> or that he ſhould ſecure them from the aſſaults of wicked men, becauſe of what he promiſed to <hi>Paul</hi> at <hi>Corinth.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Acts 18.10.</note> But we may thence conclude, that his grace ſhall be ſufficient for us: that we ſhall have help and aſſiſtance from him
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:97942:65"/>
according to the work which he calls us to;<note place="margin">Acts 26.22.</note> and that where he hath any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to ſave, he will find ways and means for the effecting of it, and that he <hi>will work</hi> ſo as none ſhall let.<note place="margin">Iſa. 43.13.</note> Again, there are promiſes made to perſons un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſome particular circumſtances, as to the Fatherleſs and Widows, to the Poor and Needy, to the Sick, to thoſe that ſuffer for Righteouſneſs ſake; and we may not be concerned in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes made to ſuch. Now it is in this caſe, as in thoſe commands that are given to ſeveral relations.<note place="margin">Eph. 5.22, &amp;c.</note> Tho ſuch commands concern us not at preſent, as they cannot all reach to all; yet as any come into ſuch relations, they come un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the obligation of ſuch commands. So as any come into ſuch circumſtances, they come under the influence of ſuch promiſes as are made to perſons in them. We read, it may be, Books of Phyſick, or Surgery, and there meet with receipts or remedies which we have no need of: let us make uſe of thoſe which we have need of, and thank God that we are free from ſo many Diſeaſes, as we perceive by ſuch Books poor mortals are ſubjects to: and that there are ſuch remedies in rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſs, in caſe we ſhould need them. So when we read ſuch variety of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:97942:65"/>
in Scripture, let us bleſs God that we are exempted from ſo many trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles as are there provided againſt; that there are ſuch promiſes laid in for ſuch as do want them, and that they are there in readineſs for us, if we ſhould be reduced to ſuch a condition. Some promiſes are made to perſons under ſome particular <hi>character or qualification,</hi> as to the meek, the humble, to thoſe that fear God, or love him; to thoſe that truſt in him, to the upright in heart, or of an upright converſation. But all theſe are ſeveral Characters of the ſame perſons: grace being as leven that levens the whole lump;<note place="margin">1 Theſ. 5.23.</note> tho ſome grace may appear more eminently in one than in another, and ſome more eminently than another in the ſame per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, as they meet or fall in with their natural temper or inclination. For when theſe meet, they are as Wind and Tide meeting together; or they are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed by thoſe graces which conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their circumſtances or temptations they have moſt occaſion for the exerciſe of: and therefore they may appear moſt eminently in them: and ſo ſuch promiſes may be made to ſuch perſons as are moſt ſuitable to them, or proper for them in the circumſtances wherin at preſent they are; and as I ſaid in the former caſe, are
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:97942:66"/>
in readineſs for us when our condition requires them. How we have the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of the Promiſes by Faith, we may ſee partly by what I have already ſaid: and it is implied in that word where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by it is expreſſed in Scripture, relying or reſting on God, the Soul is then at eaſe.<note place="margin">2 Chron. 13.18.16.7. Pſ. 37.7.</note> But as I there ſhewed you, it is not the habit of Faith, but the actual exerciſe of it, that expels fear and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, as light doth darkneſs. But it will appear further by what I have yet to add; and that is, that by Faith we do as the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>obtain the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 11.33.</note> that is, the things promiſed; <hi>faith gives glory to God,</hi> in ſealing to his truth or veracity;<note place="margin">Rom. 4.20. Jo.3.33. Matt. 9.2.22.29.</note> therefore God ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours Faith in dealing with men accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding thereto. And in many other places, <hi>we ſee faith ſaved them</hi> from temporal Evils. The ſame we find in the caſe of <hi>Aſa;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Chron. 6, 7, 8, 9. 1 Chron. 5.20. Jer. 39.17, 18.</note> ſo God was intreated of the <hi>Rubenites</hi> and <hi>Gadites,</hi> when they cried to him becauſe they truſted in him; ſo he ſaved <hi>Ebedmelech</hi> from the men that he was afraid of, <hi>becauſe he truſted in him,</hi> according to that remarkable promiſe made to the righteous, that <hi>the Lord ſhall help them and deliver them;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſ. 37.40.</note> 
                  <hi>deliver them from the wicked, and ſave them, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they truſt in him;</hi> whereas on the contrary, the noble man that would not
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:97942:66"/>
believe the plenty that ſhould be in <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maria,</hi> did not eat of it.<note place="margin">2 Kings 7.19, 20.</note> Many of the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> entred not into the promiſed Land, <hi>becauſe of their unbelief. Zechariah,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 3.19.</note> a good man, was dumb for a time, <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he believed not the words of God which were to be fulfilled in their ſeaſon.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luke 1.20.</note> There is a ſeaſon for many things to be ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled which we muſt wait for: <hi>unbelief makes God a lyar;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Jo. 5.10.</note> therefore he will ſhew his diſpleaſure againſt it. But it is ſo likewiſe in Spiritual bleſſings; we read of great things aſcribed to Faith;<note place="margin">Acts 15.9.</note> as purifying the heart; <hi>overcoming the World,</hi> quenching all the fiery darts of the wicked.<note place="margin">1 Jo. 5.4. Eph. 6.17.</note> Now it doth not all theſe things in a moral way, as <hi>Moſes</hi> over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came by looking to <hi>the recompence of the reward:</hi> but we are thereby <hi>ſtrong in the Lord, and in the power of his might;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 11.26. Epheſ. 6.10. 2 Tim 2.1. 1 Peter 1.5. Col. 1.11.</note> or <hi>in the grace that is in Chriſt Jeſus:</hi> and we <hi>are kept by the power of God through Faith to Salvation.</hi> It is the Divine Power that keeps us, and we are <hi>ſtrengthned</hi> thereby, or <hi>according</hi> thereto; and not only morally by his word, as men may ſtrengthen each other;<note place="margin">Job 43.4. Ezek. 13.22.</note> but it is Faith that takes in this aid or aſſiſtance of Grace, or the <hi>ſupplies of the Spirit of Jeſus Chriſt;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Phil. 1.9.</note> which are communicated from him to the ſeveral Members of his Myſtical Body, as the Spirits are
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:97942:67"/>
from the Head in the Natural Body; and as <hi>Chriſt dwells in the heart by faith,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Epheſ. 3.17.</note> ſo we derive Spiritual Life and Virtue from him, in the daily Exerciſe of Faith; he leaving thoſe uſually to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves that truſt to their own ſtrength; as Youth and Young men are ready to do; when thoſe that wait on the Lord, and look to him for ſupplies of Grace, ſhall ſurmount all difficulties, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſevere in well-doing without <hi>wearineſs</hi> or <hi>fainting.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſaiah 40.30, 31. Pſalm 27.14.</note> 
                  <hi>He will ſtrengthen the heart of thoſe that wait on him,</hi> and give Grace to ſuch humble Souls, as diſtruſting them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, rely upon him for ſtrength and aſſiſtance.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IX.</head>
               <p>THere is yet one way more whereby Faith becomes ſuch an effectual Remedy againſt Touble, and that is, as we thereby have a view or proſpect of the other World, or of the Future ſtate. <hi>We thereby look to the things that are not ſeen, which are eternal.</hi> And if any ſhall ſay,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 4.18.</note> the word there uſed, doth not imply that he ſaw them, or had a view of them, but only that he made them his ſcope or aim: I anſwer, The word ſometimes ſignifies to mark or
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:97942:67"/>
obſerve, as well as to conſider or have reſpect to.<note place="margin">Rom. 16.17. Phil. 3.17. Heb. 11.27.</note> And we do in a ſort ſee the things which we aim at: <hi>Moſes</hi> is ſaid to <hi>endure, as ſeeing him that is viſible;</hi> which implies not the manner of his enduring, but the ground of it; not as if he had ſeen him that is inviſible, but becauſe he ſaw him that is invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, or like one that ſaw the inviſible God.<note place="margin">John 1.14.</note> So <hi>as the glory of the only begotten Son of God, is a glory becoming ſuch an one.</hi> And if it be ſaid, there is a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction in the terms, to ſee him that is Inviſible: I anſwer, It is an Elegan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy uſed frequently in Scriptures, where a word in the ſame place is taken in different ſenſes, <hi>as to believe in hope,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 4.18. 1 Tim. 5.6.</note> 
                  <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt hope. And ſhe that liveth in plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, is dead while ſhe lives.</hi> She lives Naturally, but is dead Spiritually. So God is inviſible to our bodily Eyes, but we <hi>ſee him by faith, which is the evidence of things not ſeen.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 11.1.</note> And if it be further objected, that Faith and Sight are op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed in Scripture; as, <hi>We walk by faith, and not by ſight. And in whom,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Cor. 5.7. 1 Pet. 1.8.</note> 
                  <hi>tho now ye ſee him not, yet believing, ye rejoice with joy unſpeakable, and full of glory.</hi> For this latter place, diſtinguiſh of ſeeing as before, and the ſenſe is plain; and for the former place, Faith is there oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, either to the Viſion of God which
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:97942:68"/>
we ſhall have in the Future ſtate, or to preſent ſenſe; implying that we ſhould govern our lives not by Senſe, or what we ſee, but by what we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live, or hereafter hope for. And the Apoſtle when he would ſet forth the virtue of Faith, and of what excellent uſe it is to ſupport Chriſtians under Trials and Sufferings; he grounds it upon this,<note place="margin">Heb. 11.1.</note> that it is <hi>the ſubſtance of things hoped for, and the evidence of things not ſeen.</hi> It gives as it were a real and preſent ſubſiſtence to things that are yet but future, and ſo hoped for; and giveth us as full ſatisfaction con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning thoſe things which we do not ſee, as if we ſaw them clearly before our eyes. And theſe two things make that which is future to affect us more, and work more effectually upon us. We ſay indeed among men, that ſeeing is believing. And they have Proverbial Speeches in other Nations, like this of our own; There is ſo much deceit and falſhood to be found among men, that perſons will hardly believe till they ſee, or have ſufficient ground for it; and ſo will not venture much on un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain hopes. But when we have to do with God that cannot lie, believing is ſeeing; that is, when we have his Word to ground our Faith upon, we
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:97942:68"/>
are as ſure as if we ſaw with our eyes, or as if things were proved to us by a Mathematical Demonſtration; that is, by ſuch clear evidence as nothing can be objected againſt. But tho we look upon things as certain, they do not much affect us, if we look upon them as at a great diſtance of time: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wicked men relieve themſelves againſt the fear of future Evils, by look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon them as at a great diſtance;<note place="margin">Ezek. 12.27. Amos 6.3.</note> 
                  <hi>or putting far away the evil day.</hi> We are likewiſe encouraged to patience by the near approach of the recompense of reward; <hi>becauſe he that ſhall come, will come, and will not tarry:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 10.37. James 5.8, 9. Luke 21.28.</note> 
                  <hi>The coming of the Lord draws nigh: The judge ſtands before the door.</hi> And our Saviour bids his Diſciples <hi>lift up their heads when their redemption draws nigh.</hi> If perſons were going to ſome places, and tired with the tediouſneſs of their Journey, and diſcouraged with the Difficulties and Dangers that they meet with in their way, queſtioning whether they ſhould find the way to it, or hold out till they come at it; ſhould come to the top of an Hill, and before they are aware, ſee the place that they are going to, a little before them, what Courage and Life would it preſently put into them? As <hi>Columbus</hi> that firſt diſcovered the <hi>Weſt
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:97942:69"/>
Indies,</hi> when his men were ready to Mutiny, having been wearied with a Voyage of Sixty days over the Ocean, he perceiving the Clouds to look clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, concluded that they were not far from Land; and ſo promiſed them to return, if they did not within three days diſcover Land, which they did before the end of the third day. So if we could get a ſight of the other World, as <hi>Moſes</hi> did of the Land of <hi>Cannan, on the top of Piſgah;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Deut. 3.27.</note> What Vigour and Life would it add to us, when we are ready to faint and be diſcouraged? Now Faith (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Deſcription given of it) ſerves us as a Teleſcope or Perſpective Glaſs, diſcovering to us the things which we ſee not, and making things ſeem near which are afar off. We there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by have as full certainty of the things of the other World, as if they <hi>were evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently ſet forth before your eyes,</hi> to uſe the Apoſtles words.<note place="margin">Gal. 3.1.</note> Yea, the things of eternity are hereby brought near to us, and ſeem to us as at hand, and thereby our Affections are much abated to the things of this World: The time being ſhort, and the faſhion of this World paſſing away, we may rejoice in the good things of it, as if we rejoiced not, and mourn for the evil things of it, as if we wept not; moderate both our
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:97942:69"/>
Joy and Sorrow, the end of all things being at hand, and we being even rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to enter upon the borders of Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity.<note place="margin">1 Cor. 7.29, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>And that we may the better under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand how Faith brings things nearer to us, or makes them ſeem at a leſs diſtance; let us conſider, that God being Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, and ſeeing all things at one ſingle view, one day is with him as a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand years, and a thouſand years as one day; and tho we are indeed finite Creatures, and meaſure Time by Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion; yet taking a view of Eternity, and looking to the things that are Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, the things of this World are no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing compared therewith, and the time of this Life but as a moment in compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon with the days of Eternity. We may obſerve, That Old men that have lived long in the World, make nothing of Seven years, yea, reckon Twenty years but a ſhort time; when Younger perſons look upon it as a long time. Thoſe that are of narrow minds, and conſider no more than what they have ſeen, and have never gone far from home, look upon Twenty or Thirty miles as a long way. But thoſe that have travelled to the <hi>Indies,</hi> or Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of miles from home, reckon Twenty or Thirty Miles as nothing;
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:97942:70"/>
yea, thoſe that have by the Study of Geography, or looking on Globes or Maps, obſerved the vaſt Compaſs of the World, would account ſo many Miles as a very ſmall matter; and a great Traveller would think himſelf as good as at home, if he were within ſo many Miles of it. So tho we were ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver taken up as <hi>Paul</hi> into the Third Heaven, yet the Deſcription which we have of it in the Scriptures, may ſink the things of this World quite below our Conſideration. Thoſe that write Deſcriptions of other Countries, give us an Account ordinarily of the Scitua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Place, the Compaſs or Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of it, the Nature of the Soil, the Commodities that it affords, the Health<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs of the Air, the Genius or Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of the People. But the Countries ſo deſcribed, are ſometimes found to be but imaginary <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>topia</hi>'s, or meer Fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies: And others when we come to ſee them, fall far ſhort of the Deſcription which we had of them, and deceive our Expectations. But as we have by Faith a full Aſſurance of future Glory; the Scripture being <hi>no cunningly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed fable;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Pet. 1.16.</note> ſo we are aſſured it will not deceive our Hopes, or fall ſhort of the Account which we have of it in the Scrpitures. As <hi>Luther</hi> would ſay,
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:97942:70"/>
Chriſt and Heaven are not capable of an <hi>Hyperbole.</hi> For tho it is true, that may be ſaid of them which is falſe; yet their true and real Worth will ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed whatever the Tongue of Men and Angels can ſpeak of them. The report which the Queen of <hi>Sheba</hi> heard of the Glory and Wiſdom of <hi>Solomon</hi> in her own Country, exceeded her belief; but what ſhe found when ſhe came to ſee, far exceeded the Report;<note place="margin">1 Kings 10.7, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>The one half of it had not been told her.</hi> So glorious things are ſpoken of the City of God. Chriſt tells his Diſciples, There were many Manſions in his Fathers houſe, enow to receive not only the innumerable Company of Angels, but the General Aſſembly of that <hi>great multitude which no man can number, of all nations, and kindreds,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rev. 7.9. Pſalm 16.11.</note> 
                  <hi>and people, and tongues: There is fulneſs of joy, and pleaſures for evermore.</hi> And it is not as ſome places, where there is plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of all things, but the Air is bad, ſo as the Inhabitants are but ſhort-liv'd;<note place="margin">Iſaiah 33.24. Rev. 21.4.</note> 
                  <hi>but there the inhabitants ſhall not ſay they are ſick: There will be no death, nor ſorrow, nor crying, nor pain.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I will not take upon me to ſet forth particularly the greatneſs of this Glory; <hi>It being that which eye hath not ſeen, nor ear heard, nor hath entered into the heart of man.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 2.9.</note> And that which God hath pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared,
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:97942:71"/>
                  <hi>that he might therein ſhew the riches of his glory on the veſſels of mercy, which he hath afore prepared unto glory.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 9.23.</note> We muſt not conſider things <hi>abſolutely,</hi> but <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paratively,</hi> and this will much alter our Account of them. Let us obſerve the Account which the Apoſtle gives of his own Sufferings, and his Fellow-Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians; they were preſſed out of meaſure, above ſtrength, inſomuch that they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpaired even of Life; and for his own part,<note place="margin">Acts 20.23.</note> 
                  <hi>bonds and afflictions did abide him</hi> wherever he went; and we have a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Account of his Sufferings, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.23, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But when he comes to ſpeak of theſe things comparatively, ſee how he changes his ſtile in one of the higheſt ſtrains of Rhetorick that is to be found in Scripture, or any other Author. Theſe afflictions which in themſelves were ſo grievous, and did often return upon them, as the clouds return after the rain, were but light, and <hi>for a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 4.17.</note> 
                  <hi>compared with that far more exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and eternal weight of glory,</hi> which they wrought for them; obſerve how he raiſes his ſtrain, he begins high, yet how many notes doth he riſe? Glory, a weight of glory, an exceeding weight of glory, a more exceeding weight of glory, a far more exceeding weight of glory; yea, once more, a far more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:97942:71"/>
and eternal weight of glory; and tho the word <hi>Hyperbole</hi> be twice uſed in the <hi>Greek,</hi> there is no <hi>Hyperbole</hi> or Exceſs in the Apoſtle's Speech; he doth uſe the word again and again, to make an attempt at expreſſing the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of glory, as if it were accumulated or heaped up, yet he cannot thereby reach the thing it ſelf which he would ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs: and tho there ſeems to be a <hi>Meioſis</hi> or diminution in the former part of the verſe, as if he did not juſtly rate the ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings of this life, he ſpeaks only of what they are comparatively,<note place="margin">Num. 13.33.</note> as the <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites</hi> were but <hi>Graſhoppers compared with the Giants;</hi> we ſhould learn from ſuch language in Scriptures to Habituate our ſelves to lower and meaner thoughts of the things of this world, and high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er thoughts of thoſe things of the world to come.<note place="margin">Zech. 1.12.</note> 
                  <hi>The Angels complain of the time wherein God had indignation againſt</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>it was threeſcore and ten years,</hi> but when it is compared with the ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting kindneſs wherewith he hath mercy on his people, it is but <hi>a little wrath, and for a moment.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſaiah 54.8.</note> Children look but a little way before them, and it ſeems hard to them to be kept to their books, and to School-diſcipline, or to hard labour under a ſevere maſter; and they conſider only the preſent eaſe and
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:97942:72"/>
pleaſure of others that are left to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. But their wiſer parents look further, and conſider how ſhort a time they are at School, or at an Apprenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, in compariſon with the reſt of their lives; what Preferments, what Riches many attain to by a good im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement of that time: and on the contrary, what Straits; what Miſeries, many are reduced to, that trifle away their younger years. But there is a far greater diſproportion betwixt the things of this life, and that which is to come, and as great a difference betwixt their duration and continuance.</p>
               <p>Now by Faith we take a view of the things that are not ſeen, which are e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal, and are as ſure of them, as if we ſaw them; as if we were with <hi>Paul caught up into Paradiſe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Cor. 12.4.</note> to ſee the glory of Heaven, or as if we had ſome place opened to us to look into the Lake that burns with fire and brimſtone for ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more, as the Prophet had a place open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>through the wall</hi> to ſee the Abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions that were done by the houſe of <hi>Iſrael:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ezek. 8.7, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> Now while we do by Faith look to theſe things, and while we ſee the time of this life but <hi>as an handbreadth to Eternity;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſalm 39.5. Rom. 8.18.</note> we ſhall <hi>reckon the ſufferings of this preſent life, not worthy to be compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with the glory that ſhall be revealed in
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:97942:72"/>
us,</hi> nor any way anſwerable to thoſe miſeries which poor ſinners muſt be <hi>tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented with night and day for ever and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rev. 20.10.</note> Therefore as in our ſpiritual com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat we ſhould take to our ſelves Faith <hi>as a ſhield, to hold up againſt the fiery darts of the wicked;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Epheſ. 6.16.</note> ſo we ſhould take it to us as a Perſpective-glaſs, through the help of which we ſhall not only ſee afar off, beyond time to Eternity; but it will bring the things of the world to come nearer to us, and make them ſeem as at hand; for tho they be not really nearer, yet that diſtance of time which they are at from us, will ſeem as nothing, when we compare it with that Eternity which is beyond time, wherein we muſt be for ever happy or miſerable, according to what we propound to our ſelves as our chief end.</p>
               <p>And let us but conſider what is the principle that all the world is acted by, what is the ſpring that moves the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral wheels that are moving ſome one way and ſome another; or what is it that (as it is ſaid concerning <hi>Noah</hi>) doth comfort men concerning their work, and toil of their hands; but the hopes of future Advantages, Honour, Riches: for theſe the Soldier expoſes himſelf to a thouſand hardſhips and hazards: The Merchant leaves his Friends and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try,
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:97942:73"/>
try, and commits himſelf to the waves, runs the riſque of ſuffering Shipwrack, being taken by Pyrates, and ſubjected to perpetual Slavery: And if we do run the like hazards for the profeſſion of Religion, which men ſeldom do; let us by this Perſpective look before us, not only to the recompence of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward which will abundantly anſwer all our loſſes and ſufferings; but to the penalty that we ſhall incur if we do not by patient continuance in well-doing wait for Honour and Glory and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality, there being no middle place between Heaven and Hell.</p>
               <p>And let us but conſider the difference betwixt our caſe and the caſe of thoſe that endure ſuch hardſhips, and run ſuch hazards for the things of this world. The Apoſtle ſets it forth in two things, borrowing a ſimilitude from things then in uſe amongſt them; <hi>one did ſtrive for a corruptible crown,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 9.25, 26.</note> a Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land of Flowers or Lawrel: the other for <hi>a crown of Glory that fades not away.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Pet. 5.4.</note> The one did run uncertainly, the other with more aſſurance of ſucceſs. So here there is no compariſon betwixt what we ſhall receive through Faith and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, and what men receive as the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of their labours and ſufferings here in this world; either for the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:97942:73"/>
or for the continuance of it, and we are at greater certainties about it. Here <hi>the race is not to the ſwift,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eccl. 9.11.</note> 
                  <hi>nor the battel to the ſtrong, nor bread to the wiſe, nor riches to men of underſtanding, nor favour to men of skill; but time and chance happens to all.</hi> But if we be <hi>ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſt, unmoveable, abounding always in the Lord's work, we may know that our labour ſhall not be in vain in the Lord.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.58.</note>
               </p>
               <p>I ſhould here conclude; but that as the Apoſtle would <hi>provoke</hi> the <hi>Jews</hi> to <hi>emulation</hi> by the Gentiles, ſo I would by a <hi>Heathen,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 11.14.</note> provoke Chriſtians to look by Faith to the things which are not ſeen, which are eternal. <hi>Seneca</hi> in the beginning of his Preface to his Natural Queſtions, ſhews, <q>That as there is a difference betwixt Pholoſophy and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Arts, ſo there is a difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt that part of Philoſophy which reſpects men, and that which reſpects God. This latter <hi>(he ſaith)</hi> is more high and ſprightly, and ſuppoſes ſomething greater and more beautiful, which Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture hath placed out of ſight; and unleſs he might be admitted to theſe things, he ſhould not think it worth the while to be born, or to take ſuch pains; and adds, O how contemptible a thing is man, if he do not raiſe up himſelf above human things!</q> If an
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:97942:74"/>
                  <hi>Heathen</hi> could ſpeak thus, what a ſhame is it for us that have the help of Divine Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation, to fall under the reproach and cenſure of thoſe that mind earthly things? It is by faith alone that we can look to thoſe things out of ſight; let us thereby raiſe up our ſelves to take a view of the other World, both the good and evil things of it, and this will ſo raiſe and enlarge our minds, that we ſhall have meaner thoughts of the things of this life, and not concern our ſelves ſo far in the purſuit of the good things of the world, or in the avoiding the evil things of it, as thereby to be taken off from minding thoſe things that are above; or ſo as to run the hazard of falling ſhort of that reſt, which we have a promiſe left us of entring in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. X.</head>
               <p>HAving treated thus far of the <hi>na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> of Faith, and the <hi>benefit</hi> and advantage that Criſtians have thereby: I ſhall now add ſomething for <hi>encoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging perſons to believe,</hi> and for <hi>directing</hi> them the rein. And whereas ſome ſpeak of the Souls preparation for Chriſt, I will endeavour to ſhew you briefly and
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:97942:74"/>
plainly what is required in order to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving. And firſt, <hi>there</hi> is nothing to be done in order to our believing, which may <hi>commend us to Chriſt for his acceptance.</hi> It is ſaid, a <hi>mans gift makes room for him,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prov. 18.16.</note> 
                  <hi>and brings him before great Men; by means</hi> thereof, he hath free acceſs to great Men, and finds favour with them. But we can bring neither price nor <hi>preſent</hi> to Chriſt,<note place="margin">Iſaiah 61.10. Cant. 8.10.</note> nor come to him as a <hi>Bride adorned with Jewels,</hi> that we may be in his eyes as one that finds favour: we muſt rather come to Chriſt that we <hi>may buy of him Gold tried in the fire,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rev. 3.18. Iſaiah 55.1.</note> that we may be rich, and <hi>white raiment to cover our nakedneſs,</hi> and <hi>eye-ſalve to anoint our eyes;</hi> and we muſt buy this <hi>without mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, and without price.</hi> It is (as they ſpeak) the antecedent put for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequent;<note place="margin">Judg. 2.14. Pſalm 44.12.</note> as God is ſaid to <hi>ſell</hi> his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, when he delivers them into the hands of their Enemies, tho he ſell them <hi>for nought;</hi> becauſe in ſelling, there is a delivering of what is ſold, into the hands of the Buyer. So we are ſaid to <hi>buy,</hi> when we make a thing our own, or get it into our own hands.<note place="margin">Ezek. 16.</note> Tho the Prophet ſpeaks chiefly of the mean Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of the <hi>Jews,</hi> when God took them to be his peculiar people, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced them to ſuch greatneſs; yet that was a Repreſentation of the State
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:97942:75"/>
and Condition wherein God finds Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, when he chuſes them out of the World, and ſets than apart for himſelf. <hi>Our righteouſneſs is but as filthy rags.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſaiah 64.6.</note> Theſe do not reach to cover a man's Nakedneſs, but it is ſeen through them; and if they be filthy rags, they rather make a perſon more loathſome, than become an Ornament to him, ſo far as they do reach. So our beſt Works, or Duties, reach but a little way, they extend but to a ſmall part of our lives; and ſo far as they do reach, they are polluted and defiled with ſin. We muſt not come with our own righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs to Chriſt, <hi>but we muſt be married to Chriſt, that we may bring forth fruit to God.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 7.4.</note> And if any ſay, we are <hi>married to Chriſt by faith,</hi> and ſo muſt receive that Grace whereby we believe, before we are married to him. I anſwer, It is in this caſe, as it happens in ſome Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ages. If a mean perſon marry one that is much above her, tho ſhe be entitled by Marriage to what is her Husband's, if ſhe hath not wherewithal to bear the Charge of the Marriage, or to come to him, as <hi>Rebecca</hi> did to <hi>Iſaac,</hi> ſhe muſt take on truſt what will defray this Charge, on the Credit ſhe hath by ſuch a deſigned Marriage, or be furniſhed with what is neceſſary from him. So,
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:97942:75"/>
tho we are entitled to the benefits of Chriſt, by our believing on him; yet <hi>it is given to us to believe on him for his ſake;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Phil 1.29.</note> through whom we receive the firſt Grace, as well as all the reſt.</p>
               <p n="2">2. There is nothing required in us to make the Grace of God to become effectual. He doth not as thoſe that make choice of ſuch as nature hath qualified or fitted for improvement to great employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; or take the advantage of any good humour which he finds men in, that may diſpoſe them to Eternal Life, as ſome interpret the words of the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangeliſt, which in our Tranſlation, <hi>were ordained to eternal life.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Acts 13.48.</note> 
                  <hi>Nebuchad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nezzar,</hi> when he would take ſome of the Children of the Captivity to train up for his Service, choſe ſuch as were well-favoured, or fightly; <hi>and ſuch as were skilful in all wiſdom, and cunning in knowledge, and underſtanding ſcience, and ſuch as had ability.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Daniel 1.4.</note> But God doth not ſeek out ſuch for his Service; He makes <hi>the heart of the raſh to underſtand knowledg, and the tongue of the ſtammerers to ſpeak plainly.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſaiah 32.4.</note> The Carpenter indeed muſt look out ſuch Wood as is naturally fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for his uſe; he cannot make a crooked piece ſtraight by bending, or make a knotty piece cleave. But a Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der can take any piece of Metal of
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:97942:76"/>
what ſize or form ſoever, or however ruſty, or batter'd, and caſt it into what Mold or Form he pleaſes. So <hi>God can of ſtones raiſe up children to Abraham.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Matth. 3.9.</note> And as he ſhews the freeneſs and riches of his Mercy in chuſing the worſt of Sinners; ſo he ſhews the power of his Grace, in making a thorough change in thoſe in whom he finds the moſt deep-rooted Prejudices againſt the Goſpel. He turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Paul</hi> when he was in his full Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reer towards Hell; while <hi>he was breath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out threatnings and ſlaughter againſt the Church;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Acts 9.1.</note> and verily thought he ought to do many things againſt <hi>the name of Jeſus of Nazareth;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">and 26.9. Gal. 1.23, 24.</note> 
                  <hi>ſo that they glorified God in him,</hi> when they ſaw ſuch a won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful change wrought in him.</p>
               <p>But tho there be nothing in us which may oblige God to beſtow his Grace on us, or facilitate his Work in our Converſion, or drawing us to Chriſt; yet as Faith is our Act, there is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing required in order thereto, <hi>that we may believe with all our heart,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Acts 8.37.</note> or free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and willingly take hold on God's Covenant.<note place="margin">Prov. 27.7. Matth. 7.6. Matth. 11.28. Revel. 22.17.</note> 
                  <hi>The full ſtomach loathes the hony comb, and ſwine will tread pearls under their feet.</hi> Therefore only thoſe <hi>that are weary and heavy laden,</hi> and thoſe <hi>that thirſt, are invited to come to Chriſt,</hi> becauſe none but ſuch will come. <hi>John</hi> asks <hi>the
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:97942:76"/>
Phariſees</hi> and <hi>Sadduces,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Matth. 3.7.</note> 
                  <hi>Who had warned them to flee from the wrath to come;</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he doth not, I ſuppoſe, mean <hi>the wrath that was to come upon that nation</hi> by the <hi>Romans:</hi> but <hi>the damnation of Hell,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luke 21.23. Matth. 23.33. 1 Theſ. 1.10.</note> as our Saviour elſewhere calls it: T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s is <hi>the wrath to come, which Jeſus deliver<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> from:</hi> The <hi>Sadduces</hi> did not believe that there was any Future ſtate, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently <hi>any wrath to come:</hi> The <hi>Phariſees truſted in themſelves that they were righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous,</hi> and ſo could not apprehend any danger of the wrath to come. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he ſeems to queſtion their ſincerity in the profeſſion which they made, and requires them to bring forth fruit meet for repentance, and not to ground their hopes upon their Deſcent from <hi>Abraham.</hi> As men are to <hi>give a reaſon of the hope that is in them,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Peter 3.15.</note> ſo they ſhould have ſome reaſon for their <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving,</hi> or coming to God by Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p>I ſhall take the liberty here to refer to what hath been ſaid by a Grave So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber man on this Subject, he being a perſon that none will ſuſpect of going too far on this hand.<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhal</hi> in the Goſpel My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification, <hi>p. 207,</hi> &amp;c.</note> In the Inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that he gives to prevent the defects that we are moſt liable to in the firſt Act of Faith, he tells us, 1. We muſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve with a full perſwaſion, that we are
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:97942:77"/>
Children of Wrath by Nature, ſubject to the Curſe of the Law, the Power of Satan, and inſupportable miſery to all Eternity. 2. We muſt believe aſſured<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that there is no way to be ſaved, without receiving all the ſaving bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits of Chriſt; his Spirit as well as his Merits, Sanctification as well as Remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Sins by Faith: It being (as he ſaith) the ruin of many ſouls, that they truſt on Chriſt for the remiſſion of Sins, without any regard to Holineſs, when as theſe two benefits are inſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly joined in Chriſt [He herein grants more than many will deſire of him, that men ſhould aſſuredly believe this in the firſt Act of Faith]. 3. We muſt be fully perſwaded of the all-ſufficiency of Chriſt for the Salvation of our ſelves, and all that believe on him. 4. We are to be fully perſwaded of the truth of the general Free-promiſe in our own particular caſe. 5. We are to believe aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuredly that it is the Will of God that we ſhould believe in Chriſt, and have Eternal Life by him, as well as any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Now, without the two former of theſe, we ſhall not mind coming to Chriſt, but ſhall make light of him; without the others, we ſhall have little encouragement to come to him.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="129" facs="tcp:97942:77"/>Now if any ſhall enquire whether theſe things which are perpatory to our believing or coming to Chriſt, be in our own power, or are the effects of God's Grace in us, and whether con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion do always follow thereupon; I Anſwer,</p>
               <p>There are ſome things as much in our own power, as any of our natural or moral actions are, that may have a ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency to our converſion: and therefore the Prophet complains of <hi>Iſrael,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hoſ. 5.4.</note> that <hi>they did not frame their doings to turn to the Lord.</hi> And there is a Sermon in the Morning Exerciſe, Publiſhed in the Year 1661.<note place="margin">☜</note> reputed to be Mr. <hi>Greenhills</hi> (who was a perſon far from the ſuſpicion of aſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing too much to the power of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture) which reſolves the queſtion, what perſons muſt, and can do towards their own converſion. Now it is certain that men may as well go by their Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural power where the word is prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, as to places of temptation. And there they are within the call of the Goſpel; and ſo are as the impotent perſons at the Pool of <hi>Betheſda,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Jo. 5.1, &amp;c. 1 Cor. 3.5, &amp;c. Rom. 10:17 Luk. 8.12.</note> in a nearer capacity of cure, if it pleaſe God by his Spirit to <hi>give increaſe</hi> to what is <hi>planted and watered:</hi> for <hi>faith comes by hearing:</hi> and therefore <hi>the Devil endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to divert our minds from what we
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:97942:78"/>
hear, leſt we ſhould believe and be ſaved.</hi> We ſee further how much it is in man's power to bend his mind to the ſtudy of any particular ſubject: we ſee it plainly not only in mens chuſing in general the ſtudy of Law, Phyſick, or Divinity; but thoſe that addict them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the ſtudy of Divinity, chuſe any particular point thereof to treat on. And they who give not the leaſt ground of hope, that there is any ſaving work upon their own ſouls, will preſs upon others ſuch things as the conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of, may incline and diſpoſe them to believing;<note place="margin">Ezek. 18.14, 28. Pſal. 119.59. Rom. 2 23.</note> and men have the ſame natural power to teach themſelves, which they have to <hi>teach others.</hi> But all this will not reach to converſion, any farther than God is pleaſed to give to every one.</p>
               <p>I will now ſhew you what God doth towards the converſion of ſinners, or which may have a tendency thereto; Some things he doth by his Providence, which he makes many times ſubſervient to his Grace.<note place="margin">Acts 17.26.</note> He that <hi>determines the bounds of mens habitation,</hi> caſts them into ſuch places where they may hear the Goſpel preached plainly, ſeriouſly, by ſuch as <hi>perſuade men,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Cor. 5.11.</note> as knowing the terror of the Lord. And he may ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe them under ſome affliction, which
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:97942:78"/>
may be as a ground-rain ſoaking to the roots, and ſoftning the clods, and turning them to mold, that the ſeed that hath been long buried may ſpring up, of that which perſons have a long time before heard, and never thought of after; when ſome humbling affliction befalls them, <hi>they bethink themſelves,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Kings 8.47.</note> 
                  <hi>and repent.</hi> But ſuch works fall ſhort many times of true Converſion;<note place="margin">Hoſ. 6.4. Gen. 20.6. Jo. 16.8.</note> and this <hi>good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs proves but as the morning cloud, or early dew which paſſes away.</hi> God doth ſomething further by his common grace, reſtraining men from much evil. I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, I think our Saviour, where he ſpeaks of the Spirit's reproving or convincing the World, underſtands the World of ſuch whom he choſe his Diſciples out of, and diſtinguiſhes them from; but I think it is not intended of any inward working of the Spirit upon their hearts, but of thoſe Miracles which he wrought, which confirmed the truth of Chriſt's Reſurrection, and of his Doctrine. By ſuch means as I have now mentioned, men may be brought near the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Heaven, but never enter into it.<note place="margin">Mark. 12.34. <hi>See</hi> Caſſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der's <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſultation,</hi> p. 45.</note>
               </p>
               <p>But thoſe preparations which Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion doth follow upon, <hi>are</hi> (as the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berer Papiſts acknowledge) <hi>wrought by Gods Grace and Spirit.</hi> He enlightens the
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:97942:79"/>
mind ſo as we have a more clear ſight of Heavenly things, and other appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſions of them than before we had when it pleaſes God to <hi>reveal his Son in us;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gal. 1.16. Iſa. 53.2. Cant 5.10. Jo. 6.44, 45.</note> he that before had no form nor comelineſs in our eyes, nor any beauty that we ſhould deſire him, is now the chief of Ten thouſands in our account, and <hi>altogether lovely.</hi> God draws us to Chriſt by teaching; tho I do not think that all the efficacy of God's Grace con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts in propounding things to the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, or in enlightening the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding to conceive aright of them. But by a ſecret touch of his Spirit, he ſo effectually inclines our hearts to him,<note place="margin">1 Kings 8.57. Phil. 2.20.</note> that we do in a ſort <hi>naturally mind ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual things:</hi> that is, freely, without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint. This of the Spirit's enlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the mind, is not a peculiar notion of <hi>Enthuſiaſts,</hi> but the commonly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived Doctrine of ſober Proteſtants. So Biſhop <hi>Pierſon</hi> on the Article of the Holy Ghoſt, in his Expoſition of the Creed tells us, The work of the Spirit is double, external and general, or inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal and particular: By the former he reveals the will of God to the whole Church, by the latter he illuminates the underſtanding of particular be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers, that they may receive the truth; the Holy Ghoſt working in us an aſſent
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:97942:79"/>
to that which is by the word propound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. Again, God doth by his Spirit convince us ſpiritually of our ſtate and condition; <hi>and the word,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eph. 6.17. Heb. 4.12. Acts 2.37.</note> 
                  <hi>which is the ſword of the Spirit, and ſharper than any two-edged Sword, piercing to the dividing aſunder be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the Soul and the Spirit, the joynts and the marrow;</hi> pricking ſinners at <hi>the heart,</hi> ſo as it ſhall be as a Sword in their bones; and thoſe ſins which they went lightly under before (as <hi>David</hi> did un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his) are now a heavy burden,<note place="margin">2 Sam. 11. Pſal. 38.4.</note> too heavy for them. And theſe convicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons he makes as a bearded arrow, which while men endeavour to ſhake off, tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment them more, and they ſhall not be able to put off the thoughts of their ſins, but (as <hi>David</hi>'s) they ſhall be <hi>continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally before them;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 51.3.</note> ſo that they ſhall have no reſt in their ſpirits till they come to Chriſt.</p>
               <p>But now doubts do ordinarily ariſe in the minds of Chriſtians, whether they be rightly humbled; whether they be ſufficiently humbled; whether they have been long enough under theſe preparations.</p>
               <p n="1">1. They are ready to ſuſpect that their trouble for ſin is not kindly, that it is rather from ſelf-love, and fear of puniſhments, than from love to God,
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:97942:80"/>
and ſenſe of the nature of ſin, as it is againſt God, and diſpleaſing to him.</p>
               <p>Now to this I anſwer, That God hath placed our affections in the Soul, as handles to take hold on it, and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly,<note place="margin">Jer. 32.40. Prov. 16.6.</note> Fear: and he doth not only after converſion <hi>put his fear into our hearts</hi> (or at leaſt continue it there) <hi>that we may not depart from him,</hi> but may thereby <hi>depart from evil;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 2.17.</note> but he gave an intimidating threatning to man in the ſtate of innocency, to be a means to keep him from ſin. And at firſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion we ordinarily <hi>flee from the wrath to come;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Matt. 3.7. Heb. 6.18.</note> or to avoid that, <hi>flee for refuge to lay hold on the hope that is ſet before us.</hi> But there is a frequent exerciſe of Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal repentance after Converſion. Men eſpy a Tree in a ſtorm, or in the heat, and betake themſelves to it for ſhelter or ſhade: but when they come at it, they find fruit which they did not at ſuch a diſtance ſee, or in ſuch a fright or trouble conſider; but having found it, they are (at laſt) as much pleaſed with it, as with the covert or umbrage of it. So we <hi>ſit under the ſhadow of Chriſt with great delight, and his fruit is ſweet to our taſte.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cant. 2.3.</note> In Marriage, Eſtate and Conveniences of Life are firſt trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of, and conjugal love increaſes by ſociety or converſe; you have firſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:97942:80"/>
your ſelves to Chriſt, or deſire to come to him to ſave you from Hell, but doth this (upon ſecond thoughts) ſatisfy you? Can you content your ſelves herewith? or rather do you not deſire that he would <hi>bleſs you in turning you from your iniquities,</hi> and ſay with <hi>Paul, Lord,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Acts 3.26. Acts 9.6.</note> 
                  <hi>what wouldeſt thou have me to do?</hi> It matters not ſo much what is our firſt motive to bring us to Chriſt, if it do not terminate our deſires, when we have occaſion and opportunity more fully to conſider things. A man may addreſs himſelf to a perſon at firſt on the account of her Portion, to pay his debts, and keep him out of Priſon, and anſwer ſome other occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: but upon further knowledge of her, when he is freed from his debts, and extrica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted out of his troubles, he finds thoſe accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhments and qualifications in her which are a more abundant ſatisfaction to him than all her Eſtate.</p>
               <p>For the fear of Chriſtians that they have not been ſufficiently humbled, and ſo that they ſhould have the wounds of their conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences healed ſlightly, before they be ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently ſearched or drawn; I anſwer, It is true when perſons have been throughly hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled for their ſin, it may work in them a greater averſion from it, and a more fixed reſolution againſt it. As when <hi>Ephraim</hi> had ſuffered much for their ſin of Idolatry,<note place="margin">Hoſ. 14.3, 8.</note> 
                  <hi>they would not ſay any more to the work of their hands, ye are my Gods:</hi> but <hi>would rather ſay, what have I to do any more with Idols?</hi> and tho the <hi>Jews</hi> were much addicted to Idolatry, yet the deſtruction of their Temple and City by the <hi>Caldeans,</hi> and their Captivity in <hi>Babylon,</hi> did much reclaim them from it. Yea, God is pleaſed to deal variouſly with perſons, either
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:97942:81"/>
according as their former converſations have been; where mens ſins have been notorious, God doth many times make their Repentance as notorious, or as the frame and temper of their hearts is:<note place="margin">Iſa. 28.26.</note> he that inſtructs the husband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man to uſe ſeveral means for getting out his Corn, as the nature of it requires, or as it is threſhed with more eaſe or difficulty; doth himſelf exerciſe perſons under affliction as need requires, till he hath brought their uncircum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed hearts to be humbled, to accept of the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of their iniquity.<note place="margin">Levit 16.41.</note> And ſo in bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Souls to Jeſus Chriſt, he exerciſes them un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der different degrees of humiliation, as he ſees their ſtate to require; or as he intends for the future to deal with them: But thoſe that have to do with troubled Souls, or ſuch as are hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled under a ſenſe of their ſin, ſhould take heed of tampering too much in keeping them down, leſt they do as Phyſicians; who that they may throughly ſubdue a diſeaſe, bring their Patients ſo low, that they cannot recover their ſtrength, and raiſe them up again: and let Chriſtians themſelves take heed, leſt out of a miſtaken modeſty or humility, they think they can never be ſufficiently humbled, <hi>and ſo refuſe to be comforted.</hi> It is not for us to teach our Phyſicians,<note place="margin">Pſalm 77.2.</note> or to preſcribe to God how he ſhould deal with us: I have heard of an Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Man, who (in a deep humility) deſired that God would ſhew him his ſin in its own co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours; or let him ſee the deformity of it, that he might be yet more humbled for it; and God did ſhew it to him ſo as to make him go mourning to his grave. And I have likewiſe heard of a wowan, that made the like requeſt to God, thinking ſhe could never be ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently humbled for her ſin. But it pleaſed God
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:97942:81"/>
to give her ſuch a ſight of her Sin, that (like <hi>Heman) while ſhe ſuffer'd his terrors,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſalm 88.15.</note> 
                  <hi>ſhe was diſtracted;</hi> and in that Condition killed her own Child. It is the end that determines the manner and meaſure of the means leading thereto. And that Humiliation and Convi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction is ſufficient, that makes us willing to forſake our Sin, and come to Chriſt. A kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Sorrow and Trouble for Sin,<note place="margin">Jer. 31.19. Ezek. 16.63.</note> may grow upon us (as I lately ſaid) after Converſion, and Senſe of Pardon.</p>
               <p>For the other doubt of Chriſtians, that they have not been long enough under the pangs of the New Birth, (as they ſpeak) and know not whether they may not be too forward to believe.</p>
               <p>I anſwer, That if by believing, we mean <hi>a perſwaſion or confidence, that our ſins are pardoned;</hi> we may believe too ſoon.<note place="margin">P. 172.</note> And Mr. <hi>Marſhall</hi> (in the forementioned Treatiſe) notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all that he hath ſaid of Aſſurance being Eſſential to Faith, acknowledges, That many muſt be taught to doubt, whether their preſent State be good, and that it is Humility ſo to do; that we muſt find out the certainty and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity of our Faith and Obedience, by Self-examination, before we can have a well-grounded Aſſurance, that we are in a ſtate of Grace and Salvation already; and that ſuch an Aſſurance belongs to the reflect Act of Faith, and is not of the Eſſence of that Faith where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we are juſtified and ſaved. But if by believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, we mean <hi>coming to God by Jeſus Chriſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 119.60. 1 John 3.23. Eſther 2.12.</note> we ſhould <hi>make haſte and not delay to keep this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand,</hi> as well as others. We are not to think, that as the Queens of <hi>Perſia</hi> were to be prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red <hi>Six months with oyl of myrrh, and ſix months with ſweet odours, and other things,</hi> before they
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:97942:82"/>
might be admitted to the King; ſo we muſt continue ſuch a time under Humiliation, and ſo long under Contrition, before we may preſume to come to Chriſt. <hi>For tho</hi> (it is true) <hi>we ſhould count the coſt</hi> of being his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples,<note place="margin">Luke 14.28. Matth. 13.21.</note> for want of which many (as it is in the Parable of the Sower) are forward to hear the word with joy, and believe for a time, but afterwards fall away; yet it is not ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary that we ſuſpend our believing till we have throughly weighed every thing. It is not in this caſe as in ordinary Marriages, where Perſons ſhould inform themſelves well of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very particular before they engage, becauſe when once engaged it will be too late to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, or to make a better choice. But it is herein, as if a Perſon had one propounded to her, that ſhe muſt Marry, or be undone; and one who (they know) will put her upon no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, or require nothing of her which ſhe can juſtly except againſt, in whom there is nothing that ſhe can diſlike; there can be no danger or inconvenience in finiſhing ſuch a Match, without further delay. So if there were any other Name whereby we could be ſaved; if Chriſt did put us upon any thing, or require any thing of us which Heaven will not countervail; or if he would not have us yet come to him, we might defer our be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving. And tho ſomething is to be done (as I have ſaid) to make us willing to come to Chriſt, yet there is no long time required for the Soul to continue in a State of Prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration; the whole Work hath been done at once,<note place="margin">Acts 2. Acts 9. Acts 16. Vol. 2. 148.</note> as we ſee in thoſe that were converted at <hi>Peter</hi>'s Sermons, in <hi>Paul,</hi> in the Jaylor: As Mr. <hi>Charnock</hi> doth ingeniouſly illuſtrate it: The preparation of the Subject is neceſſary,
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:97942:82"/>
but this preparation may be at the ſame time with the conveyance of the Divine Nature. As a warm Seal may both prepare the hard Wax, and convey the Image to it by one and the ſame touch.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XI.</head>
               <p>I Will finiſh all with a few words about the Neceſſity of Holineſs, both for the allaying of thoſe heats that are amongſt ſome about it, and for preventing or removing the Preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dices of Men againſt it. There is no need of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhing betwixt the Neceſſity of Holineſs or Obedience, to the beginning of our Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification, and to the Continuation of it, among thoſe that (according to the Doctrine of the Church of <hi>England</hi>) believe the Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance of the Saints, and that there is no In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terciſion of Juſtification. But there is a Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of Holineſs in thoſe that are juſtified; for tho we may be juſtified at firſt by ſuch a Faith as is only in tendency to obedience, but wants time and opportunity to put it ſelf forth; yet, where Faith is unfeigned (and only ſuch Faith juſtifies) it will, as there is occaſion and opportunity, <hi>work by love;</hi> ſo,<note place="margin">Gal. 5.6. 1 Cor. 6.11. Heb. 12.14.</note> that <hi>whom God doth juſtify in the name of Chriſt, he doth alſo ſanctify by his ſpirit;</hi> therefore <hi>with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out holineſs none ſhall ſee God;</hi> Yet we are not to think that Holineſs is required on the ſame account with Faith, much leſs in co-ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with the righteouſneſs of Chriſt. I doubt it is a piece of ordinary Chriſtian's Divinity, that the righteouſneſs of Chriſt ſerves only as grains of allowance to make our righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs currant where it is too light. But
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:97942:83"/>
as Chriſt hath no ſharers in his Mediation, ſo neither is there any thing needful to be added to his ſatisfaction; but we are acquitted only upon the account thereof; and whatever we do, ſerves not for ſo much as grains of allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance to make his ſatisfaction currant with God for us.</p>
               <p>But yet it is neceſſary upon other accounts, not only becauſe God will inſiſt on it, as a thing condecent to his Holineſs, <hi>who is of purer eyes than to behold evil;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 1.13.</note> but there is a natural <hi>neceſſity of it as a means to our chief end,</hi> which is to <hi>glorify God, and enjoy him.</hi> As when <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> choſe ſome of the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity to ſerve under him,<note place="margin">Dan. 1.3, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> he would not only have them well-favoured, and fed with the King's Meat and Wine, that they might ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear ſightly before the King; but had ſuch choſen as had good Natural Abilities, and had them taught the Learning and Language of the <hi>Caldeans,</hi> that they might be fit to do him Service. So God doth not only delight in Holineſs, but indeed without that, we are not fit to ſerve him; we are <hi>naturally repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate to every good work;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Tit. 1.16.</note> and we muſt be God's workmanſhip, created in Chriſt Jeſus to thoſe good Works which he hath before ordained, that we ſhould walk in them. But it is likewiſe neceſſary, that we may <hi>enjoy that happineſs which he hath prepared for us.</hi> He brings in the <hi>Highways and Hedges,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luke 14.23.</note> the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt and moſt unworthy to partake of his Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. But if a King ſhould invite thoſe that are Sick, and that of ſome loathſome Diſeaſe, to eat at his Table; if he would of his Boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Goodneſs diſpenſe with the ſmell and loathſomeneſs of their Diſeaſe; it would be no favour to them (in the Condition wherein
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:97942:83"/>
they are) to ſit at the King's Table, while their Sickneſs makes them nauſeate every thing there, and the ſmell of Meat to be offenſive to them: But it would be a favour indeed, to be firſt recovered from their Diſeaſe, that they might not be aſhamed to appear in ſuch a place, and that they might be able to reliſh their Meat and Drink. This is our caſe, as we are unfit to appear before God (in the ſtate wherein we are) to whom our inner<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man is as naked and open, as our outward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man is to men like our ſelves. So we are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ogether uncapable of that Comfort and Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs, which is to be found in the Preſence of God, or of the foretaſts of it, which he gives his People in this Life. Whatever Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency there is in any thing, we muſt have a Senſe or Faculty correſpondent therewith, or elſe we cannot underſtand or enjoy any thing of it. There is a Beauty in a Roſe, and in other Flowers, which thoſe that have their ſight may enjoy the pleaſure of; but there is further a ſweet ſmell, or fragrancy in them, which the ſight intermeddles not with; and there muſt be another ſenſe, of Smelling, to enjoy the pleaſure thereof. So neither can we enjoy the pleaſure of Wine without the ſenſe of Taſting, or of Muſick without the ſenſe of Hearing. So likewiſe, if a man do not underſtand any thing of Learning, or have no Genius thereto, he cannot take any pleaſure in reading Books, or in Academical Exerciſes, which are better than Wine and Muſick to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. So, if a man be not ſanctified or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed after the Image of God, tho he would diſpenſe with his Sin, and admit him to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, he would ſay of it (as of the Service of God) <hi>what a wearineſs is it;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mal. 1.13.</note> he might be
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:97942:84"/>
content to be there to be kept out of Hell, as here he might be content to be in a place where there is a Sermon, to be ſheltred from a ſtorm. It was to no purpoſe for <hi>Barzilla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> to go to <hi>David's</hi> Court, when nature was ſo decayed in him that he could not enjoy any of the pleaſures of it.<note place="margin">2 Sam. 19.35.</note>
               </p>
               <p>If it be ſaid, this doth not infer any neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of Holineſs here in this life; for God can in a moment at death fit us for Heaven, which is eaſily done, when we lay down this body, which is both a clog and a temptation to the Soul, not only as it influences the Soul, but as moſt of our ſins are in order to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide for the body, or to fulfil the luſts of the fleſh. I anſwer,</p>
               <p>There is a neceſſity of Holineſs here, part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as there is ſuch an inſeparable connexion betwixt that and <hi>Faith which works by love,</hi> and <hi>is dead without works:</hi> this purifies the heart, <hi>overcomes the world;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gal. 5.6. Jam. 2.24. Acts 15.9. 1 John 5.4. Heb. 11. Iſa. 43.21. Titus 2.14. Luk. 1.74, 75.</note> and the Apoſtle ſpends an whole chapter in ſetting forth the virtue of it. Beſides, it is the pleaſure of God to form a people for himſelf, that they may in this world <hi>ſhew forth his praiſe;</hi> and hath redeemed us to be <hi>a peculiar people to himſelf,</hi> that we may ſerve him <hi>in holineſs and righteouſneſs before him all the days of our life:</hi> He would have our light ſhine ſo before men, <hi>that they ſeeing our good works, may glorify our father which is in Heaven:</hi> ſo that we do hereby keep up his Honour, and a Remembrance of him in the world. We have hereby likewiſe ſome preliba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions or foretaſtes of future Glory, which (as I have already ſaid) we are not capable of without Holineſs;<note place="margin">Numb. 13.23.</note> God would have ſome of the fruits of the Land of <hi>Canaan</hi> brought to the people in the Wilderneſs, that (ſeeing what goodly
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:97942:84"/>
fruit it was) they might be the more encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged to go to poſſeſs it, notwithſtanding the difficulties and dangers that they were to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter with; and there is nothing that doth more raiſe our thoughts of future Glory, than the earneſt that we have of it here; which we can no more underſtand without Holineſs, than we can the ſweetneſs and vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of Wine by hearſay without taſting: We have hereby likewiſe a more lively ſenſe of the Goodneſs of God to us, in delivering us from the ſinful ſtate wherein we are by nature; than we could have, if we were perfected at once at death. If a man be ſuddenly ſurpriz'd with an Apoplexy, and immediately at once recovered from it, he hath not ſuch a ſenſe of the Mercy that he hath received therein, as one that is recovered by degrees from a Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, or ſome other Diſeaſe, wherein he hath felt much of pain, ſickneſs, weakneſs; and hath, not only known what it was to be revi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by Cordials, to be helped by Friends, to to be eaſed by reſt in his bed; but after his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery he can reflect with pleaſure upon his former condition when it is paſt, and more prize his preſent Eaſe and Health. So thoſe who have with the Apoſtle groaned under a body of ſin and death, will not only reflect with pleaſure upon the ſupplies of God's Grace which they have had to ſtrengthen them in their Spiritual conflict, and to fortify them againſt temptations: but will afterwards with more thankfulneſs acknowledge the goodneſs of God, in giving them the victory through our Lord Jeſus, and bringing them into a ſtate of perfection, where they ſhall be freed from all annoyance of ſin and temptations, which they could never have ſo well underſtood, had
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:97942:85"/>
it not been for the experience which they had in that middle ſtate, wherein they found ſuch a conflict while they were under cure, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covering by degrees. So that it is a great miſtake in any, to think that holineſs is not neceſſary, if we may be juſtified without it, or that juſtification is our great priviledge, and holineſs a burden impoſed upon us, which we muſt be content to ſubmit to, in conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſo great a favour as the pardon of our ſins. Holineſs is rather our honor and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs,<note place="margin">Rom. 6.22. 1 Theſ 1.10. Acts 3.26.</note> the preſt of fruit of our being the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of God here; and Chriſt doth not only ſave us from our ſins in <hi>delivering us from the wrath to come;</hi> but <hi>by bleſſing us in turning us from our iniquities.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus have I briefly touched ſeveral things, which more Learned men have treated of with more clearneſs and acurateneſs: but I have not written to ſupply the defects of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, or to add to what they have done: but conſidering that this ſmall Treatiſe might fall into the hands of ſome, to whom it may not happen to read larger and more learned Books, I have adventured to write ſomething, which I hope may be of ſome uſe to them for the right underſtanding of the important truths therein handled: deſiring my Readers can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>didly to interpret what hath been well inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and to bear with that weakneſs which I am as ready to own as any can be to charge upon me.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:97942:85"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:97942:86"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:97942:86"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:97942:87" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:97942:87"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:97942:88"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:97942:88"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:97942:89"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:97942:89"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:97942:90"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:97942:90"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:97942:91"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:97942:91"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:97942:92"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:97942:92"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:97942:93"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:97942:93"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:97942:94"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:97942:94"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:97942:95"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:97942:95"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:97942:96"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:97942:96"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:97942:97"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:97942:97"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:97942:98"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:97942:98"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="60" facs="tcp:97942:99"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="61" facs="tcp:97942:99"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="62" facs="tcp:97942:100"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="63" facs="tcp:97942:100"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="64" facs="tcp:97942:101"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="65" facs="tcp:97942:101"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="66" facs="tcp:97942:102"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="67" facs="tcp:97942:102"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="68" facs="tcp:97942:103"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="69" facs="tcp:97942:103"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="70" facs="tcp:97942:104"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="71" facs="tcp:97942:104"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="72" facs="tcp:97942:105"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="73" facs="tcp:97942:105"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="74" facs="tcp:97942:106"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="75" facs="tcp:97942:106"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="76" facs="tcp:97942:107"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="77" facs="tcp:97942:107"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="78" facs="tcp:97942:108"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="79" facs="tcp:97942:108"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="80" facs="tcp:97942:109"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="81" facs="tcp:97942:109"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="82" facs="tcp:97942:110"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="83" facs="tcp:97942:110"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="84" facs="tcp:97942:111"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="85" facs="tcp:97942:111"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="86" facs="tcp:97942:112"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="87" facs="tcp:97942:112"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="88" facs="tcp:97942:113"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="89" facs="tcp:97942:113"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="90" facs="tcp:97942:114"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="91" facs="tcp:97942:114"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="92" facs="tcp:97942:115"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="93" facs="tcp:97942:115"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="94" facs="tcp:97942:116"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="95" facs="tcp:97942:116"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="96" facs="tcp:97942:117"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="97" facs="tcp:97942:117"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="98" facs="tcp:97942:118"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="99" facs="tcp:97942:118"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="100" facs="tcp:97942:119"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="101" facs="tcp:97942:119"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="102" facs="tcp:97942:120"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="103" facs="tcp:97942:120"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="104" facs="tcp:97942:121"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="105" facs="tcp:97942:121"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="130" facs="tcp:97942:122"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="131" facs="tcp:97942:122"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="132" facs="tcp:97942:123"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="133" facs="tcp:97942:123"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="134" facs="tcp:97942:124"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="135" facs="tcp:97942:124"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="136" facs="tcp:97942:125"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="137" facs="tcp:97942:125"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="138" facs="tcp:97942:126"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="139" facs="tcp:97942:126"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="140" facs="tcp:97942:127"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="141" facs="tcp:97942:127"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="142" facs="tcp:97942:128"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="143" facs="tcp:97942:128"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="144" facs="tcp:97942:129"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:97942:129"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
